<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts tagged `personal&apos;</title>
        <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        <generator>cl-ownpress</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <image>
            <title>Posts tagged `personal&apos;</title>
            <url>/images/avatar.png</url>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>Helping others to help myself</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd-help-others-to-help-yourself</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
It is near impossible for me to get something done if I don&apos;t have 100%
peaked interest in it at &lt;b&gt;this&lt;/b&gt; very moment. Occasionally I can hyper
focus on things, but that hyper focus rarely finish things. Hyper focus
is like eating all the desert, leaving behind a plate full of broccoli.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have noticed however that most of the times when I have actually
finished something, I was, in my mind, helping someone else.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reviewing the judicious documentation of my life, that is my journal, I
can say it for near about 100% of the things that I actually finished.
The force behind crossing the finishing line was either accountability,
or my belief that someone else is relying on me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of my own &quot;side projects&quot; have ever seen a ray of light, but most
things I started for others were finished. Mostly that was
presentations, processes, and very personally tailored learning
materials.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reviewing my journal, I noticed a pattern developing over the course of
last year. Whenever I had an idea that I wanted to see done, I tried to
frame it in somebody else&apos; canvas. If I could do that, I shared the idea
with the person and got them involved as a partner. Chances of success
I&apos;ve observed were directly proportional to how much I care for the
person. Some of the things I started that I couldn&apos;t fit in to help
someone else are still in &quot;TODO&quot; state, despite the long and clear
road-maps I created for them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This discovery of transforming emotions that come easily to me, into
what I believe I severely lack has sown seeds of new hope. Perhaps I
will be able to replace my need of accountability to get things done
with this. I don&apos;t know if it is vain need of acknowledgment, or
goodness of heart, but it works.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have started taking actions to optimize this. I am as anti-social as
they come, and that, now I believe, is a problem to be solved if I want
to increase my happiness.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most of my activities with other people don&apos;t register to my brain as
something it should remember. My mind is often meeting people for first
time despite several previous encounters. That is the first thing I am
going to tackle. Concrete step I am taking for this, is to start using
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/monicahq/monica/&quot;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt; to keep track of my
social life. Next step would be to actually start making effort to
socialize. I suppose saying &quot;hello&quot; to my colleagues every morning could
be a good start.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>coming-to-terms-with-adhd-help-others-to-help-yourself</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-05-13T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>