<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts tagged `adhd&apos;</title>
        <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        <generator>cl-ownpress</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <image>
            <title>Posts tagged `adhd&apos;</title>
            <url>/images/avatar.png</url>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>Helping others to help myself</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd-help-others-to-help-yourself</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
It is near impossible for me to get something done if I don&apos;t have 100%
peaked interest in it at &lt;b&gt;this&lt;/b&gt; very moment. Occasionally I can hyper
focus on things, but that hyper focus rarely finish things. Hyper focus
is like eating all the desert, leaving behind a plate full of broccoli.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have noticed however that most of the times when I have actually
finished something, I was, in my mind, helping someone else.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reviewing the judicious documentation of my life, that is my journal, I
can say it for near about 100% of the things that I actually finished.
The force behind crossing the finishing line was either accountability,
or my belief that someone else is relying on me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of my own &quot;side projects&quot; have ever seen a ray of light, but most
things I started for others were finished. Mostly that was
presentations, processes, and very personally tailored learning
materials.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reviewing my journal, I noticed a pattern developing over the course of
last year. Whenever I had an idea that I wanted to see done, I tried to
frame it in somebody else&apos; canvas. If I could do that, I shared the idea
with the person and got them involved as a partner. Chances of success
I&apos;ve observed were directly proportional to how much I care for the
person. Some of the things I started that I couldn&apos;t fit in to help
someone else are still in &quot;TODO&quot; state, despite the long and clear
road-maps I created for them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This discovery of transforming emotions that come easily to me, into
what I believe I severely lack has sown seeds of new hope. Perhaps I
will be able to replace my need of accountability to get things done
with this. I don&apos;t know if it is vain need of acknowledgment, or
goodness of heart, but it works.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have started taking actions to optimize this. I am as anti-social as
they come, and that, now I believe, is a problem to be solved if I want
to increase my happiness.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most of my activities with other people don&apos;t register to my brain as
something it should remember. My mind is often meeting people for first
time despite several previous encounters. That is the first thing I am
going to tackle. Concrete step I am taking for this, is to start using
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/monicahq/monica/&quot;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt; to keep track of my
social life. Next step would be to actually start making effort to
socialize. I suppose saying &quot;hello&quot; to my colleagues every morning could
be a good start.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>coming-to-terms-with-adhd-help-others-to-help-yourself</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-05-13T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Managing Chaos</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/managing-chaos-org-mode-as-a-todo-list</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I am thinking about doing a small series of posts on how I am managing
the chaos that I am trying to stop fighting. I hope the chaos of an ADHD
mind can be utilized rather than fought against. So far it has been
working out pretty great (for past ~8 months). This post is about how I
manage my ever exploding list of things I want to do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I believe one of the most important things is to externalize your
thoughts. Making it a habit to write them down is immensely helpful. So
many of my problems stopped being problems as I adopted writing things
down more and more. I have very small working memory. I forget often and
I forget most things. Mind is always thinking of new ideas, things to
do, things to tell people. The knowledge that I am going to forget the
thing I am thinking right now is a big source of anxiety. The burden of
remembering innumerable things and then failing to do so has a cognitive
toll of its own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I use org-mode as a lot of things; a TODO list is one of them. I am not
going to get into the details of using org-mode for a beginner, but I&apos;ll
share my flow of using org mode as a TODO list.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-capturing-things-to-do&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;capturing-things-to-do&quot;&gt;Capturing things to do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-capturing-things-to-do&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A very useful feature of org-mode is how easy it makes to &quot;capture&quot; TOOD
items. I use Emacs as my primary text editor; being a software
developer, most of my day time is spent in Emacs. Any time I think of
something I [want|have] to do, I capture it with 3 keystrokes and
usually immediately refile it under an appropriate heading. I keep 2
TODOs.org files, one for work and one for my personal life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my personal TODOs.org file, I keep headings categorizing the kind of
thing it is that I want to do; right now, they are =Study, Personal
Development, Habits, Projects, Reading List, In Basket&quot;.&quot;In Basket&quot;
heading keeps things that are quickly done in a day or few, and/or
cannot be categorized.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My work TODOs.org carries all my work related tasks, including Jira
issues, and general things I want/have to do when I am in the office. I
have a TODO item to integrate org-jira, but right now I am manually
copying Jira task IDs around like an imbecile.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is how my org-capture-templates variable looks like right now:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;org8b5076d&quot;&gt;
(setq
   org-capture-templates
   &apos;((&quot;d&quot; &quot;Diary Entry&quot; plain (file+datetree org-agenda-diary-file) &quot;\n&amp;lt;%&amp;lt;%I:%M %p&amp;gt;&amp;gt;\n%?\n&quot;)
     (&quot;f&quot; &quot;Feedback&quot; plain (file+datetree trantor-feedback-file) &quot;\n&amp;lt;%&amp;lt;%I:%M %p&amp;gt;&amp;gt;\n%?\n&quot;)
     (&quot;i&quot; &quot;Idea&quot; entry (file org-ideas-file) &quot;* %?\n%T&quot;)
     (&quot;t&quot; &quot;Todo&quot; entry (file+headline &quot;&quot; &quot;Todos&quot;) &quot;* TODO %?\n%U\n[[%F]]&quot;)
     (&quot;c&quot; &quot;Contact&quot; entry (file org-contacts-file) &quot;* %^{Name}\n:PROPERTIES:\n:COMPANY %^{Company}\n:PHONE: %^{Phone}\n:END:&quot;)))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-delegating-things-to-future&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;delegating-things-to-future&quot;&gt;Delegating things to future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-delegating-things-to-future&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode has a brilliant feature of scheduling tasks. It&apos;s rare for me
to schedule a task for &quot;today&quot;; I delegate stuff to future me. I can
capture and file things in any header, and then use org-mode&apos;s agenda
views to filter out things past-me assigned for today. I try to finish
the &quot;today&quot; tasks, and try to stay at peace when I fail to every day.
Org-mode also display a count of for how long I&apos;ve been missing to do a
certain task which is a handy reminder that I am falling short on my
commitments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-prioritizing-things&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;prioritizing-things&quot;&gt;Prioritizing things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-prioritizing-things&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not all tasks are made equal. Although I try my best to not let my
&quot;Today&quot; tasks list become too big, sometimes there is simply too much on
the plate. In that case, I define priorities for the most important
tasks, which are displayed at the top of the list in Day-agenda view.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-tagging-items&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tagging-items&quot;&gt;Tagging items&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-tagging-items&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I often tag my TODO items so I can easily filter them in the agenda view
when I want to find things I have to do in some particular context. I
often tag things by:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The person&apos;s name who I need to be with for doing something e.g when I
want to tell someone something&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Scrum sprint in which a task need to get done. For this I don&apos;t
tag each task but instead file my tasks in a &quot;Sprint X&quot; heading which
is tagged, and org-mode automatically inherit tags to all the
subheadings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place where I need to be at for doing something&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some other task specific metadata that I think can be helpful for
finding this task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-finding-things-to-do&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-things-to-do&quot;&gt;Finding things to do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-finding-things-to-do&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode allow me to write my todo items in any order in any manner; I
have several files where I write a lot of stuff, some of it is things to
do; most if it isn&apos;t. It&apos;s crucial to write things down for me, because
I know that I am going to forget it. Org-mode is immensely helpful in
finding things out when I need it. Org-files being just text files allow
me to just grep stuff; which is even more powerful with
helm-projectile-grep. But the killer feature for finding out what I am
supposed to be doing right now is org&apos;s agenda view. It allow me to
filter things by time and tags.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode require you to explicitly add files to a list of
&lt;code&gt;org-agenda-files&lt;/code&gt;. The agenda views only pick tasks from files in this
list. I have almost all my org files in my agenda list. It also provides
different views for the agenda; the one I am using most these days is
the &quot;Day-agenda&quot; view, and Week-agenda view when I want to plan things
ahead for the week.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On my mobile, I use orgzly android app. I am not too happy with it, but
it&apos;s the best I&apos;ve got for now. I&apos;ve it in my TODO list to create an app
focused on org-mode and TODO lists the way I want it to work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>managing-chaos-org-mode-as-a-todo-list</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-01-05T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Coming to terms with ADHD - Part 2</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd-part-2</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the important aspects of living with ADHD is getting overwhelmed
by thoughts. This is usually a major pain in the ass. When left
unchecked it usually leads to a lot of confusion very painfully visible
to people around you. This made most of my school life very tormenting.
Despite being an &quot;A&quot; student, I was always completely lost.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got better when I found computers. A book I found while sitting in
the wrong classroom turned things around for me. My thoughts got
channeled, things started becoming a lot more clearer when I wasn&apos;t
thinking of 10 random things at a time. I was still thinking of 10
things at a time, but it was now manageable; it was interesting. I
wasn&apos;t fighting the trains of thought anymore, I was enjoying the ride.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was alright while it was fun and games, but it became a problem
again when I entered software development as a profession. Now I had to
focus on things for extended duration of time; which usually was more
than my interest span. It was a struggle again. I got over that period
though; my current solution is to bring more accountability for my work,
for which right now, I am doing a day job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During my period of struggle, I did a lot of fight to stay focused. I
fought to not let distractions come in; I blocked sites, tried several
time-boxing techniques; most things worked, but for a small duration of
time. The fight did me more bad than good. Exploring things is what make
me happy, when I took that away from myself, the frustration that built
up as a result threw me in a pit of despair.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My recommendation to anyone finding [her|him]self in my shoes is to not
fight it all the time. Do whatever you feel like every once in a while.
It is very important to keep feeling happy. Trust yourself that you&apos;ll
manage to get important things done in time. However, you need to
build/earn this trust. Read my
&lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; for some tips on how I do it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When you find something you feel passionate about, the multiple trains
of thought kinda all go in the same direction. They&apos;re all interesting,
and you want to ride them all. If you fight to ride one (or few) of
them, you&apos;re gonna give yourself a hard time. Instinct to hop on each
one of them until another one is more interesting isn&apos;t all that evil.
I&apos;ll be writing more posts on how I do that (i.e tools and techniques I
use), I don&apos;t have time right now, and am losing interest in writing
this post. Try to trust yourself that you&apos;ll come back to what you&apos;re
pausing, have means that allow you to hop b/w different things, and try
to be at peace with the fact that this is simply how you operate. It
might look chaotic to others, you&apos;ll still not be &quot;normal&quot;, but you&apos;ll
be a whole lot happy, and hopefully satisfied.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my current setup I have tens of different things I am time-sharing
on, and am still delivering satisfactory value in my work. It is
certainly possible for you to not fight tooth and nail with your way of
thinking and have a satisfactory career (at least in Software
Development).
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>coming-to-terms-with-adhd-part-2</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-01-03T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Coming to terms with ADHD</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
After my recent subscription to &lt;a href=&quot;http://reddit.com/r/adhd&quot;&gt;/r/adhd&lt;/a&gt;, I
realized how important it can be to share experiences. Even when it is
something very personal and seem unlikely that anyone can relate to it,
it can be quite helpful for someone who thinks she&apos;s alone with her
struggles. A while back I deleted most of my old blog posts feeling
embarrassed of their suspected cringeworthiness. Now I think it was a
mistake. I am thinking about resurrecting them from archive.org.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this post I want to talk about how I came to the single instance of
my life when I am not completely lost in self-pity for being too lazy
and undisciplined. Perhaps it was this self-loathing that slowly turned
to depression, and a bad event finally pushed me into the hole that I
believe I am out of now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started my research on ADHD when my doctor pointed I might have it. At
that time I was in limbo of a special kind. I was quite used to the
struggle of making myself do work that wasn&apos;t interesting anymore. I was
also used to the periods of time when I was simply incapable of doing
any work. But what made me go to the doctor was a relatively longer
period of true nothingness. Nothing would excite me, no matter what I
tried. The chaos inside my head got so out of control I was often
talking to myself in an attempt to materialize the voices and solidify
the line of thought so I could deal with them one at a time. Nothing
worked. I would often contemplate suicide because my mind just wouldn&apos;t
shut up about how pathetic I was. It was then I decided to consult help
from a professional.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have not reached a solution, perhaps there is no solution that solves
everything. But here is a list of things that has made a huge impact in
helping me come to terms with my ADHD.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-keep-a-daily-journal&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-a-daily-journal&quot;&gt;Keep a daily journal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-keep-a-daily-journal&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Try to know yourself. Understanding why you are thinking what you are
thinking can be immensely helpful. It will help you figure out the flaws
in your thinking, and how to make up for them. For example, a pat
routine has saved me so many times once I started noticing that how
often in a single I would forget my wallet or my phone or keys. Small
things like this add up to make life miserable, and often go unnoticed
in the storms of thoughts we face every day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So much of the overwhelmingness can just be let gone by writing it down.
Try to be your own therapist, try to witness yourself. Not to
participate, or engage, just analyze. It can be quite an exhausting
thing to do, but I&apos;ve found it to be more helpful than meditation. When
I write in my diary, I find myself to be much more in control of life
the next day. It&apos;ll also help you figure out which of your ideas are
actually work-able and which are just fluff that need to go in trash
can.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-write-stuff-down&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;write-stuff-down&quot;&gt;Write stuff down&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-write-stuff-down&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You don&apos;t need to wait for the night to fall before you can write in
your diary. Writing often during the day is quite helpful too. Write
anything and everything down. Is it something you want to do but can&apos;t
right now? Create a todo entry. Just had a brilliant new idea? Capture
it. Invest in a tool that can help you capture your thoughts quickly.
Make this process a part of your life. I use Emacs&apos; Org mode which has a
brilliant capture system, and I am very happy with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-delegate-to-your-future-self&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;delegate-to-your-future-self&quot;&gt;Delegate to your future self&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-delegate-to-your-future-self&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You don&apos;t need to do all the hundred things you have thought of, today
itself. Delegate them to your future self. I don&apos;t remember where I
learned it, but it is very helpful to treat your future self as a
different person, and just assign tasks to him that you don&apos;t have time
to work on right now. You can schedule stuff you capture right away, or
you can have a weekly review when you sort everything you captured in
the week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-review-weekly&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;review-weekly&quot;&gt;Review weekly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-review-weekly&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is very important to review everything you capture on regular
intervals. It&apos;ll give you confidence regarding your system, you could
trust yourself more. When you can start trusting your future self,
things becomes a lot very easier. You also become better at estimating
stuff, so the commitments you give to other people bring you that much
less anxiety.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-respect-the-decisions-made-by-your-past-self&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;respect-the-decisions-made-by-your-past-self&quot;&gt;Respect the decisions made by your past self&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-respect-the-decisions-made-by-your-past-self&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Only way you can trust your future self to finish what&apos;s assigned to him
is if you respect the decisions made by your past self. You don&apos;t have
to beat yourself up too much about it either. Understand that it&apos;s not
easy to estimate things. If we could predict things very reliably, we
could open shops as psychics. Try to achieve &quot;eventual consistency&quot;. Not
everything is equally important. Make sure that if something has been
assigned to you, it eventually gets completed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-find-something-you-can-attach-meaning-to&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;find-something-you-can-attach-meaning-to&quot;&gt;Find something you can attach meaning to&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-find-something-you-can-attach-meaning-to&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&apos;s helpful to have something to call home. A principle that you
wouldn&apos;t compromise with. I have chosen to attach meaning to the quality
of the work I do. That&apos;s where I try to find solace. That&apos;s what I use
to bring myself to peace, when I can&apos;t control the mess in some parts of
my life. It might be one of the cardinal sins, but this kind of pride
helps build confidence to face life.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>coming-to-terms-with-adhd</guid>
            <pubDate>2018-12-15T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>