<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xlmns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title type="text">Clownpress - bitspook.in</title><id>https://bitspook.in/tags/clownpress/feed.xml</id><updated>2024-01-04T08:18:20.169658Z</updated><link href="https://bitspook.in/tags/clownpress/feed.xml" rel="self" title="Clownpress"/><author type="text">Charanjit Singh</author><subtitle type="text"></subtitle><logo>https://bitspook.in/images/avatar.png</logo><entry><title type="text">Thoughts on HPI and future of cl-ownpress</title><id>https://bitspook.in/blog/thoughts-on-hpi-and-future-of-cl-ownpress</id><updated>2024-01-01T10:54:00.000000Z</updated><link href="https://bitspook.in/blog/thoughts-on-hpi-and-future-of-cl-ownpress" title="Thoughts on HPI and future of cl-ownpress"/><author type="text">Charanjit Singh</author><category term="blog"/><published>2024-01-01T10:54:00.000000Z</published><summary type="text"></summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote id=&quot;org89bc37c&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reflecting on similarities and differences b/w HPI and what I want cl-ownpress to build into.
Thinking out loud.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Recently I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karlicoss/HPI&quot;&gt;HPI&lt;/a&gt; again. HPI has a lot of similarities to what I want cl-ownpress to be.
Its goal seem to be enabling a user to take ownership of their own data that's locked in online
platforms. This is exactly what I want cl-ownpress to do for me. This realization gave me pause, and
here I am rationalizing continued existence of cl-ownpress.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
cl-ownpress is supposed to be a part of a bigger ecosystem for personal computing. By personal
computing I mean hooking into every aspect of my personal life. My thoughts (daily journal, captured
ideas), finances, things I own, people I interact with, work I do and everything else. In my ideal
personal computing ecosystem, different independent pieces interact with and build upon each other.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;For example&lt;/i&gt;, I want to have a CRM to manage people and my relationships with them. I want the
ability to mention people from my CRM in my daily journal, and then be able to make queries like
&amp;quot;all interactions with person &amp;lt;X&amp;gt;&amp;quot;. Similarly, I want to utilize my CRM to also mention people in my
blog-posts. These mentions however should get intelligently published. e.g on my personal website,
mention of a person should become a link to their own personal website. When publishing to mastodon,
it should become a mastodon mention.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Another example&lt;/i&gt;, I'd like to maintain an accounting ledger of all the money I spend. I want to
utilize this to also maintain a list of things I own. I'd like to utilize this in turn to review
things I use, and publish my reviews to my personal website and/or where I purchased it from.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Publishing a subset of all the data in my personal computing ecosystem is where cl-ownpress comes
in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At present, cl-ownpress happens to be the most complete component of my ecosystem. I have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/brandi&quot;&gt;few&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/saunf&quot;&gt;other&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/kharcha&quot;&gt;pieces&lt;/a&gt; in pretty-much abandoned state while I have replaced them with some untracked lisp code
(mostly in my Emacs setup).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
HPI seems to provide same functionality as cl-ownpress's &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/cl-ownpress/blob/master/src/provider/package.lisp#L1-L4&quot;&gt;providers&lt;/a&gt;. So why not replace &lt;code&gt;provider&lt;/code&gt;-s
with HPI and build on already done work? Well, things I wanted so far (converting my denote notes to
blog posts while using my Emacs configuration to do the conversion from org to html) don't have a
replacement in HPI. In future, when I want to deal with an external data source and there is an HPI
module available for it, perhaps I'll create an &lt;code&gt;hpi-provider&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That settles one aspect of relationship of cl-ownpress and HPI. They're complimentary instead of
contradictory. HPI is essentially a set of cl-ownpress &lt;code&gt;provider&lt;/code&gt;-s. But I believe there is a
philosophical difference in how both these projects approach gaining ownership over user's data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
HPI &lt;b&gt;accepts&lt;/b&gt; that data is going to be produced on walled platforms, while cl-ownpress establishes
user's own platform where data is originally published. Cl-ownpress then uses the walled platforms
for interacting with people these platforms have managed to hold hostage.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Admittedly HPI has a broader scope, it deals with more than just getting data back from walled
platforms, but in the aspect of 'publishing', I believe this holds true. With cl-ownpress, I want to
invert the relationship. Instead of &amp;quot;the platform &amp;lt;X&amp;gt; uses me and locks in &lt;b&gt;my&lt;/b&gt; content&amp;quot;, I want it
to be &amp;quot;&lt;b&gt;I&lt;/b&gt; own my content, and use the walled garden to interact with its hostages&amp;quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The subtle difference is important to me. This is an attitude I'd like to have towards life, and
what is my personal computing ecosystem if not its reflection.
&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><base href="https://bitspook.in"/></feed>