<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts categorized as `talks&apos;</title>
        <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        <generator>cl-ownpress</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <image>
            <title>Posts categorized as `talks&apos;</title>
            <url>/images/avatar.png</url>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>Microservices</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/microservices-techblend</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I recently joined a Whatsapp group named &quot;Tech Blend&quot;, which conduct
weekly online meetups. Topic for last meetup was &quot;Microservices&quot;, for
which I volunteered. Since I was working for around 2 years on a
microservices based project of decent complexity, I thought it would be
fun to talk about my experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The meetup was fun. I ran out of time. The meetup is quite well managed.
Manpreet, the guy who organizes the meetup does a very good job
respecting everyone&apos;s time while managing to have meaningful discussions
at the same time. Their topics/talks are usually quite shallow, but this
event management is something I can learn from participating in this
group.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are the slides for I created for the meetup. I was holding on to
them hoping I&apos;ll create a video, but that&apos;s not happening. So I am just
putting the slides over here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Feel free to hit me up if you need some help regarding microservices, or
if you need me to explain some slide, or just for a chat.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/microservices/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>microservices-techblend</guid>
            <pubDate>2020-08-06T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Personal Brands for Software Developers (Talk)</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/personal-brands-for-software-developers-talk</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
After long diligence, me and my old (Trantor) team decided to organize a meetup
to showcase our efforts, and to share our ideas with the local community. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/Chandigarh-Programmers-Club/events/263862634/&quot;&gt;The
meetup&lt;/a&gt; was organized in Trantor on September 18, 2019.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was a collaborative talk given in 3 parts be me, Ayush Sharma, and
Sheenam Narula. Attendance was very low, but that&apos;s usually how it is in
Tricity. Overall it was a fun session with lengthy, and mostly fruitful
discussions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here&apos;s my set of slides from the talk:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/personal-brands-for-software-developers/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>personal-brands-for-software-developers-talk</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-10-21T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Secure Software Teams Trantor</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/secure-software-teams-trantor</link>
            <description>&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/secure-software-teams/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I gave this talk in one of internal sessions at Trantor. Goal was to
acquaint one of our software teams into the world of application
security. This was a basic talk, just to familiarize attendees with
basic information security concepts. I leveraged this opportunity to
propose setting up a Red Team in Trantor.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As practical part of this session, I created a docker based virtual lab
with webgoat set up. During the session we went through some of the
exercises, rest were left for the attendees as homework. Here&apos;s the
&lt;code&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; file that was used in the session.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;org15739df&quot;&gt;
version: &apos;3&apos;
services:
  webgoat:
    image: webgoat/webgoat-8.0
    environment:
      - WEBWOLF_HOST=webwolf
      - WEBWOLF_PORT=9090
    ports:
      - &quot;8080:8080&quot;
      - &quot;9001:9001&quot;
    volumes:
      - ./docker-volumes/webgoat-home:/home/webgoat/.webgoat
  webwolf:
    image: webgoat/webwolf
    ports:
      - &quot;9090:9090&quot;
    command: --spring.datasource.url=jdbc:hsqldb:hsql://webgoat:9001/webgoat --server.address=0.0.0.0
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start the lab, simply create a directory, save above snippet as
&lt;code&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt;, and run &lt;code&gt;docker-compose up&lt;/code&gt; in it. You will then
be able to access webgoat on &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:8080/WebGoat&quot;&gt;http://localhost:8080/WebGoat&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>secure-software-teams-trantor</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-08-26T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Lessons From a Year of TDD</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/lessons-from-a-year-of-tdd</link>
            <description>&lt;style&gt;img { max-width: 600px; margin: 1rem 0; }&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;///slides.com/bitspook/lessons-from-a-year-of-tdd/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This talk was delivered in &lt;a href=&quot;https://agilenetworkindia.com/events/technical-agility-day-chandigarh/&quot;&gt;Technical Agility Day, Chandigarh (June 15, 2019)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-transcript&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcript&quot;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-transcript&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Following is the transcript for the talk. There was no video recording,
but the transcript I prepared for the talk should sufficiently convey
what I meant to say in the talk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-introduction&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-introduction&quot;&gt;
&lt;img
  src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/01--introduction-to-tdd-talk.png&quot;
  title=&quot;Experience from a year of TDD by Charanjit Singh&quot;
  alt=&quot;Experience from a year of TDD by Charanjit Singh&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hello everyone, my name is Charanjit. I am working as a technical lead
at Trantor.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I joined Trantor a year ago, in one of Trantor&apos;s projects where I was
fortunate enough to see people willing to apply test driven development
on what was going to become a rather complex project. I am leading one
part of this project under a team named &quot;The cloud team&quot;. This talk is
the story of things we learned while practicing test driven development
to build a micro-services based cloud with several third-party
integrations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our cloud is built primarily with Node.js (express.js), uses GraphQL to
communicate with clients as well as for inter-service communication,
backed by Azure&apos;s CosmosDB (with its Mongo API), has Kafka for messaging
queue, and Elasticsearch for complex search solutions. We have about 9
services till today, and 3 third party integrations. We are building an
IOT-ish solution, and our cloud primarily serves the android application
running on our custom hardware, along with some companion applications
(for support and sales).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before we get into the details of how we did TDD in our project, or of
TDD itself, let&apos;s take a step back and work out some abstract thoughts.
Abstract thoughts about what we are trying to accomplish with techniques
like TDD. Actually, let&apos;s take all the steps back and go to the very
beginning.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the beginning, there were myths. Humans weren&apos;t always recording
history. The myths were used to fill the plot holes in stories told by
one generation to next. A common and very fascinating theme among the
myths of different cultures is that of magic.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/02--the-wizard.png&quot; title=&quot;The Wizard&quot; alt=&quot;The
Wizard&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Allegedly there used to be some very special people who could use the
mysterious powers. With flick of a wand they could create things out of
thin air, they could put life into the inanimate, they could bend the
reality itself to their will.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But those were of course myths. What we have now are developers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/03--the-stallman.png&quot; title=&quot;The Stallman&quot;
alt=&quot;The Stallman&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, I argue that developers are in fact the wizards of the information
age. We certainly meet the criteria:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;on&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[X]&lt;/code&gt; Create things (business/products/tools) out of thin air (without
any raw materials)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;on&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[X]&lt;/code&gt; Put life into the inanimate (software is practically the soul of
computer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;on&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[X]&lt;/code&gt; Bend reality to our will (/r/insidethesoftstone reality is what
you want it to be)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/04--the-stallzard.png&quot; title=&quot;The Stallzard&quot;
alt=&quot;The Stallzard&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Raw materials for the products a software developer creates are the
thoughts. The third point here is the focus of this talk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-software-as-universe&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;software-as-universe&quot;&gt;Software as Universe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-software-as-universe&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/05--the-universe.png&quot; title=&quot;The Universe&quot;
alt=&quot;The Universe&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am not kidding. I believe it is fair to say that every software is a
universe of its own. It has its own rules it operates within, its own
reality, which is at your disposal to do whatever with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is a living and breathing thing which must change and evolve and die
as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Do anyone here watches Rick and Morty? It is a good show about a
rockstar and a junior software developer. Try it sometime.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/06--the-microverse.png&quot; title=&quot;The Microverse&quot;
alt=&quot;The Microverse&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the episodes are about the microverse battery. The rockstar
developer creates a miniature universe whose sole purpose is to provide
power to his car. It is essentially a very complex car battery.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Funnier thing in that episode, the universe within the universe in the
battery does the exact same thing. Creates a universe whose sole purpose
is to power its host.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/07--many-layers-of-microverse.png&quot; title=&quot;Many
layers of the Microverse&quot; alt=&quot;Many layers of the Microverse&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Software we write are not very different. We create entire universe to
serve our needs, and it is rarely created in isolation. Usually our
universe has a bunch of other, more complex universes wrapped around it.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/08--realm-of-tux.png&quot; title=&quot;The realm of Tux&quot;
alt=&quot;The realm of Tux&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We often start with a base universe of Operating system. The platform,
programming language, the frameworks, they all make up for our initial
&quot;empty&quot; worlds. They set up their layers of rules, on which then we
write our own. Layers and layers of worlds.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/11--layers-of-software-universe.png&quot; title=&quot;Many
layered of software universe&quot; alt=&quot;Many layered of software universe&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, how do we populate this empty universe with the inhabitants which
would do our bidding? Well, with our thoughts and prayers of course.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/13--pray-to-the-machine.png&quot; title=&quot;Pray to the
machine&quot; alt=&quot;Pray to the machine&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am not kidding. But you get it, you aren&apos;t laughing. We literally send
our thoughts, often prayers as well, formulated in some special form
governed by some programming language to a compiler (or interpreter),
which then inhabit and basically forms the universe of our software.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Asgard isn&apos;t a place. Asgard is its people.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/14--pray-to-the-compiler.png&quot; title=&quot;Pray to the
compiler&quot; alt=&quot;Pray to the compiler&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That brings us to the corollary which takes us in the general direction
of practices like Test Driven Development.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/15--bugs-are-thoughts-gone-wrong.png&quot; title=&quot;Bugs
are thoughts too&quot; alt=&quot;Bugs are thoughts too&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-bugs-are-thoughts-gone-wrong&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;bugs-are-thoughts-gone-wrong&quot;&gt;Bugs are thoughts, gone wrong&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-bugs-are-thoughts-gone-wrong&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Correctness of software is inversely proportional to the client side
product team.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thoughts go wrong primarily in two ways:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are wrong to begin with. Mostly caused by misunderstanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thoughts that go wrong during translation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can create correct software if we can validate the correctness of
thoughts that get into the system, and those that reside it
subsequently.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is what TDD essentially do.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/16--tdd-validates-thoughts.png&quot; title=&quot;Bugs are
thoughts too&quot; alt=&quot;Bugs are thoughts too&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first point points to the red-green-refactor cycle. When doing TDD,
you write down the &quot;what&quot; aspect of the unit/module/function you are
going to write. It essentially allow you to pause, sit back, and think
about what you are going to implement. How it should behave.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The second point points to the help we get from our well-written tests
when we have to then make changes in our.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-busting-some-myths&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;busting-some-myths&quot;&gt;Busting some Myths&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-busting-some-myths&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-myth-1-tdd-is-time-consuming&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;myth-1-tdd-is-time-consuming&quot;&gt;Myth #1 : TDD is time consuming&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-myth-1-tdd-is-time-consuming&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This one is half a myth. TDD does consume time when you are starting.
Your mileage may vary depending on how much experience your team has
with TDD, initial time consumption is more if there is a learning curve
involved. Disregarding the learning curve, developing same features took
us roughly 30% longer to develop new features in our project.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/17--myth-tdd-is-time-consuming.png&quot; title=&quot;Myth
#1: TDD is time consuming&quot; alt=&quot;Myth #1: TDD is time consuming&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But this time is an investment you are making into your software, as
well as your developers. When the project started off, we did start off
slow. Other teams (there are 3 including us) were delivering more &quot;story
points&quot;. After about 3-4 months however, both other teams had dedicated
processes set up to tackle bugs, to prioritize and decide which bugs to
quash and which ones to live with. We still don&apos;t have any process
explicitly for bugs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our product is a startup, we have been going through a lot of changes
and pivots throughout the year. While other teams were struggling with
new bugs after every such change, we were delivering at pretty much the
same pace. Every bug that occurred in cloud got test(s) for it too, so
no mistakes were repeated. Till now, we have been able to keep the list
of bugs small enough that we don&apos;t pay particular attention to it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On-boarding new people to our team was a no-op, we would just give them
an overview, and tell them to run the tests. We did put considerable
amount of effort to make the tests our live documentation for
developers, and it paid dividends.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/24--tdd-gave-us-free-time.png&quot; title=&quot;TDD gave us
time to invest elsewhere&quot; alt=&quot;TDD gave us time to invest elsewhere&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Not just that, TDD actually gave our team to do more than just our
assigned duties. Most notably, we were able to not have a separate
dev/ops team at all, and took care of provisioning a cloud with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infrastructure_as_Code&quot;&gt;IAC&lt;/a&gt; (using
Terraform and Ansible), and a small sized K8s cluster too. Our
development environment is pristine as well. It just takes a single
command (docker-compose up) to get the complete cloud (including log
aggregation, Elasticsearch, Kibana and Kafka) running on new machine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-myth-2-tdd-is-about-tests&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;myth-2-tdd-is-about-tests&quot;&gt;Myth #2 : TDD is about tests&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-myth-2-tdd-is-about-tests&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is not. &quot;DD&quot; in &quot;TDD&quot; is more important than &quot;T&quot;. We learned this the
hard way because of lack of experience with TDD. When you are applying
TDD on a new project, &lt;b&gt;your tests should be driving the development&lt;/b&gt;.
Tests by themselves aren&apos;t the goal. The essential thing you must do to
ensure this, is to ensure that you write tests first.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/24--myth-tdd-is-about-tests.png&quot; title=&quot;Myth #2:
TDD is about Tests&quot; alt=&quot;Myth #2: TDD is about Tests&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tests written after the fact are practically handicapped. No matter how
good a developer you are, when you are writing tests after you have
written the feature/code, the &quot;how&quot; aspect of your code will creep in,
and your tests will never be as effective as they could have been. Same
goes for the feature you are writing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-myth-3-tdd-means-no-bugs&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;myth-3-tdd-means-no-bugs&quot;&gt;Myth #3 : TDD means no bugs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-myth-3-tdd-means-no-bugs&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is what I&apos;ve been advertising so far, ain&apos;t I! Well, it is not a
100% truth. Even if we ignore the fact that your tests will almost never
be 100% complete, TDD will not guarantee a fully correct software.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/29--myth-tdd-means-no-bugs.png&quot; title=&quot;Myth #3:
TDD means no bugs&quot; alt=&quot;Myth #3: TDD means no bugs&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TDD is your last line of defense. By the time you have sat down to
judiciously implement TDD, the thoughts that are going to populate your
software&apos;s universe have already been set. All you are going to do is
verify that they behave as it has been decided.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/32--protect-yourself-from-your-po.png&quot;
title=&quot;Adopt BDD&quot; alt=&quot;Adopt BDD&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
BDD operates at a much higher layer than TDD. At the layer where
discussions are done and decisions are made. I believe a combination of
BDD and TDD can create a very solid software. We adopted BDD in our
project at a much later time, looking back at the long meetings we used
to have, I can see how much time and confusion it could have saved us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-grow-as-a-developer&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;grow-as-a-developer&quot;&gt;Grow as a developer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-grow-as-a-developer&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/33--tdd-guides-you-in-right-direction.png&quot;
title=&quot;TDD Guides you in right direction&quot; alt=&quot;TDD Guides you in right
direction&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was an interesting observation. Team seem to have a much higher
appreciation for design patterns like dependency injection. We also
observed a shift in PR review comments toward a focus on software design
and architecture. Discussions we used to have to make our TDD approach
more fruitful brought a cultural shift in the team.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-when-adding-tdd-to-a-new-team&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-adding-tdd-to-a-new-team&quot;&gt;When adding TDD to a new team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-when-adding-tdd-to-a-new-team&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/38--brace-yourself.png&quot; title=&quot;When adding TDD to
a new team&quot; alt=&quot;When adding TDD to a new team&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Biggest resistance we faced was convincing developers that it&apos;s worth
their while to write tests &lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt; they write code for their code. We
ended up introducing an extra step in our PR review checklist: &lt;i&gt;ensure
there is a &quot;test:&quot; commit which only has test descriptions&lt;/i&gt;. This helped
somewhat, but it took some time (and a lot of pair programming) till
developers realized the benefits of this process.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-things-i-wish-we-did&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-i-wish-we-did&quot;&gt;Things I wish we did&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-things-i-wish-we-did&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-mutation-testing&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;mutation-testing&quot;&gt;Mutation Testing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-mutation-testing&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/41--mutation-testing.png&quot; title=&quot;I wish we did:
Mutation Testing&quot; alt=&quot;I wish we did: Mutation Testing&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, coverage reports are big fat liars. They don&apos;t tell you how your
tests are doing. In my opinion, they are more like the Velocity Charts
our Scrum Master loves so much. They tell you if you are going in the
correct general direction, and it is very easy to make them lie.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://stryker-mutator.io/&quot;&gt;Mutation test&lt;/a&gt; is a rather interesting
concept that we played around with. Big idea is that the test-runner can
modify your code (e.g replace an if condition with &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;),
and re-run your code to verify how many mutations it can withhold. It
gives a lot better insight into the strength of your tests.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We experimented with mutation testing for a while. But I suppose because
of lack of integration of a platform for our CI (Bamboo) to present
thorough coverage reports, we haven&apos;t yet made mutation testing a part
of our test process.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can see how it can make PR reviews a lot more effective though. I hope
we can take some time out of our everlasting &quot;churn mode&quot; for this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-bdd&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;bdd&quot;&gt;BDD&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-bdd&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/42--bdd.png&quot; title=&quot;I wish we did: Behavior
Driven Development&quot; alt=&quot;I wish we did: Behavior Driven Development&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We implemented BDD a bit late (just a couple months ago) when we had
some critical modules for which we wanted automated tests, which
required the complete cloud up and running. Like all software projects,
we have always been on a rather tight schedule :-)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
BDD could have saved us a lot of trouble and confusion. It contributes
immensely to help you maintain a ubiquitous language of the project, and
make the communication between product people and developers much more
correct.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I apologize for rushing the transcript a bit in last few headlines
above. Need to get this off my todo list :-). If I get to deliver this
talk again at some occasion, I will revisit and will probably add some
velocity/burndown charts from Jira as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/47--thank-you.png&quot; title=&quot;Thank you for your
patience&quot; alt=&quot;Thank you for your patience&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>lessons-from-a-year-of-tdd</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-06-21T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>React/Redux Workshop</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/react-redux-workshop</link>
            <description>  &lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/react-redux-workshop/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
#+end_html
  &lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
React/Redux workshop I gave with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/Chandigarh-Programmers-Club/&quot;&gt;Programmers&apos; Club Chandigarh&lt;/a&gt; meetup group after
seeing community&apos;s interest in these technologies.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>react-redux-workshop</guid>
            <pubDate>2017-02-16T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Modern day JS Apps (2017)</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/modern-day-js-apps-2017</link>
            <description>&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/modern-js-apps-2017/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;html&quot; id=&quot;orga5fa732&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think this was the second meetup I organized after I came back from Bangalore
(to Chandigarh). It was organized with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/Chandigarh-Programmers-Club/&quot;&gt;Programmers&apos; Club Chandigarh&lt;/a&gt; meetup
group.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>modern-day-js-apps-2017</guid>
            <pubDate>2017-02-07T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>React, Redux and Reactive programming</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/react-redux-and-reactive-programming</link>
            <description>&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/react-redux-and-reactive-programming/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Building a React/Redux app with a twist of Reactive programming.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My first time speaking at a big conference! It was a great experience.
There is a video as well!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SFPF56BB1Cs&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/frp-with-rxjs-jschannel-conf&quot;&gt;Transcript for this talk&lt;/a&gt; is available in its Github repository.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>react-redux-and-reactive-programming</guid>
            <pubDate>2016-07-08T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Jschannel RxJS workshop Nov 2015</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/jschannel-rxjs-workshop-now-2015</link>
            <description>&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/jschannel-rxjs-workshop-nov-2015/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;html&quot; id=&quot;org34b43bd&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was very fascinated about Reactive programming, and when we had a shortage of
talks in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/jslovers-bengaluru/&quot;&gt;JsChannel&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to give a workshop on RxJS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/rxjs-workshop-nov-2015&quot;&gt;code used in this workshop&lt;/a&gt; can be found in my Github.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>jschannel-rxjs-workshop-now-2015</guid>
            <pubDate>2015-11-01T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Meteor Js Jschannel Feb 2015</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/meteor-js-jschannel-feb-2015</link>
            <description>&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/meteor-jschannel-feb-2015/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First talk I ever gave. I was new to Bangalore and all excited about the
whole idea of meetup.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>meteor-js-jschannel-feb-2015</guid>
            <pubDate>2015-02-07T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>