<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts tagged `productivity&apos;</title>
        <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        <generator>cl-ownpress</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <image>
            <title>Posts tagged `productivity&apos;</title>
            <url>/images/avatar.png</url>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>Managing Chaos</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/managing-chaos-org-mode-as-a-todo-list</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I am thinking about doing a small series of posts on how I am managing
the chaos that I am trying to stop fighting. I hope the chaos of an ADHD
mind can be utilized rather than fought against. So far it has been
working out pretty great (for past ~8 months). This post is about how I
manage my ever exploding list of things I want to do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I believe one of the most important things is to externalize your
thoughts. Making it a habit to write them down is immensely helpful. So
many of my problems stopped being problems as I adopted writing things
down more and more. I have very small working memory. I forget often and
I forget most things. Mind is always thinking of new ideas, things to
do, things to tell people. The knowledge that I am going to forget the
thing I am thinking right now is a big source of anxiety. The burden of
remembering innumerable things and then failing to do so has a cognitive
toll of its own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I use org-mode as a lot of things; a TODO list is one of them. I am not
going to get into the details of using org-mode for a beginner, but I&apos;ll
share my flow of using org mode as a TODO list.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-capturing-things-to-do&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;capturing-things-to-do&quot;&gt;Capturing things to do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-capturing-things-to-do&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A very useful feature of org-mode is how easy it makes to &quot;capture&quot; TOOD
items. I use Emacs as my primary text editor; being a software
developer, most of my day time is spent in Emacs. Any time I think of
something I [want|have] to do, I capture it with 3 keystrokes and
usually immediately refile it under an appropriate heading. I keep 2
TODOs.org files, one for work and one for my personal life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my personal TODOs.org file, I keep headings categorizing the kind of
thing it is that I want to do; right now, they are =Study, Personal
Development, Habits, Projects, Reading List, In Basket&quot;.&quot;In Basket&quot;
heading keeps things that are quickly done in a day or few, and/or
cannot be categorized.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My work TODOs.org carries all my work related tasks, including Jira
issues, and general things I want/have to do when I am in the office. I
have a TODO item to integrate org-jira, but right now I am manually
copying Jira task IDs around like an imbecile.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is how my org-capture-templates variable looks like right now:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;org2337649&quot;&gt;
(setq
   org-capture-templates
   &apos;((&quot;d&quot; &quot;Diary Entry&quot; plain (file+datetree org-agenda-diary-file) &quot;\n&amp;lt;%&amp;lt;%I:%M %p&amp;gt;&amp;gt;\n%?\n&quot;)
     (&quot;f&quot; &quot;Feedback&quot; plain (file+datetree trantor-feedback-file) &quot;\n&amp;lt;%&amp;lt;%I:%M %p&amp;gt;&amp;gt;\n%?\n&quot;)
     (&quot;i&quot; &quot;Idea&quot; entry (file org-ideas-file) &quot;* %?\n%T&quot;)
     (&quot;t&quot; &quot;Todo&quot; entry (file+headline &quot;&quot; &quot;Todos&quot;) &quot;* TODO %?\n%U\n[[%F]]&quot;)
     (&quot;c&quot; &quot;Contact&quot; entry (file org-contacts-file) &quot;* %^{Name}\n:PROPERTIES:\n:COMPANY %^{Company}\n:PHONE: %^{Phone}\n:END:&quot;)))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-delegating-things-to-future&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;delegating-things-to-future&quot;&gt;Delegating things to future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-delegating-things-to-future&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode has a brilliant feature of scheduling tasks. It&apos;s rare for me
to schedule a task for &quot;today&quot;; I delegate stuff to future me. I can
capture and file things in any header, and then use org-mode&apos;s agenda
views to filter out things past-me assigned for today. I try to finish
the &quot;today&quot; tasks, and try to stay at peace when I fail to every day.
Org-mode also display a count of for how long I&apos;ve been missing to do a
certain task which is a handy reminder that I am falling short on my
commitments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-prioritizing-things&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;prioritizing-things&quot;&gt;Prioritizing things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-prioritizing-things&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not all tasks are made equal. Although I try my best to not let my
&quot;Today&quot; tasks list become too big, sometimes there is simply too much on
the plate. In that case, I define priorities for the most important
tasks, which are displayed at the top of the list in Day-agenda view.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-tagging-items&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tagging-items&quot;&gt;Tagging items&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-tagging-items&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I often tag my TODO items so I can easily filter them in the agenda view
when I want to find things I have to do in some particular context. I
often tag things by:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The person&apos;s name who I need to be with for doing something e.g when I
want to tell someone something&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Scrum sprint in which a task need to get done. For this I don&apos;t
tag each task but instead file my tasks in a &quot;Sprint X&quot; heading which
is tagged, and org-mode automatically inherit tags to all the
subheadings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place where I need to be at for doing something&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some other task specific metadata that I think can be helpful for
finding this task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-finding-things-to-do&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-things-to-do&quot;&gt;Finding things to do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-finding-things-to-do&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode allow me to write my todo items in any order in any manner; I
have several files where I write a lot of stuff, some of it is things to
do; most if it isn&apos;t. It&apos;s crucial to write things down for me, because
I know that I am going to forget it. Org-mode is immensely helpful in
finding things out when I need it. Org-files being just text files allow
me to just grep stuff; which is even more powerful with
helm-projectile-grep. But the killer feature for finding out what I am
supposed to be doing right now is org&apos;s agenda view. It allow me to
filter things by time and tags.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode require you to explicitly add files to a list of
&lt;code&gt;org-agenda-files&lt;/code&gt;. The agenda views only pick tasks from files in this
list. I have almost all my org files in my agenda list. It also provides
different views for the agenda; the one I am using most these days is
the &quot;Day-agenda&quot; view, and Week-agenda view when I want to plan things
ahead for the week.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On my mobile, I use orgzly android app. I am not too happy with it, but
it&apos;s the best I&apos;ve got for now. I&apos;ve it in my TODO list to create an app
focused on org-mode and TODO lists the way I want it to work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>managing-chaos-org-mode-as-a-todo-list</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-01-05T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Coming to terms with ADHD - Part 2</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd-part-2</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the important aspects of living with ADHD is getting overwhelmed
by thoughts. This is usually a major pain in the ass. When left
unchecked it usually leads to a lot of confusion very painfully visible
to people around you. This made most of my school life very tormenting.
Despite being an &quot;A&quot; student, I was always completely lost.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got better when I found computers. A book I found while sitting in
the wrong classroom turned things around for me. My thoughts got
channeled, things started becoming a lot more clearer when I wasn&apos;t
thinking of 10 random things at a time. I was still thinking of 10
things at a time, but it was now manageable; it was interesting. I
wasn&apos;t fighting the trains of thought anymore, I was enjoying the ride.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was alright while it was fun and games, but it became a problem
again when I entered software development as a profession. Now I had to
focus on things for extended duration of time; which usually was more
than my interest span. It was a struggle again. I got over that period
though; my current solution is to bring more accountability for my work,
for which right now, I am doing a day job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During my period of struggle, I did a lot of fight to stay focused. I
fought to not let distractions come in; I blocked sites, tried several
time-boxing techniques; most things worked, but for a small duration of
time. The fight did me more bad than good. Exploring things is what make
me happy, when I took that away from myself, the frustration that built
up as a result threw me in a pit of despair.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My recommendation to anyone finding [her|him]self in my shoes is to not
fight it all the time. Do whatever you feel like every once in a while.
It is very important to keep feeling happy. Trust yourself that you&apos;ll
manage to get important things done in time. However, you need to
build/earn this trust. Read my
&lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; for some tips on how I do it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When you find something you feel passionate about, the multiple trains
of thought kinda all go in the same direction. They&apos;re all interesting,
and you want to ride them all. If you fight to ride one (or few) of
them, you&apos;re gonna give yourself a hard time. Instinct to hop on each
one of them until another one is more interesting isn&apos;t all that evil.
I&apos;ll be writing more posts on how I do that (i.e tools and techniques I
use), I don&apos;t have time right now, and am losing interest in writing
this post. Try to trust yourself that you&apos;ll come back to what you&apos;re
pausing, have means that allow you to hop b/w different things, and try
to be at peace with the fact that this is simply how you operate. It
might look chaotic to others, you&apos;ll still not be &quot;normal&quot;, but you&apos;ll
be a whole lot happy, and hopefully satisfied.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my current setup I have tens of different things I am time-sharing
on, and am still delivering satisfactory value in my work. It is
certainly possible for you to not fight tooth and nail with your way of
thinking and have a satisfactory career (at least in Software
Development).
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>coming-to-terms-with-adhd-part-2</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-01-03T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>