<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts tagged `trantor&apos;</title>
        <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        <generator>cl-ownpress</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <image>
            <title>Posts tagged `trantor&apos;</title>
            <url>/images/spooky-avatar.png</url>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>Microservices</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/microservices-techblend/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I recently joined a Whatsapp group named &quot;Tech Blend&quot;, which conduct
weekly online meetups. Topic for last meetup was &quot;Microservices&quot;, for
which I volunteered. Since I was working for around 2 years on a
microservices based project of decent complexity, I thought it would be
fun to talk about my experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The meetup was fun. I ran out of time. The meetup is quite well managed.
Manpreet, the guy who organizes the meetup does a very good job
respecting everyone&apos;s time while managing to have meaningful discussions
at the same time. Their topics/talks are usually quite shallow, but this
event management is something I can learn from participating in this
group.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are the slides for I created for the meetup. I was holding on to
them hoping I&apos;ll create a video, but that&apos;s not happening. So I am just
putting the slides over here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Feel free to hit me up if you need some help regarding microservices, or
if you need me to explain some slide, or just for a chat.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/microservices/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>microservices-techblend</guid>
            <pubDate>2020-08-06T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Personal Brands for Software Developers (Talk)</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/personal-brands-for-software-developers-talk/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
After long diligence, me and my old (Trantor) team decided to organize a meetup
to showcase our efforts, and to share our ideas with the local community. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/Chandigarh-Programmers-Club/events/263862634/&quot;&gt;The
meetup&lt;/a&gt; was organized in Trantor on September 18, 2019.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was a collaborative talk given in 3 parts be me, Ayush Sharma, and
Sheenam Narula. Attendance was very low, but that&apos;s usually how it is in
Tricity. Overall it was a fun session with lengthy, and mostly fruitful
discussions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here&apos;s my set of slides from the talk:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/personal-brands-for-software-developers/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>personal-brands-for-software-developers-talk</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-10-21T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Quick and Pretty Docs for Software Projects</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/quick-and-pretty-docs-for-software-projects/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I have practiced
&lt;a href=&quot;http://tom.preston-werner.com/2010/08/23/readme-driven-development.html&quot;&gt;Readme
Driven Development&lt;/a&gt; on a number of my projects with varying milage. I
have often found myself wishing for a few things:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;More structure&lt;/b&gt; When writing the documentation, and even more so
when reading it. A single markdown file starts getting out of hand
really quickly. On my presonal projects I go for org-mode, which keep
me satisfied. But when working on a professional gig, it don&apos;t feel
right to force other developers into org-mode/emacs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Prettiness&lt;/b&gt; Markdown is a quite reasonably readable format, but
there is always room for prettyness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Basically I wish for github-pages with more structure; so, a statically
generate site.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To minimize the added complexity to our dev setup, and since I am
already using docker to run dev-environments for almost all of my
projects, I chose to leverage it for building my readme as a local
&quot;service&quot;. i.e I chose to structure my documentation with filesystem,
and use docker to abstract the complexity of setting up the static site
generator.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have chosen hugo because of its simplicity. Its intuitive content
management means near-zero learning curve for my teammates to start
contributing documentation. I chose
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/matcornic/hugo-theme-learn&quot;&gt;hugo-theme-learn&lt;/a&gt;
because of its simplicity, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mermaidjs.github.io/&quot;&gt;mermaid.js&lt;/a&gt;
support for UML diagrams, and well, prettiness.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have a directory named &lt;code&gt;docs&lt;/code&gt; in our repository, with following
general structure:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;org732c48a&quot;&gt;
.
├── config.toml
├── content
└── Dockerfile
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Every markdown file in &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; directory adds to the generated
documentation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here is the Dockerfile I have used to create the docs container. It
downloads and sets up hugo with the theme in a single command without
anything other than docker installed on a developer&apos;s machine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;org63acae1&quot;&gt;
FROM alpine:latest

WORKDIR /app

EXPOSE 80
ENV HOST=0.0.0.0

RUN apk update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; apk add hugo git

ENV HUGO_THEME_URL=&apos;https://github.com/matcornic/hugo-theme-learn&apos;
ENV HUGO_THEME_COMMIT=&apos;2.4.0&apos;

RUN mkdir -p /themes/current \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd /themes/current \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git init \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git remote add origin $HUGO_THEME_URL \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git fetch --depth 1 origin $HUGO_THEME_COMMIT \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git checkout FETCH_HEAD \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd /app
RUN echo &quot;alias hugo=&apos;hugo --themesDir /themes --theme current&apos;&quot; &amp;gt; ~/.profile

COPY . /app

CMD hugo serve --port 3000 --bind=&apos;0.0.0.0&apos; --themesDir /themes --theme current
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When exposed on port &lt;code&gt;3000&lt;/code&gt;, it allows live-reloading of docs and search
in docs as well. It is possible to change the theme and theme version by
setting environment variables &lt;code&gt;HUGO_THEME_URL&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;HUGO_THEME_COMMIT&lt;/code&gt;
when building the docker image.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here is &lt;code&gt;config.toml&lt;/code&gt; file I&apos;ve used for my &lt;code&gt;docs&lt;/code&gt;, which allow me to
configure the hugo theme with above mentioned environment variable only:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;org97ebfd0&quot;&gt;
buildDrafts = true
title = &quot;My Project&quot;

# For search functionality
[outputs]
home = [ &quot;HTML&quot;, &quot;RSS&quot;, &quot;JSON&quot;]

[params]
  author = &quot;My team&quot;
  description = &quot;My project&apos;s cloud&quot;
&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>quick-and-pretty-docs-for-software-projects</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-08-28T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Secure Software Teams Trantor</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/secure-software-teams-trantor/</link>
            <description>&lt;iframe src=&quot;//slides.com/bitspook/secure-software-teams/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I gave this talk in one of internal sessions at Trantor. Goal was to
acquaint one of our software teams into the world of application
security. This was a basic talk, just to familiarize attendees with
basic information security concepts. I leveraged this opportunity to
propose setting up a Red Team in Trantor.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As practical part of this session, I created a docker based virtual lab
with webgoat set up. During the session we went through some of the
exercises, rest were left for the attendees as homework. Here&apos;s the
&lt;code&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; file that was used in the session.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;orgceccab9&quot;&gt;
version: &apos;3&apos;
services:
  webgoat:
    image: webgoat/webgoat-8.0
    environment:
      - WEBWOLF_HOST=webwolf
      - WEBWOLF_PORT=9090
    ports:
      - &quot;8080:8080&quot;
      - &quot;9001:9001&quot;
    volumes:
      - ./docker-volumes/webgoat-home:/home/webgoat/.webgoat
  webwolf:
    image: webgoat/webwolf
    ports:
      - &quot;9090:9090&quot;
    command: --spring.datasource.url=jdbc:hsqldb:hsql://webgoat:9001/webgoat --server.address=0.0.0.0
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start the lab, simply create a directory, save above snippet as
&lt;code&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt;, and run &lt;code&gt;docker-compose up&lt;/code&gt; in it. You will then
be able to access webgoat on &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:8080/WebGoat&quot;&gt;http://localhost:8080/WebGoat&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>secure-software-teams-trantor</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-08-26T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Lessons From a Year of TDD</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/talks/lessons-from-a-year-of-tdd/</link>
            <description>&lt;style&gt;img { max-width: 600px; margin: 1rem 0; }&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;///slides.com/bitspook/lessons-from-a-year-of-tdd/embed?style=light&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This talk was delivered in &lt;a href=&quot;https://agilenetworkindia.com/events/technical-agility-day-chandigarh/&quot;&gt;Technical Agility Day, Chandigarh (June 15, 2019)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-transcript&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcript&quot;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-transcript&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Following is the transcript for the talk. There was no video recording,
but the transcript I prepared for the talk should sufficiently convey
what I meant to say in the talk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-introduction&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-introduction&quot;&gt;
&lt;img
  src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/01--introduction-to-tdd-talk.png&quot;
  title=&quot;Experience from a year of TDD by Charanjit Singh&quot;
  alt=&quot;Experience from a year of TDD by Charanjit Singh&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hello everyone, my name is Charanjit. I am working as a technical lead
at Trantor.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I joined Trantor a year ago, in one of Trantor&apos;s projects where I was
fortunate enough to see people willing to apply test driven development
on what was going to become a rather complex project. I am leading one
part of this project under a team named &quot;The cloud team&quot;. This talk is
the story of things we learned while practicing test driven development
to build a micro-services based cloud with several third-party
integrations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our cloud is built primarily with Node.js (express.js), uses GraphQL to
communicate with clients as well as for inter-service communication,
backed by Azure&apos;s CosmosDB (with its Mongo API), has Kafka for messaging
queue, and Elasticsearch for complex search solutions. We have about 9
services till today, and 3 third party integrations. We are building an
IOT-ish solution, and our cloud primarily serves the android application
running on our custom hardware, along with some companion applications
(for support and sales).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before we get into the details of how we did TDD in our project, or of
TDD itself, let&apos;s take a step back and work out some abstract thoughts.
Abstract thoughts about what we are trying to accomplish with techniques
like TDD. Actually, let&apos;s take all the steps back and go to the very
beginning.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the beginning, there were myths. Humans weren&apos;t always recording
history. The myths were used to fill the plot holes in stories told by
one generation to next. A common and very fascinating theme among the
myths of different cultures is that of magic.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/02--the-wizard.png&quot; title=&quot;The Wizard&quot; alt=&quot;The
Wizard&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Allegedly there used to be some very special people who could use the
mysterious powers. With flick of a wand they could create things out of
thin air, they could put life into the inanimate, they could bend the
reality itself to their will.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But those were of course myths. What we have now are developers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/03--the-stallman.png&quot; title=&quot;The Stallman&quot;
alt=&quot;The Stallman&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, I argue that developers are in fact the wizards of the information
age. We certainly meet the criteria:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;on&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[X]&lt;/code&gt; Create things (business/products/tools) out of thin air (without
any raw materials)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;on&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[X]&lt;/code&gt; Put life into the inanimate (software is practically the soul of
computer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class=&quot;on&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[X]&lt;/code&gt; Bend reality to our will (/r/insidethesoftstone reality is what
you want it to be)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/04--the-stallzard.png&quot; title=&quot;The Stallzard&quot;
alt=&quot;The Stallzard&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Raw materials for the products a software developer creates are the
thoughts. The third point here is the focus of this talk.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-software-as-universe&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;software-as-universe&quot;&gt;Software as Universe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-software-as-universe&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/05--the-universe.png&quot; title=&quot;The Universe&quot;
alt=&quot;The Universe&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am not kidding. I believe it is fair to say that every software is a
universe of its own. It has its own rules it operates within, its own
reality, which is at your disposal to do whatever with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is a living and breathing thing which must change and evolve and die
as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Do anyone here watches Rick and Morty? It is a good show about a
rockstar and a junior software developer. Try it sometime.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/06--the-microverse.png&quot; title=&quot;The Microverse&quot;
alt=&quot;The Microverse&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the episodes are about the microverse battery. The rockstar
developer creates a miniature universe whose sole purpose is to provide
power to his car. It is essentially a very complex car battery.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Funnier thing in that episode, the universe within the universe in the
battery does the exact same thing. Creates a universe whose sole purpose
is to power its host.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/07--many-layers-of-microverse.png&quot; title=&quot;Many
layers of the Microverse&quot; alt=&quot;Many layers of the Microverse&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Software we write are not very different. We create entire universe to
serve our needs, and it is rarely created in isolation. Usually our
universe has a bunch of other, more complex universes wrapped around it.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/08--realm-of-tux.png&quot; title=&quot;The realm of Tux&quot;
alt=&quot;The realm of Tux&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We often start with a base universe of Operating system. The platform,
programming language, the frameworks, they all make up for our initial
&quot;empty&quot; worlds. They set up their layers of rules, on which then we
write our own. Layers and layers of worlds.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/11--layers-of-software-universe.png&quot; title=&quot;Many
layered of software universe&quot; alt=&quot;Many layered of software universe&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, how do we populate this empty universe with the inhabitants which
would do our bidding? Well, with our thoughts and prayers of course.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/13--pray-to-the-machine.png&quot; title=&quot;Pray to the
machine&quot; alt=&quot;Pray to the machine&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am not kidding. But you get it, you aren&apos;t laughing. We literally send
our thoughts, often prayers as well, formulated in some special form
governed by some programming language to a compiler (or interpreter),
which then inhabit and basically forms the universe of our software.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Asgard isn&apos;t a place. Asgard is its people.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/14--pray-to-the-compiler.png&quot; title=&quot;Pray to the
compiler&quot; alt=&quot;Pray to the compiler&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That brings us to the corollary which takes us in the general direction
of practices like Test Driven Development.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/15--bugs-are-thoughts-gone-wrong.png&quot; title=&quot;Bugs
are thoughts too&quot; alt=&quot;Bugs are thoughts too&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-bugs-are-thoughts-gone-wrong&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;bugs-are-thoughts-gone-wrong&quot;&gt;Bugs are thoughts, gone wrong&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-bugs-are-thoughts-gone-wrong&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Correctness of software is inversely proportional to the client side
product team.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thoughts go wrong primarily in two ways:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are wrong to begin with. Mostly caused by misunderstanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thoughts that go wrong during translation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can create correct software if we can validate the correctness of
thoughts that get into the system, and those that reside it
subsequently.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is what TDD essentially do.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/16--tdd-validates-thoughts.png&quot; title=&quot;Bugs are
thoughts too&quot; alt=&quot;Bugs are thoughts too&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first point points to the red-green-refactor cycle. When doing TDD,
you write down the &quot;what&quot; aspect of the unit/module/function you are
going to write. It essentially allow you to pause, sit back, and think
about what you are going to implement. How it should behave.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The second point points to the help we get from our well-written tests
when we have to then make changes in our.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-busting-some-myths&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;busting-some-myths&quot;&gt;Busting some Myths&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-busting-some-myths&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-myth-1-tdd-is-time-consuming&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;myth-1-tdd-is-time-consuming&quot;&gt;Myth #1 : TDD is time consuming&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-myth-1-tdd-is-time-consuming&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This one is half a myth. TDD does consume time when you are starting.
Your mileage may vary depending on how much experience your team has
with TDD, initial time consumption is more if there is a learning curve
involved. Disregarding the learning curve, developing same features took
us roughly 30% longer to develop new features in our project.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/17--myth-tdd-is-time-consuming.png&quot; title=&quot;Myth
#1: TDD is time consuming&quot; alt=&quot;Myth #1: TDD is time consuming&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But this time is an investment you are making into your software, as
well as your developers. When the project started off, we did start off
slow. Other teams (there are 3 including us) were delivering more &quot;story
points&quot;. After about 3-4 months however, both other teams had dedicated
processes set up to tackle bugs, to prioritize and decide which bugs to
quash and which ones to live with. We still don&apos;t have any process
explicitly for bugs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our product is a startup, we have been going through a lot of changes
and pivots throughout the year. While other teams were struggling with
new bugs after every such change, we were delivering at pretty much the
same pace. Every bug that occurred in cloud got test(s) for it too, so
no mistakes were repeated. Till now, we have been able to keep the list
of bugs small enough that we don&apos;t pay particular attention to it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On-boarding new people to our team was a no-op, we would just give them
an overview, and tell them to run the tests. We did put considerable
amount of effort to make the tests our live documentation for
developers, and it paid dividends.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/24--tdd-gave-us-free-time.png&quot; title=&quot;TDD gave us
time to invest elsewhere&quot; alt=&quot;TDD gave us time to invest elsewhere&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Not just that, TDD actually gave our team to do more than just our
assigned duties. Most notably, we were able to not have a separate
dev/ops team at all, and took care of provisioning a cloud with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infrastructure_as_Code&quot;&gt;IAC&lt;/a&gt; (using
Terraform and Ansible), and a small sized K8s cluster too. Our
development environment is pristine as well. It just takes a single
command (docker-compose up) to get the complete cloud (including log
aggregation, Elasticsearch, Kibana and Kafka) running on new machine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-myth-2-tdd-is-about-tests&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;myth-2-tdd-is-about-tests&quot;&gt;Myth #2 : TDD is about tests&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-myth-2-tdd-is-about-tests&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is not. &quot;DD&quot; in &quot;TDD&quot; is more important than &quot;T&quot;. We learned this the
hard way because of lack of experience with TDD. When you are applying
TDD on a new project, &lt;b&gt;your tests should be driving the development&lt;/b&gt;.
Tests by themselves aren&apos;t the goal. The essential thing you must do to
ensure this, is to ensure that you write tests first.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/24--myth-tdd-is-about-tests.png&quot; title=&quot;Myth #2:
TDD is about Tests&quot; alt=&quot;Myth #2: TDD is about Tests&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tests written after the fact are practically handicapped. No matter how
good a developer you are, when you are writing tests after you have
written the feature/code, the &quot;how&quot; aspect of your code will creep in,
and your tests will never be as effective as they could have been. Same
goes for the feature you are writing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-myth-3-tdd-means-no-bugs&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;myth-3-tdd-means-no-bugs&quot;&gt;Myth #3 : TDD means no bugs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-myth-3-tdd-means-no-bugs&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is what I&apos;ve been advertising so far, ain&apos;t I! Well, it is not a
100% truth. Even if we ignore the fact that your tests will almost never
be 100% complete, TDD will not guarantee a fully correct software.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/29--myth-tdd-means-no-bugs.png&quot; title=&quot;Myth #3:
TDD means no bugs&quot; alt=&quot;Myth #3: TDD means no bugs&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TDD is your last line of defense. By the time you have sat down to
judiciously implement TDD, the thoughts that are going to populate your
software&apos;s universe have already been set. All you are going to do is
verify that they behave as it has been decided.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/32--protect-yourself-from-your-po.png&quot;
title=&quot;Adopt BDD&quot; alt=&quot;Adopt BDD&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
BDD operates at a much higher layer than TDD. At the layer where
discussions are done and decisions are made. I believe a combination of
BDD and TDD can create a very solid software. We adopted BDD in our
project at a much later time, looking back at the long meetings we used
to have, I can see how much time and confusion it could have saved us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-grow-as-a-developer&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;grow-as-a-developer&quot;&gt;Grow as a developer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-grow-as-a-developer&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/33--tdd-guides-you-in-right-direction.png&quot;
title=&quot;TDD Guides you in right direction&quot; alt=&quot;TDD Guides you in right
direction&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was an interesting observation. Team seem to have a much higher
appreciation for design patterns like dependency injection. We also
observed a shift in PR review comments toward a focus on software design
and architecture. Discussions we used to have to make our TDD approach
more fruitful brought a cultural shift in the team.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-when-adding-tdd-to-a-new-team&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-adding-tdd-to-a-new-team&quot;&gt;When adding TDD to a new team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-when-adding-tdd-to-a-new-team&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/38--brace-yourself.png&quot; title=&quot;When adding TDD to
a new team&quot; alt=&quot;When adding TDD to a new team&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Biggest resistance we faced was convincing developers that it&apos;s worth
their while to write tests &lt;b&gt;before&lt;/b&gt; they write code for their code. We
ended up introducing an extra step in our PR review checklist: &lt;i&gt;ensure
there is a &quot;test:&quot; commit which only has test descriptions&lt;/i&gt;. This helped
somewhat, but it took some time (and a lot of pair programming) till
developers realized the benefits of this process.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-things-i-wish-we-did&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-i-wish-we-did&quot;&gt;Things I wish we did&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-things-i-wish-we-did&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-mutation-testing&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;mutation-testing&quot;&gt;Mutation Testing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-mutation-testing&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/41--mutation-testing.png&quot; title=&quot;I wish we did:
Mutation Testing&quot; alt=&quot;I wish we did: Mutation Testing&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, coverage reports are big fat liars. They don&apos;t tell you how your
tests are doing. In my opinion, they are more like the Velocity Charts
our Scrum Master loves so much. They tell you if you are going in the
correct general direction, and it is very easy to make them lie.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://stryker-mutator.io/&quot;&gt;Mutation test&lt;/a&gt; is a rather interesting
concept that we played around with. Big idea is that the test-runner can
modify your code (e.g replace an if condition with &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;),
and re-run your code to verify how many mutations it can withhold. It
gives a lot better insight into the strength of your tests.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We experimented with mutation testing for a while. But I suppose because
of lack of integration of a platform for our CI (Bamboo) to present
thorough coverage reports, we haven&apos;t yet made mutation testing a part
of our test process.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can see how it can make PR reviews a lot more effective though. I hope
we can take some time out of our everlasting &quot;churn mode&quot; for this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-bdd&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;bdd&quot;&gt;BDD&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-bdd&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/42--bdd.png&quot; title=&quot;I wish we did: Behavior
Driven Development&quot; alt=&quot;I wish we did: Behavior Driven Development&quot;
width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We implemented BDD a bit late (just a couple months ago) when we had
some critical modules for which we wanted automated tests, which
required the complete cloud up and running. Like all software projects,
we have always been on a rather tight schedule :-)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
BDD could have saved us a lot of trouble and confusion. It contributes
immensely to help you maintain a ubiquitous language of the project, and
make the communication between product people and developers much more
correct.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I apologize for rushing the transcript a bit in last few headlines
above. Need to get this off my todo list :-). If I get to deliver this
talk again at some occasion, I will revisit and will probably add some
velocity/burndown charts from Jira as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/lfyot-slides/47--thank-you.png&quot; title=&quot;Thank you for your
patience&quot; alt=&quot;Thank you for your patience&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>talks</category>
            <guid>lessons-from-a-year-of-tdd</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-06-21T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Personal brands for software developers</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/personal-brands-for-software-developers/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/maximize-individual-growing-in-a-software-team-2-month-report/&quot;&gt;Reflecting on the progress&lt;/a&gt; we have made in our &lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/how-to-maximize-individual-growth-in-a-software-team/&quot;&gt;&quot;nurture a culture of individual
growth in a software team&quot; initiative&lt;/a&gt;, I realized there is much to gain from
candy wrapping our efforts. As per our plan, we&apos;ll be (and are) giving talks,
doing research, and writing itch-scratching code. Coming out of shadows and
presenting our efforts in a nice frame present many fold benefits.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My proposal is to invest energy in making our efforts more visible. To
focus this emotion on a more concrete goal, I have chosen
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-establishing-a-personal-brand&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;establishing-a-personal-brand&quot;&gt;Establishing a personal brand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-establishing-a-personal-brand&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I believe a person is a brand when (s)he is recognizable for the value
(s)he carry and can contribute, without fresh proof. Building a genuine
brand need genuine efforts. Efforts we are already making, and which can
gain a boost if we focus on this short term goal.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Doing so will also incentivize us to engage more in our chosen
activities. Our objective is personal growth of individuals involved in
our team(s), and I believe visibility of this growth is important for
its sustenance. The organization we work for, if it can see us growing
new skills, will be able to leverage them, hence contributing more to
our growth. Before I start fantasizing about all the good this can bring
to us, let&apos;s brainstorm on
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-how-can-we-establish-ourselves-as-brands&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-can-we-establish-ourselves-as-brands&quot;&gt;How can we establish ourselves as brands?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-how-can-we-establish-ourselves-as-brands&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Being a brand is a completely dependent value. Unlike our technical
skills, it is not something that can independently stand on its own. It
is almost entirely dependent on other people. People decide how valuable
you are as a brand. Thinking along these lines, I suppose the first
natural step turns out to be
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;b&gt;Building an online presence&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It boils down to having a home to showcase all the value we are
delivering right now. For starters, this can be a personal website which
can showcase the talks we are giving (since that is where we are
investing most of our time). Eventually, I imagine at least
incorporating all the steps we have chosen in our personal websites:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Talks/Presentations section&lt;/b&gt; for the talks we deliver. Perhaps we
can have &quot;Review&quot; section for the talks we attend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;A blog&lt;/b&gt; for sharing the discussions we have on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.trantorinc.com/&quot;&gt;Trantor forum&lt;/a&gt;, our research notes,
thoughts, opinions and just about anything. Blogs are great for
making noise and gather attention to yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;A Portfolio&lt;/b&gt; for showcasing the open source(?) work we do, as a
demonstration of our growing skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though there are platforms for creating and sharing content, I
firmly believe in having complete ownership of the content we generate.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once we have a platform where we are creating and sharing content, then
we can focus on
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Step 2&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;b&gt;Creating online visibility&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just creating content is not enough, there is too much noise all over
the internet to get noticed organically. Once we have the bare minimum
content creation pipeline, we can then focus on polishing things like
how it looks, SEO, automatic sharing across social media platforms,
analytic and data gathering, automatic updates for new content. I
wouldn&apos;t delve too deep into this right now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;b&gt;Building an offline presence&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another great first step along with aiming to build an online presence
is to build an offline presence. Local brands are very valuable,
probably more valuable than internet celebrities to local communities
and organizations employing us. Building offline presence require
engagement in local community, organizing and attending meetups,
hackathons etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We are in a unique position in this regard, the tech &quot;culture&quot; in our city
(Chandigarh) is yet barely blossoming. It used to be a &lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/dear-first-world-dev-have-a-look-at-your-nightmare/&quot;&gt;rather gloomy picture&lt;/a&gt;
around here, but I believe people have now started seeing the exploitation going
around in the tech scene of the city for what it is. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/find/events/?allMeetups=true&amp;amp;radius=10&amp;amp;userFreeform=Chandigarh%252C+India&amp;amp;mcId=z1018132&amp;amp;mcName=Chandigarh%252C+IN&amp;amp;eventFilter=mysugg&quot;&gt;More and more meetup groups&lt;/a&gt;
are blossoming for the good. Participating in these groups can be a great source
of content for our online presence. Before I start day-dreaming about how we can
hack for Chandigarh, I&apos;ll shut up about it : )
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For this, I suppose the next course of action is to open the sessions we
have been doing for public to attend. Trantor is one of the few
companies I have seen being quite open for organizing meetups in
Tricity, so this shouldn&apos;t be a problem from that front.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here is what I am imagining for our next goal is to attain our grand
objective of nurturing the culture of growth. Please do share your
ideas, opinions and thoughts. You are also always welcome to join us in
our endeavor.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>personal-brands-for-software-developers</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-04-01T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Maximize individual growing in a software team (2 month report)</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/maximize-individual-growing-in-a-software-team-2-month-report/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Couple months ago we started an &lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/how-to-maximize-individual-growth-in-a-software-team/&quot;&gt;initiative&lt;/a&gt; in our team here at &lt;a href=&quot;http://trantorinc.com/&quot;&gt;Trantor&lt;/a&gt; with the
focus on nurturing a culture which optimizes personal growth of an individual in
the team. I believe it is turning out to be quite successful. We decided we&apos;ll
focus on 4 things to achieve our goal:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-interactive-sessions-of-tools-technologies&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;interactive-sessions-of-tools-technologies&quot;&gt;Interactive sessions of tools/technologies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-interactive-sessions-of-tools-technologies&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is where we&apos;ve observed most success. We have had 4 sessions in
past 2 months (we do two-week sprints), with following primary topics:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up your ops game: Ansible and Vagrant &lt;i&gt;(delivered by &lt;b&gt;Charanjit Singh
(me)&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up your ops game: Docker and Docker Compose &lt;i&gt;(delivered by &lt;b&gt;Charanjit
Singh (me)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick and Dirty Kafka &lt;i&gt;(collaboratively delivered by &lt;b&gt;Charanjit Singh
(me), Rupinder Singh, Sheenam Narula, Krishan Saini&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting acquainted with Elasticsearch &lt;i&gt;(delivered by &lt;b&gt;Krishan Saini&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot;&gt;Collaboratively studying open source projects we use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We started off with &lt;code&gt;chai.js&lt;/code&gt;, but after probably spending only a few
minutes each, the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/13dko42FS9kcnpqnrjp9QCouQO0vZHDQ0tslID3BAQBs/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;google
doc&lt;/a&gt; we created for collaboratively creating notes didn&apos;t see much
action.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-being-active-in-trantor-forums&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;being-active-in-trantor-forums&quot;&gt;Being active in Trantor forums&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-being-active-in-trantor-forums&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Plan was to use Trantor Forums as a platform for proposing
(revolutionary) changes in our project. We started off with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.trantorinc.com/t/suggested-improvements-for-tdd-in-veriown-cloud-mutation-testing-and-running-tests-concurrently/74&quot;&gt;a
proposal to introduce mutation testing&lt;/a&gt; in our test-coverage reports,
but didn&apos;t move forward from that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I believe this is because we don&apos;t really spend as much time exploring
new/different things/subject-matters to be able to bring more of such
proposals. This problem is one of many that should fix itself if we are
successful in fostering a culture of self growth in the team.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-day-long-hackathons&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-long-hackathons&quot;&gt;Day long hackathons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-day-long-hackathons&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We are yet to realize this dream. Shiva proposed a neat little idea to
solve a problem faced by Trantor employees, but turned out an official
solution was already in the works and about to be released in couple
weeks (it didn&apos;t). I believe we should have just gone ahead and spend a
day to build what we wanted, just for the heck of it. That would have
been more fruitful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Above points are more than just steps to achieve our goal, I believe,
they are also metrics of our success. How much engagement each of these
get reflects on how much of a self-growth culture is prospering in the
team. I wonder if we can somehow quantize these per-person. If nothing
else, that&apos;ll create some cool graphs to gawk at.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>maximize-individual-growing-in-a-software-team-2-month-report</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-03-26T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>How to maximize individual growth in a software team?</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/how-to-maximize-individual-growth-in-a-software-team/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Working as a solo freelance developer, I used to have lofty ideas of how
a group of people can grow so much more together. I imagined how a mind
in the hive can grow at exponential rates. I made several attempts to
build communities striving for this, a few were successful to some
degree, most were not. Now working in a software development team at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://trantorinc.com/&quot;&gt;Trantor&lt;/a&gt;, I am revisiting these ideas.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I still believe that it&apos;s a worthwhile general direction to move in. In
this post, I am asking myself (and you) the question of &quot;how&quot;. How can
we maximize growth of an individual developer in a software team?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What do I mean by growth? Software is about so much more than just
writing code. It is also philosophy, psychology, mathematics, art and
policy making. Growth as a software developer encompass growth in all
these areas. Learning new tools and technologies is important, but so is
the conceptual knowledge of software development principles, foresight
about how decisions as trivial as naming a variable are going to impact
the future of our code, to perceiving the perception of reader of our
code, and also to make it elegant at many levels.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why focus on an individual&apos;s growth? I believe people are selfish by
design. We think first for ourselves, then for our family, then for our
closest community, and so on. Growing individuals help teams (and
companies) directly as well. A culture of growth attracts good
developers, more good developers are good for teams/companies than
mediocre/bad ones. Optimizing for an individual&apos;s growth seem like a
good idea to me. I think it adds significant positive value to everyone
involved in the process of writing software.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now then, how do we optimize for an individual&apos;s growth? I had a
discussion with the team here and we came up with some points that we
are going to try this
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlassian.com/agile/scrum/sprints&quot;&gt;sprint&lt;/a&gt;. Plan is to
buckle up and finish our committed work a day earlier than planned. Then
on the extra day we earn, we sit back together, analyze two weeks of our
code, share peer feedback, and dig into one or more of following
activities.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-interactive-sessions-of-new-tools-technologies&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;interactive-sessions-of-new-tools-technologies&quot;&gt;Interactive sessions of new tools/technologies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-interactive-sessions-of-new-tools-technologies&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Topmost and shiniest layer of a software developer&apos;s growth is knowledge
of new tools and technologies. Some of us explore more technologies than
others. It was proposed that team members present a tool or technology,
and give an interactive session of something they find cool. This can be
very helpful for knowledge sharing in a diverse team where different
people might have very different roles. For example, I am also handling
the dev-ops in our current project, using tools like
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ansible.com/&quot;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.terraform.io/&quot;&gt;Terraform&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/&quot;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://kubernetes.io/&quot;&gt;Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt;. But rest of the team has no
exposure to these tools. Me giving a session about these tools can be
very helpful for me, rest of the team, and the company. It is also very
much in alignment with my personal belief that every backend web
developer should be familiar with devops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I differ from the proposal by the team a bit though. I think it is cool
to just &quot;show and tell&quot; bi-weekly, giving an interactive session is a
good to have.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot;&gt;Collaboratively studying open source projects we use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another very good suggestion was reading the source code of an open
source project, and collaboratively make notes of the patterns that
codebase has used, things they did right, things they did wrong etc. At
the end of the sprint, we can all discuss the notes we took, if we can
take something and use in our projects etc. We have picked chai.js for
this sprint.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-put-forward-new-approaches-in-forums&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;put-forward-new-approaches-in-forums&quot;&gt;Put forward new approaches in forums&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-put-forward-new-approaches-in-forums&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Often times there are disagreements in team regarding approaches that
can be taken towards a problem. Or sometimes under the pressure of
delivery we pick one approach on another. If the taken approach is too
bad, a technical debt is created, but when it is &quot;good enough&quot;, we just
move on. We don&apos;t want to let this slide. We should reconsider these
small improvements, and keep incrementally improving and challenging our
current practices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We decided that we create posts on Trantor Forums for this, the team
should actively explore the alternative approaches, debate, reach a
consensus and implement the approach into our project. An example of
this is my proposal to bring &lt;a href=&quot;https://stryker-mutator.io/&quot;&gt;mutation
testing&lt;/a&gt; to our workflow. I raised it, and then higher priorities sent
it so deep into the ground that I myself forgot about it. A forum post
can be a healthy reminder in such cases, provide documented discussion
and bring activity in our forums as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-day-long-hackathons&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-long-hackathons&quot;&gt;Day long Hackathons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-day-long-hackathons&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another nice thing that came out of our discussion was that we can
utilize this extra day we earn ourselves as an internal team hackathon.
We can decide on any idea, regardless of its relevance for the
project/work, and the entire team spends a day hacking on it. Member
whose idea is selected can lead the team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think this can be a great way for team members to develop leadership
skills, learn new things, have some open-source portfolio, and most
importantly, feel that rush of starting a new project, and the bliss of
finishing one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Above are few things we are going to start doing starting this sprint.
Please put in comments below if you have opinions and/or suggestions!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>how-to-maximize-individual-growth-in-a-software-team</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-01-21T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>That sounds fun!</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/that-sounds-fun/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I got an opportunity to introspect in a conversation with a client when
he questioned my use of the word &quot;fun&quot;. What do I mean when I say
something is fun? I am not entirely sure. May be when I see something
that excites me a little. People have very different interpretations of
fun. For me it is usually applying creativity to build something.
Activities the involve combination of these two, make me feel most
satisfied. Balance is very important.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But what do I really mean when I say something is fun? I almost never
know if it is going to be fulfilling at the time of making this
declaration. So how do I reach the point where I can say that X is going
to be fun?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It might be an opportunity to learn something new. The unknown scares me. It&apos;s a
thrill and possibly vain feeling of growth. I have a long list of things I want
to learn/master. When my mind sees an opportunity to check a box off of that
list, it gets excited.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It might as well be pure vanity. Vanity plays important part in my mind. When my
subconscious thinks keeping appearances is important, seeing a geeky-sounding
statement just automatically make it blabber &quot;that sounds fun&quot;. Although I try
to keep my narcissism in check, occasional slips are a thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another thing that I think I consider fun is &quot;fixing&quot; something. It is quite
possible to mark me as a control freak; although I won&apos;t voluntarily accept the
label. I do however occasionally attain rather strong opinions about how certain
things shall be. When I see an opportunity to &quot;fix&quot; something to my definition
of right, that is a strong motivational force. However unreliable it might be,
working with motivation is fun.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>that-sounds-fun</guid>
            <pubDate>2018-09-11T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>