<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts categorized as `blog&apos;</title>
        <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        <generator>cl-ownpress</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <image>
            <title>Posts categorized as `blog&apos;</title>
            <url>/images/spooky-avatar.png</url>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>Reading, and not forgetting</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/reading-and-not-forgetting/</link>
            <description>
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org0c59ff6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org0c59ff6&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org0c59ff6&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I forget everything I read, as soon as I am done reading (a sentence). Over
time, reading turned from leisure to labor. Pressure of having to remember
things took the fun out of reading. Small attention span and easily getting
distracted made it even worse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org4eabe67&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org4eabe67&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org4eabe67&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Take notes to outsource remembering, and make reading more engaging.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Creating well-organized notes take the burden of remembering away. The act of
taking notes keep my attention tethered.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org1b2835a&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org1b2835a&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org1b2835a&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note taking process need to be designed to reduce the burden that note-taking
itself can become. Key here is not taking notes, it is crafting a smooth
note-taking workflow.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org180ceae&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;org180ceae&quot;&gt;Components&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-org180ceae&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My reading workflow involves 3 major components
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emacs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Denote, an Emacs package for managing notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spookfox: An Emacs package for controlling Firefox from Emacs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org06b4d42&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;org06b4d42&quot;&gt;Emacs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-org06b4d42&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Emacs is the center stage on which everything else plays. I chose Emacs, because
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is where I spend most time on my computer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am very comfortable hacking on it, so tuning things to make my workflow
smoother is an already acquired habit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I already have a thriving documenting system/workflow in Emacs. I have to
externalize a lot of my mind, for which I&apos;ve been using Emacs for over a
decade now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org6da1b27&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;org6da1b27&quot;&gt;Denote&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-org6da1b27&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/protesilaos/denote&quot;&gt;Denote&lt;/a&gt; is my present choice of note-taking Emacs package. It provide structure
to my notes, and thin tooling to navigate this structure. Notes are kept in
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;timestamp&amp;gt;-&amp;lt;slug&amp;gt;__&amp;lt;tags&amp;gt;.org&lt;/code&gt; format. This makes it easy to find a note by
keywords and tags even from outside Emacs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org50bcf5f&quot; class=&quot;outline-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;org50bcf5f&quot;&gt;Spookfox&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-4&quot; id=&quot;text-org50bcf5f&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/spookfox&quot;&gt;Spookfox&lt;/a&gt; is my answer to &quot;but what about when you need to leave Emacs?&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I consume most of the educational content on the web, that usually means
Firefox. I built myself a small system (Spookfox) to make Emacs speak with
Firefox.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is sort of a launch-pad for quickly creating Firefox addons which talk to
Emacs. Most commonly I use it for accessing content I have in browser, e.g
getting information about current browser tab, video being played etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org54bf55f&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;org54bf55f&quot;&gt;The workflow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-org54bf55f&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It boils down to a single key-combo: &lt;code&gt;C-c n r&lt;/code&gt; open a &quot;reading note&quot; in my
scratchpad. &lt;code&gt;C-c n r&lt;/code&gt; opens the same note regardless of when I open it; i.e it
don&apos;t re-create a new note every time. This is super useful when you are blessed
with the combo of laziness and forgetfulness.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Scratchpad is a mechanism for quickly launching an Emacs window for capturing
some information. This usually means bringing an Emacs window to focus with a
keypress.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A reading note is a note which has
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;reading&lt;/code&gt; tag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; property, which is 95% of the times the web URL (from Firefox)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;reading&lt;/code&gt; subdirectory in my notes
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It seems redundant given that there is already a &lt;code&gt;reading&lt;/code&gt; tag, but I keep it
not for categorizing the notes but to keep them out of my normal
notes-search.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My &quot;normal&quot; notes are conceptual, they come from different sources and are
essence of my understanding from different sources. My reading notes &lt;b&gt;are&lt;/b&gt; these
sources.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&quot;Reading&quot; notes free me up to not worry about the structure of the notes I am
taking or its impact on other notes. After taking the &quot;reading&quot; notes, I review
them and move appropriate parts (or summary/rephrase) them in my &quot;normal&quot;
note(s), while linking back to the reading note.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This create a neat web of sources and concepts. I get to be free from the burden
of keeping track of where the knowledge in my notes is coming from. When I need
to track something back to its source, I get nice hand-drafted summary of the
original source.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With Spookfox I extend this workflow to (Youtube) videos as well. In addition to
automatically opening the note, I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/spookmax.d/blame/7f5f0fbde3777662d2d2fb2baefc18a71c012855/readme.org#L1528-L1610&quot;&gt;Emacs configured to insert video
timestamps with my notes&lt;/a&gt;. This essentially annotate Youtube videos, and have
come super handy recently in my German language study.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20221023T135817</guid>
            <pubDate>2023-01-15T20:46:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>I am moving to Berlin</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/i-am-moving-to-berlin/</link>
            <description>
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org0a739fe&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org0a739fe&quot;&gt;Why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org0a739fe&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are several reasons I stated in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitspook.in/blog/after-6-months-of-voluntary-unemployment/&quot;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Other than those,
here are a few more:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Peer pressure
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At this point it is customary for Punjabis to immigrate to a foreign country.
Since I was little I was conditioned to want to go to a developed country, so
it had become a deep rooted desire. My choice was of &lt;b&gt;which&lt;/b&gt; country, and
going against the advice of almost everyone in my family, I chose to not go
to Canada or Australia. I was promised more money and easier life in those
countries, but I see more of my personal goals in alignment in Germany.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Cold weather
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Punjab has colder weather than most parts of India, and they&apos;re my favorite
part of the year. I absolutely abhor Punjab&apos;s summers. Germany&apos;s cold weather
was appealing.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Europe
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The fact that I get access to more than one country was also a factor. If I
still have the appetite, I can move to a different culture relatively easily.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Rules
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am a sucker for rules. If they are sensible and sensibly implemented, they
can free you up in so many ways. Many lines-of-thought can be short-circuited
and mental resources invested in more interesting things. Germany as far as I
have researched online have more sensible rules, and a culture of mostly
following them.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orge38a1b3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orge38a1b3&quot;&gt;How I am feeling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orge38a1b3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am scared shitless. I am full of stress and anxiety, I can barely sleep and
can&apos;t focus on anything. I have stopped drinking coffee because I no longer need
caffeine for the jitters.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is way more scarier than what I imagined. When I decided to move to Berlin I
was excited, a little scared too but also looking forward to it. Now I am
fighting myself to not just drop the whole thing every second of the day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am not an adventurous person, I find all forms of traveling tiresome. I stay
at home to recharge. Fear I am feeling right now however is more than the
ambiguity of going somewhere new. Me burning through my savings during past few
months is also a major contributor. I have made this huge decision, and spent
almost all my remaining funds to book housing, tickets and stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgfb3f383&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgfb3f383&quot;&gt;What lies ahead&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgfb3f383&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I intend to come back to India after at most 2 years and at least 1 year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
1 year minimum because 1 year is the limit I am putting for myself to buckle up
and stay in Berlin, experience stuff even if I don&apos;t want to. I am hoping it&apos;ll
be enough to reveal whether my feeling that being outside my comfort zone will
make me do more fulfilling things is true or not. 2 year maximum because I think
2 years should be enough for personal growth by being in a foreign country.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I find the ideas of e-governance and using technology in public administration
most exciting. I think India is the right place to make most impact with these.
I want to establish a parallel social administration system, which can help the
State&apos;s system, or fight it to make a positive impact. This is also one of the
reasons I have decided to go work outside India. Because it is a significant
commitment and I don&apos;t want to find myself taking breaks from it for other
things I wanted to do which might significantly disrupt this commitment.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Or all this could just be fantasies. In almost every phase of life, whenever I
felt like things need to be improved I have fantasized about how things could
have been made better. At my home, in school, in college, in software companies,
in my village, in my city, in the companies I worked in; pretty much everywhere.
I have not always taken action, and often moved to the newer set of problems
forgetting the old ones as they became irrelevant to me. I won&apos;t fight it if it
happens this time as well. I can&apos;t fight every battle, I prefer letting the
fights pick themselves for me. But so far I am fully intent on returning to
India and participate somehow in public administration.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20221122T151233</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-11-22T16:12:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Insolent Software</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/insolent-software/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I am used to put limits on myself. Finding reasons, some in authority, most in
circumstance; to not solve the problems I&apos;ve judged solvable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People putting limits on themselves is not something new or unique to building
software. It is a recurring pattern in human behavior. Well meaning reasons are
often rationalizations for fear of unknown, or that of actually putting in the
work. Just as often, there are actual limits universe has put on us, crossing
which come at great cost.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But software is &lt;b&gt;our&lt;/b&gt; domain. Things writ in stone in &quot;real&quot; world are not
necessarily so in the wonderful world of software development. What is subjected
to physical laws in real world is a matter of choice of constraints. Often we
get to pick and choose, trade the expensive ones for those inconvenient, but
still make the impossible probable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When the imaginary constraints are dropped, what is left behind is curiosity and
wonder. It is in essence, a source of joy. It is similar to re-discovering joy
in tending to fruitless flowers after a lifetime of growing crops for commerce.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I say imaginary constraints, I am speaking in the sense of Max Stirner&apos;s
spooks. Imaginary constraints, for example those of
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;authority: am I allowed to do this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tribalism: will my team adopt it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;economy: can I monetize it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;romance: will it scale?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vanity: is it elegant?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wanted a term to express this kind of software. Anarchism comes close to the
meaning I want to convey, but it is too nuanced. What I mean is simpler. An
unapologetic form of &lt;i&gt;&quot;works on my machine&quot;&lt;/i&gt;. Software which is deliberately
insolent toward the processes which the creator believes get in their way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is a deceptively simple thing. It is not easy reaching a solution so free.
This line of thinking is very much going against the grain of human
civilization. Unlearning the lessons society has taught us before we knew
learning, does not come easy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What is even harder is identifying problems which can be solved with insolence.
These problems are often invisible. Problems we accept and get used to, and
don&apos;t see as problems at all. Until someone solves them and obviousness of it
hit us like a brick. Perhaps recognizing and solving such problems is what
separates inventors from the rest of us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a kid, reading of inventors of the golden age of science would fill me up
with fantasies of becoming one myself someday. It saddens me to think that I
have not yet become one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Not all software can be written this way. Line between imaginary and real
becomes blurry as more people believe in something. Very often we need to
maintain the charades of make-believe, simply because we can not be alone in the
solution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There is one form of software, which almost always can be insolent. Software
built for yourself. Not apps to sell or startups to change the world. Simple
scripts, big and small, to solve your personal problems. Over last few months, I
have come to associate personal computing with same feelings I have when playing
something like Factorio or Cities Skylines. It is a joyous endeavor, we shall
talk of on another day.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20210429T070902</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-11-07T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>After 6 months of voluntary unemployment</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/after-6-months-of-voluntary-unemployment/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
For the last six months, I have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitspook.in/blog/i-have-quit-my-job&quot;&gt;voluntarily unemployed&lt;/a&gt;. Here&apos;s a brief
summary of how the last six months shaped my thoughts, and an abstract plan of
what I intend to do next.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgaaffce2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgaaffce2&quot;&gt;Mental health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgaaffce2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I needed this break a lot more than I thought I did. Being perpetually restless
had been my state of being for too long. It felt good, to breath out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When writing software, you reach a certain point where things start falling into
place, the uncertainties are answered for and you can feel that the decisions
you made were right. Those few seconds of invincibility spanned over several
(not always consequent) days, because I felt it was me in control. Them I
remember most cherishingly. It was a kind of high I intend to chase again in
life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Primary reason for which I quit my job was the curiosity about whether I can
manage my ADHD now; or if I still need the crutches of accountability. On job, I
could effortlessly perform well, in contrast to solo freelancing. My therapist
had suggested it will get better with age.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had more good days than bad, which is a win. Unfortunately I still don&apos;t have
a definite answer to consider the matter resolved. More on this later (below).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgb5756fc&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgb5756fc&quot;&gt;Social work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgb5756fc&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When busy with material responsibilities, I used to fantasize that if I had more
free time I could do so much more for people around me. When I had it, I tried
to start with the place closest to my heart.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tried to &quot;help&quot; my village by contributing to its small primary school, least
politically charged of situations there. Well, not so much as tried to help as
probed with a long stick to assess the willingness to be helped. I quickly found
out that a significant involvement there is a luxury I can&apos;t afford just yet.
Established power structures see everything new as threat, and eagerly sabotage
what they can get away with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So I chose a different avenue. One just as dear to me, but where I have more
experience and room to maneuver. I decided to make &lt;a href=&quot;https://entropyhacker.space/&quot;&gt;another attempt&lt;/a&gt; to nurture a
healthy tech culture in my city. It produced mixed results because I was not
able to put in as much energy as it demanded.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org400a956&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org400a956&quot;&gt;Mistake of learning Common Lisp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org400a956&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was running full speed building &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/press.el&quot;&gt;foolish&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/spookfox&quot;&gt;things&lt;/a&gt;. Then lisp came calling.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video autoplay loop alt=&quot;Wile E Coyote hitting the tunnel. Tunnel hits back.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;/videos/hit-it.webm&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was working on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/entropy&quot;&gt;Entropy&lt;/a&gt;, to build a software to help me do the leg work of
building a tech community. Thought came that it is for hackers, so it should be
hackable. Lisp is praised for how hackable it is. It is also praised for its
expressiveness. Momentum is something I was finding hard to achieve with Rust,
because of my inexperience and perhaps the nature of the language and problem I
was trying to solve with it. At least checking lisp out seemed reasonable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After 30 years of living with them, I have come to recognize desires of pivotal
nature. In the face of these sublimely consuming whims, I can either do what
they say, or not do anything at all (I am told it is common with ADHD, so not to
beat myself too much about it).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve learned that it is possible to suppress these urges by feigning blindness.
My mistake was that of indecision. It is not possible to take a sip and not
gulp. I chose to look at it, but took too long to engage. I got thrown off the
build-mode.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have observed that I operate in two distinct modes: build-mode and study-mode.
Although building something is always a learning experience, and to learn
something I gotta build something; it is efficient to treat them as separate. It
is also easier on my mental peace.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This time, the transition between the two modes was not smooth. Getting
involuntarily thrown out of the workshop left me with (mental) bruises. This
incident is the reason I still consider the matter of my self-discipline
unresolved. Although the fact that there were only 2 such incidents over 6
months is a win by itself (another was when I fell in love with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://practicalguidetoevil.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;, and
spent weeks doing nothing else).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I filled the downtime during transition with another thing I wanted to do, and
probably would not have done otherwise. I traveled.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org4b515ea&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org4b515ea&quot;&gt;Travel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org4b515ea&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am not much of a site-seeing kind of guy. I find traveling exhausting,
regardless of how beautiful the views or how fun the activities. Being a tourist
is not for me. I like to stay and experience. I enjoy exploring/observing people
(people watching?). Witnessing people go by their lives is soothing. There is a
warm fuzzy feeling behind every smile, however mundane.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So I traveled the way I truly like, perhaps for the first time. For about 3
months trotting around the mountains of Uttrakhand, visiting people in their
homes (home stays). Observing a way of life familiar yet strange.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It came as a surprise how eye-opening the experience turned out to be, despite
being quite event-less. It was like learning a new language or studying math. I
could almost feel my brain building new connections. This is one of the few
feelings which still stays exciting even when the rat-race and hoarding have
stopped being as stimulating. I did not expect to find an entirely new source of
it in an experience like this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is also the easiest methods in terms of active participation, compared to all
the other sources (most are a variations of intellectual exercises; solving a
challenging problem, crafting an elegant solution etc). It does have its costs,
but I believe they do not overlap with those of other methods; so they can be
employed at the same time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I take it to mean I can have twice of what makes me feel most alive, just by
putting myself in a place 🤯
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org458387f&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org458387f&quot;&gt;What comes next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org458387f&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can perhaps spend a few more months before I run out of savings, but the
dimming safety net has already started making me anxious. I miss the tribe-like
feeling of working in a team, so I am actually looking forward to join work for
that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most freeing would be to start a business of my own; not because it will leave
me with more free time, but because I can feel more like myself when working on
something I find meaningful. But that won&apos;t be profitable right out of the door,
so perhaps after a bit more grinding I can save up to give myself a chance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The grind is decided, but I will not choose misery along with. I intend to chase
the feeling of growth and fulfillment. With these constraints, some more
decisions make themselves:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can&apos;t stay at home. Being home is extremely comfortable, but with
comfort comes stagnation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need a job which leaves me with enough time I can invest in something
demanding like math&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to put myself in a foreign culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Putting these into practice, I have decided I&apos;ll move to Berlin for a few years.
The city makes itself a good place to be for me for a few reasons:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practically, it is perhaps the easiest to immigrate to for an individual
Indian citizen, with a job in hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has a good hacker culture, something I&apos;ve always wanted to experience but
have only ever read about&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;German culture seem like a great fit for my personal tastes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get to learn a new language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;German work culture is praised (on the Internet) for respecting boundaries and
giving a priority to life over money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I ever decide to seek higher education (which is likely), German education
policies are good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now that that is decided, what&apos;s left to figure out is how to go about it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgee5fc11&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgee5fc11&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgee5fc11&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After 6 months of voluntary unemployment, I am the same man I was before it.
Things I experienced and burdens I unburdened could be achieved by other means
as well. Perhaps I&apos;ve sown seeds to make me a different person in future, but
they will take time to bloom. It is a guessing game, same as what might have
happened had I done it differently.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As for the journey to be where I already was, I&apos;ll do it again if I can.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20220921T194836</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-10-03T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Extending org-mode to handle youtube links</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/extending-org-mode-to-handle-youtube-links/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//youtube.com/embed/eaZUZCzaIgw&quot; title=&quot;nil&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org73719e2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org73719e2&quot;&gt;Requirement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org73719e2&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to open youtube links in my notes in &lt;code&gt;mpv&lt;/code&gt; instead of opening the
browser&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;When exporting to HTML, youtube links should become embedded videos instead
of hyperlinks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org6ff7963&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org6ff7963&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org6ff7963&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Org has a concept of &apos;link types&apos;. We can add a new type of link and have it
behave the way we want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;org-link-parameters&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This variable contains link types and how they behave on follow (i.e when
someone opens the link with &lt;code&gt;C-c C-o&lt;/code&gt;), export etc. A type of a link is
determined by the string before first &quot;:&quot; in it. e.g &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bitspook.in&quot;&gt;https://bitspook.in&lt;/a&gt;&quot; has
&lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt; type, &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;file:///etc&quot;&gt;file:///etc&lt;/a&gt;&quot; has &lt;code&gt;file&lt;/code&gt; type.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Items in this list has 2 main components:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First element is string representing the link type&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key-value pairs of behavior name (e.g &lt;code&gt;:follow&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;:export&lt;/code&gt;) and
function which handles that behavior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For example:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;((&lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;yt&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:follow&lt;/span&gt; spook-org--follow-yt-link &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:export&lt;/span&gt; spook-org--export-yt-link)
 (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;eww&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:follow&lt;/span&gt; org-eww-open &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:store&lt;/span&gt; org-eww-store-link))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;org-link-set-parameters&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This function is used to add new link-types (and also to add new behavior to
existing ones). You can check the docs for &lt;code&gt;org-link-parameters&lt;/code&gt; (with &lt;code&gt;C-h v
  org-link-parameters&lt;/code&gt;) to see arguments provided to each type of callback.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here&apos;s the code I&apos;ve added in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/spookmax.d&quot;&gt;my emacs config&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;spook-org--follow-yt-link&lt;/span&gt; (path prefix)
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;let*&lt;/span&gt; ((url (format &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;https:%s&quot;&lt;/span&gt; path))
         (proc-name (format &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;*yt://%s*&quot;&lt;/span&gt; url)))
    (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; prefix (executable-find &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;mpv&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
        (browse-url url)
      (make-process &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:name&lt;/span&gt; proc-name &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:buffer&lt;/span&gt; proc-name &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:command&lt;/span&gt; `(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;mpv&quot;&lt;/span&gt; ,url))
      (message &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;Launched mpv in buffer: %s&quot;&lt;/span&gt; proc-name))))

(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;spook-org--export-yt-link&lt;/span&gt; (path desc backend)
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;when&lt;/span&gt; (eq backend &apos;html)
    (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;let*&lt;/span&gt; ((video-id (cadar (url-parse-query-string path)))
           (url (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; (string-empty-p video-id) path
                  (format &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;//youtube.com/embed/%s&quot;&lt;/span&gt; video-id))))
      (format
       &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;&amp;lt;iframe width=\&quot;560\&quot; height=\&quot;315\&quot; src=\&quot;%s\&quot; title=\&quot;%s\&quot; frameborder=\&quot;0\&quot; allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
       url desc))))

(org-link-set-parameters &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;yt&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:follow&lt;/span&gt; #&apos;spook-org--follow-yt-link &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:export&lt;/span&gt; #&apos;spook-org--export-yt-link)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;make-process&lt;/code&gt; will create a background buffer named &lt;code&gt;*yt://&amp;lt;url&amp;gt;*&lt;/code&gt; which
allow monitoring and killing the mpv process.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Update&lt;/i&gt;: Use &lt;code&gt;make-process&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;async-shell-command&lt;/code&gt; for launching mpv.
Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/emacs/comments/xls0ih/extending_orgmode_to_handle_youtube_links/iplpk57/&quot;&gt;nv-elisp on /r/emacs&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org508e06b&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org508e06b&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org508e06b&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;C-c C-o&lt;/code&gt; (i.e &lt;code&gt;org-open-at-point&lt;/code&gt;) on a &lt;code&gt;yt://&lt;/code&gt; link opens the youtube video
in mpv&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;C-u C-c C-o&lt;/code&gt; (i.e &lt;code&gt;org-open-at-point&lt;/code&gt; with an prefix argument) on a &lt;code&gt;yt://&lt;/code&gt;
link opens the video in browser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When exported to HTML, all &lt;code&gt;yt://&lt;/code&gt; links file are exported as embedded
youtube videos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgb5b17f6&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgb5b17f6&quot;&gt;Bonus gains 💪&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgb5b17f6&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Recently I&apos;ve been building a tool (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/cl-ownpress&quot;&gt;cl-ownpress&lt;/a&gt;) which to make blogging a
zero-effort activity for me. Since I have already built a habit of judicious
note taking, publishing a subset of my notes will enable maintaining an active
blog without doing any &quot;work&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve also been making thickly-accented-awkardly-narrated youtube videos. These
are almost always &lt;i&gt;tldr;&lt;/i&gt; videos for my blog posts. So they get embedded in my
blog posts.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&apos;Blog with notes + embed youtube videos&apos; become easier to do with this little
tinkering. Since &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/cl-ownpress&quot;&gt;cl-ownpress&lt;/a&gt; uses my running Emacs to publish my posts, I don&apos;t
need to make any change in my blogging setup. I can embed my &lt;i&gt;tldr;&lt;/i&gt; videos in
my blog posts by just prefixing youtube links with &lt;code&gt;yt://&lt;/code&gt; instead of
&lt;code&gt;https://&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am pretty happy that I got zero work blogging-setup, and zero work
extending-the-blogging-setup as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20220922T174420</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-09-26T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>How I manage my passwords</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/how-i-manage-my-passwords/</link>
            <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/faFJzaAjy0E&quot; title=&quot;tldr; video&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgc1d977b&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgc1d977b&quot;&gt;My requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgc1d977b&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;No third-parties&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don&apos;t want to put my trust in any third party. Be it Google/Mozilla (via
saved passwords in browser), or some dedicated password manager like KeyPass.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Simplicity&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Simple tools are easier to understand and bend to my will. It also means I&apos;ll
be able to intervene when something goes wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Composability&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I should be able to make the tool a part of my forever changing workflow. It
should play nice with presence/absence of other tools.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgf432e7b&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgf432e7b&quot;&gt;Tools I chose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgf432e7b&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.passwordstore.org/&quot;&gt;Pass&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;i&gt;The simple password manager&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think it is as simple as it gets. A password-store in pass is a git repo
(so a directory) which contains gpg encrypted files. Each file represent one
set of credentials, and can contain all the plain-text, not just password and
username. E.g I often end up storing recovery codes for accounts in these.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are no third-parties involved, encryption happens on my machine, and I
can store my password store anywhere I want (e.g a private git repo on
github).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most pass operations are convenience wrappers on basic operations provided by
other tools; e.g &lt;code&gt;edit = decrypting a file + open it in an editor +
   re-encrypting + git-commit&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Pass has a whole ecosystem of tools written around it, which makes it an easy
choice considering how much work it saves me when integrating it in my
workflow.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/carnager/rofi-pass&quot;&gt;rofi-pass&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;i&gt;Rofi-based UI for pass for desktop&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/davatorium/rofi&quot;&gt;Rofi&lt;/a&gt; is a lightweight popup choice-selection UI, which has so far worked
out-of-the-box on all window-managers I have used. &lt;i&gt;rofi-pass&lt;/i&gt; extends rofi
with:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to search and select credentials stored in pass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Auto-fill credentials into any GUI app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/fireword&quot;&gt;fireword&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;i&gt;Converting easy-to-remember passwords to hard-to-crack ones&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Not all credentials need to be saved. Occasionally I need to create
&lt;i&gt;throwaway&lt;/i&gt; accounts, for which I like to keep easy-to-guess (for me)
passwords. But I want even these password to be opaque (so analyzing them
wouldn&apos;t reveal a theme of my throwaway passwords).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fireword is a small script I wrote many years ago which create insane
passwords from any string. Even a single change of character in a string
creates wildly different output. So instead of passing a plain easy-to-guess
password, I give them to fireword and use its output.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For example, &lt;code&gt;pass&lt;/code&gt; becomes &lt;code&gt;5B72?[30:F&lt;/code&gt; but &lt;code&gt;passs&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;3Ec012aD5(&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/android-password-store/Android-Password-Store#readme&quot;&gt;Android Password Store&lt;/a&gt; - Android app for accessing pass
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Password store on android allows using the passwords I create/edit on my
desktop on my mobile and tablet. I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://syncthing.net/&quot;&gt;syncthing&lt;/a&gt; to sync my password store to
my mobile devices.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org12671e8&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org12671e8&quot;&gt;Workflow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org12671e8&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgb56e9ba&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;orgb56e9ba&quot;&gt;Add/edit/delete a password&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-orgb56e9ba&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For all these operations, I use the &lt;code&gt;pass&lt;/code&gt; cli. It is simple and intuitive, and
mostly just delegates to other Linux utilities. For example, deleting a password
for &lt;i&gt;my-acc&lt;/i&gt; account in &lt;i&gt;example.com&lt;/i&gt; is &lt;code&gt;pass rm example.com/my-acc&lt;/code&gt;; and
deleting all accounts in &lt;i&gt;example.com&lt;/i&gt; is &lt;code&gt;pass rm -r example.com&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video autoplay loop&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;/videos/how-i-manage-my-passwords/1--pass-cli.webm&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I used to use &lt;code&gt;pass generate&lt;/code&gt; for creating new passwords, which creates cryptic
hard (impossible?) to crack strings. Over time however, I have come to prefer
password phrases which are easy to type by hand. I pick 3-4 words that come to
my mind at a time, and make a loose sentence out of them to create a new
password. For example &lt;code&gt;libauvutilcelingfan&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgf7810a9&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;orgf7810a9&quot;&gt;Using a password&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-orgf7810a9&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Using &lt;code&gt;pass&lt;/code&gt; CLI for using a password gets tedious quickly. Using a password is
much more common than adding/editing/deleting one. So I use &lt;i&gt;rofi-pass&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It gives me a nice prompt to search and select the credentials I want, and
autofills them. It is smart enough to recognize that credentials are more than
just a password; so if you edit your password file to look like:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-text&quot;&gt;mypassword

user: myuser
some-other-key: some-val
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;rofi-pass&lt;/i&gt; will allow you to select the key and auto-type its value. It
recognizes first line as the password, and a value with &lt;code&gt;user&lt;/code&gt; key to autotype
both username and password in forms which ask for first username and then
password (on the same form).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video autoplay loop&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;/videos/how-i-manage-my-passwords/2--using-rofi-pass.webm&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org9b044bc&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;org9b044bc&quot;&gt;Throwaway passwords&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-org9b044bc&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&apos;t &quot;install&quot; fireword since it is just a self-contained python script. But
because throwaway passwords, although temporary, tend to be entered frequently
(private browsing), I have created a small command in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/stumpwm.d&quot;&gt;my stumpwm configuration&lt;/a&gt;
to make it easy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-lisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;defvar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;spook/fireword-bin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;~/Documents/work/fireword/fireword&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)

(defcommand fireword (pass len)
  ((&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:password&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;Password: &quot;&lt;/span&gt;)
   (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:password&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;Length: &quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
  (run-shell-command (format nil  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;~a ~a ~a | xclip -sel clip&quot;&lt;/span&gt; spook/fireword-bin pass len)))

(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;define-key&lt;/span&gt; *top-map* (kbd &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;s-P&quot;&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;fireword&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the end I get a nice prompt on pressing &lt;code&gt;C-P&lt;/code&gt; to enter my password and
desired length, get the fireword copied to clipboard which I then paste in a
private browser window.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video autoplay loop&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;/videos/how-i-manage-my-passwords/3-using-fireword-with-stumpwm.webm&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20220912T152156</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-09-19T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Using ELisp as an HTML templating engine</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/using-elisp-as-an/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/9Pcv5W1Gnvg&quot; title=&quot;TLDR Video&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
HTML templating engines like &lt;a href=&quot;https://jinja.palletsprojects.com/en/3.1.x/&quot;&gt;Jinja&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://handlebarsjs.com/&quot;&gt;handlebars&lt;/a&gt; are commonly used in web
development for weaving data into HTML.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For last couple of days, I&apos;ve been porting &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/brandi&quot;&gt;my Hakyll based static-site generator&lt;/a&gt;
to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/press.el&quot;&gt;Emacs Lisp&lt;/a&gt;, for a more fluent thought-publishing workflow. I found myself in
need of an HTML templating engine so I could convert data about my blog posts
and notes to HTML.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I found that we actually don&apos;t need an HTML templating engine to convert ELisp
to HTML. Emacs has built-in capability to work with HTML, we can piggy back on
that to get a templating engine without adding any new code.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can represent DOM, which is a tree data-structure, as a lisp form
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Consider following HTML element
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;=&lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;container&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;href&lt;/span&gt;=&lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;https://google.com&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;Google&amp;lt;/&lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/&lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;div&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can write it as a lisp form like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;&apos;(div ((class . &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;container&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
      (a ((href . &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;https://google.com&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
         &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;Google&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Note that this is a quoted lisp form. Which means this code isn&apos;t actually
executed, &lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; aren&apos;t lisp functions. We can just put in any symbol
there, and it is treated as a DOM node.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;shr-dom-to-xml&lt;/code&gt; converts this lisp form to an HTML string:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; ((my-url &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;https://google.com&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
  (shr-dom-to-xml
   `(div ((class . &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;container&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))
         (a ((href . ,my-url))
            &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;Google&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot;&gt;
&amp;lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&quot;https://google.com&quot;&amp;gt;Google&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
In this example we changed the quote used to showcase how we can run arbitrary
lisp forms in our DOM to weave data into it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can check &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/press.el&quot;&gt;my wip ELisp blogging setup&lt;/a&gt; for more complex examples, and some
glue code I&apos;ve written to make using ELisp as HTML templating engine easier.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20220408T161902</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-04-08T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>I have quit my job</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/i-have-quit-my-job/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Several years ago, I decided to quit freelancing and do a day job. The
job would pay much less but I was struggling with mental health (ADHD).
On my therapist&apos;s suggestion, I decided to give the job thing a try. It
worked wonderfully, my struggles with discipline are a thing of past. Or
so I believe.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once again, I have decided to take a drastic step. I have decided to
quit my day job. This is my last week at work, coming Monday I will be
unemployed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don&apos;t have a plan. I haven&apos;t planned to leave work permanently. I
don&apos;t have an ambition either, world changing or otherwise. This post is
me deciding to take a break from work and finding reasons for doing so,
after the fact.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-curiosity&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;curiosity&quot;&gt;Curiosity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-curiosity&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is exciting. The possibilities are endless. It is scary. Endless
possibilities means a lot of them lead to failure. Odds are stacked in
my favor in some regards; I am good at what I do, world will still need
good software engineers 6 months down the road. They are not so much in
my favor in some regards; precedence says I will fall into inaction and
misery, and achieve nothing. Complete nothing. I&apos;ve almost always lost
in my struggles with ADHD in past. There is a good chance that I am
deluding myself into believing that this time will be any different.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am curios of whether it is me who has finally tamed the beast, or if I
am going to need the structure a formal job as crutches.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-exhaustion&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;exhaustion&quot;&gt;Exhaustion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-exhaustion&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am sort of exhausted from making pragmatic decisions all the time.
Building software needs a delicate balance between what makes your
software technically good, and what makes it actually good. Actually
good software solve problems despite its own imperfections.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I want to spend some time making impractical decisions. I want to build
software which solve the problem of making me happy, or at least
entertained.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-heartbreak&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;heartbreak&quot;&gt;Heartbreak&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-heartbreak&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I joined my last company because I was sold on an idea. An idea of a
project which was solving a meaningful problem, and was challenging
enough to keep me engaged. I dedicated myself to that, gladly making
many sacrifices in my personal life. I got to build a team and lead it
with autonomy, we built a stolid product (actually, a part of it). And
then I was taken off that project, with what felt like without warning.
I accepted that decision because it was practical for the company.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But I was unprepared for the aftershock. It was traumatizing. With a
snap I was plucked out of one project, and added into another with the
expectation of establishing myself into a similar critical role. The
fact that I did it without a break didn&apos;t help. I could no longer find
that sense of belonging anymore, in this new project, or others that
came after.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Perhaps I am not suited for working in a services company with rapid
transitions. Perhaps I set my expectations wrong. Perhaps there was a
lapse in communication. Perhaps, I need to spend some time grieving.
Regardless, I need a break.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-self-growth&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;self-growth&quot;&gt;Self growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-self-growth&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As good a workplace as Trantor has been, I&apos;ve been feeling stagnated for
a while. I have learned a lot outside of work, but work has started to
feel like work, which makes me miserable. Overlap between things I want
to learn and things which my job needs have been steadily and
increasingly decreasing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many of the things I want to learn need dedication which I can&apos;t afford
while working full-time as a software engineer. There is no off-switch,
I am always working; even when I am not sitting in front of a computer.
Things I want to learn need me 100% there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-social-work&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;social-work&quot;&gt;Social work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-social-work&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the most delusional of all the reasons I&apos;ve cooked up. I imagine
building solutions to problems I see in my surroundings. For some
irrational reason, I feel a desire to give back to society. This is
perhaps narcissism finding its way around my reasoning, coloring itself
righteous. More logical would be to uproot myself and immigrate to a
place where people have already solved the basic problems of human
coexistence.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I was in school I used to imagine how the school can be reformed,
in college it was the education system, as a freelance developer I
actually started acting on my imaginations and trying to improve my
local tech community. Several times. As an employee, I tried to uplift
my team (and imagined work reform, but never acted on it). Now, I
imagine solutions for many of the problems I see my village face. I am
curious if I will put them into action.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-what-lies-ahead&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-lies-ahead&quot;&gt;What lies ahead?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-what-lies-ahead&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&apos;t know. There are too many things. There is a very good chance
that I am going to freeze in the face of choice, be miserable for a few
weeks, and get back to doing a day job. I am going to take time off for
as long as I feel like it, or run out of money. During this time I will
try to learn things and build software that bring me joy. Try to teach
myself how to focus more on the journey.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve observed that many activities (including building software) can be
a meditative experience. If you can let go of the goals, you can quite
enjoy the act. Counter intuitively, the result is often much better. But
it is not always on time, which makes this a dangerous thing to do when
someone else is paying for my work. Perhaps the last bit is because I am
not yet well versed in it. This too might be a matter of finding a
balance. I&apos;ll explore.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>i-have-quit-my-job</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-03-24T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Using org-mode as an SQL playground</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/using-org-mode-as-an-sql-playground/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Showcase video:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DY7t4T4TmUU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For every web app I work on, a database client is always present for exploring
data and building complex queries. Recently, I have moved on from my PgAdmin to
org-mode for this purpose, because why not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode allows executing code snippets and can show results in a nice tabular
form. But org-mode isn&apos;t &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cvedetails.com/vulnerability-list/vendor_id-26/product_id-320/Microsoft-Office.html&quot;&gt;written by Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;. So it don&apos;t allow arbitrary code
execution without our explicit consent. To tell org-mode that it is okay to
execute SQL snippets, we need to run following elisp snippet:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;with-eval-after-load&lt;/span&gt; &apos;org
(org-babel-do-load-languages
 &apos;org-babel-load-languages
 &apos;((sql . t))))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode has a number of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.orgmode.org/worg/org-contrib/babel/languages/ob-doc-sql.html#org7f0941b&quot;&gt;header arguments for SQL blocks&lt;/a&gt; which can be used to
configure how a particular SQL source-code snippet is executed. Most important
ones perhaps are:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;:engine&lt;/code&gt; which tells which database to run the SQL against&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;:dbhost&lt;/code&gt; to configure the database host, most likely &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; for a dev
environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;:dbport&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;:dbuser&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;:dbpassword&lt;/code&gt; for database authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;:database&lt;/code&gt; for database name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By default org-mode runs the code snippets in current OS environment. I use this
fact to get the ability to run SQL against our postgres database without passing
most of the above arguments. Postgres allows setting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/libpq-envars.html&quot;&gt;some environment&lt;/a&gt; variables,
which it then use to for making connections by default. In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/entropy/blob/ae5ee52646c2c67ce713938548d67a722b73a294/flake.nix&quot;&gt;flake.nix&lt;/a&gt; file, I
setup the required environment variables:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-sh&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;PGDIR&lt;/span&gt;=$&lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;PWD&lt;/span&gt;/storage/postgres
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;PGDATA&lt;/span&gt;=$&lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;PGDIR&lt;/span&gt;/data
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;PGHOST&lt;/span&gt;=$&lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;PGDIR&lt;/span&gt;/run
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;PGDATABASE&lt;/span&gt;=entropy
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;DATABASE_URL&lt;/span&gt;=&lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;postgresql:///$PGDATABASE?host=$PGHOST&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;# &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;not required by postgres, but will be helpful&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With this, only header option left to set is &lt;code&gt;:engine&lt;/code&gt;, which I prefer to
configure globally for my &lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bitspook/entropy/96cc9c0485d972ed819996d61c3730cafb228660/sql-playground.org&quot;&gt;sql-playground.org&lt;/a&gt; since I usually have one database
for my personal projects. You can check this &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/entropy/commit/96cc9c0485d972ed819996d61c3730cafb228660&quot;&gt;commit on Entropy project&lt;/a&gt; for how I
have setup my sql-playground there. Following snippet on top of the
sql-playground.org does the trick:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-org&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;#+PROPERTY: header-args:sql  :engine postgres&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now any SQL snippets that we create can be executed against our development
database right within the org file. For example, pressing &lt;code&gt;C-c C-c&lt;/code&gt; in following
SQL block produces output shown below that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-org&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;#+name: events&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585; font-style: italic; text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;#+begin_src sql&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;SELECT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt; events.title,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;         events.slug,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;         start_time,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;         events.id,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;         events.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;source&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;         format(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&apos;%s mins&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;extract&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;(epoch &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt; (events.end_time - events.start_time))/60)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;FROM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585;&quot;&gt; events;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585; font-style: italic; text-decoration: overline;&quot;&gt;#+end_src&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;#+RESULTS: events&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #86b5e8;&quot;&gt;| title              | slug                 | start_time          | end_time            | source | format  |&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #86b5e8;&quot;&gt;|--------------------+----------------------+---------------------+---------------------+--------+---------|&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #86b5e8;&quot;&gt;| Lol bro what       | lol-rofl-lmao        | 2021-11-29 12:30:00 | 2021-11-29 13:30:00 | local  | 60 mins |&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color: #86b5e8;&quot;&gt;| Nested event title | nested-lol-rofl-lmao | 2021-10-29 12:30:00 | 2021-10-29 13:30:00 | local  | 60 mins |&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org0b6f9e8&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org0b6f9e8&quot;&gt;Utilizing LSP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org0b6f9e8&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Building SQL queries is my primary use-case, and org-mode configured so far
serves that purpose. But since I am putting all this effort in writing this blog
post anyway, I thought let&apos;s go a step further and try configuring LSP mode for
SQL snippets in my org file. To my surprise, it is possible. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lighttiger2505/sqls/&quot;&gt;SQLS&lt;/a&gt; provides an
LSP server for SQL files, which once configured can provide certain features
like auto-completing table and column names. I have created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/entropy/blob/96cc9c0485d972ed819996d61c3730cafb228660/.dir-locals.el&quot;&gt;.dir-locals&lt;/a&gt; file
for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/emacs/Directory-Variables.html&quot;&gt;adding directory local variables&lt;/a&gt; to configure LSP to connect to correct
database.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;((nil . ((eval (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; ()
                 (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt; lsp-sqls-connections `(((driver . &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;postgresql&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)
                                               (dataSourceName . ,(getenv &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;DATABASE_URL&quot;&lt;/span&gt;))))))))))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This snippet isn&apos;t actually the right way configuring directory local variables,
becuase it sets &lt;code&gt;lsp-sqls-connections&lt;/code&gt; globally. This is the result of me
time-boxing the task of evaluating &lt;code&gt;(getenv &quot;DATABASE_URL&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;, so I won&apos;t need to
duplicate my database configuration here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
LSP for org-mode also need to provide a file to which it can tangle source
blocks. So I added another snippet to top of my org file.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-org&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #858585; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;#+PROPERTY: header-args:sql  :tangle test.sql&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can now run &lt;code&gt;lsp-org&lt;/code&gt; in an SQL block, and 8/10 times it has lsp configured
properly. It isn&apos;t flawless though, but that is expected since &lt;a href=&quot;https://emacs-lsp.github.io/lsp-mode/manual-language-docs/lsp-org/#&quot;&gt;lsp support in
org-snippets&lt;/a&gt; is in alpha stage right now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also tried setting up lsp support in edit buffer for SQL statements (which you
get by pressing &lt;code&gt;C-c &apos;&lt;/code&gt; in org src blocks), but because of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/emacs-lsp/lsp-mode/issues/2525&quot;&gt;bug in lsp-mode&lt;/a&gt;,
that didn&apos;t work out too well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;org-babel-edit-prep:sql&lt;/span&gt; (babel-info)
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;setq-local&lt;/span&gt; buffer-file-name (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; babel-info caddr (alist-get &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:tangle&lt;/span&gt;)))
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;setq-local&lt;/span&gt; lsp-buffer-uri (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; babel-info caddr (alist-get &lt;span style=&quot;color: #7f7dca;&quot;&gt;:tangle&lt;/span&gt;) lsp--path-to-uri))
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;setq-local&lt;/span&gt; lsp-headerline-breadcrumb-enable nil)
  (lsp))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org1508ecd&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org1508ecd&quot;&gt;Problems with this setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org1508ecd&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are 2 main problems I face during my primary use-case.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Org tables don&apos;t work well if a column has a lot of data. e.g &lt;code&gt;description&lt;/code&gt;
of an &lt;code&gt;event&lt;/code&gt; messes up the table real bad. lsp-mode allow executing queries
which don&apos;t suffer from this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No LSP support in edit buffer is a major bummer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20220125T111233</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-02-03T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Using org-roam as a CRM</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/using-org-roam-as-a-crm/</link>
            <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DteN5uBV5ts&quot; title=&quot;TLDR video&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
org-roam is an Emacs application which makes efficiently capturing and finding
notes easy. It does so a good job at that, I decided to use it as a makeshift
personal CRM. With a few lines of Elisp, I get to:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Take notes about people and events. I usually capture their contact
information, important dates, how they made me feel during our interactions.
Documenting meetings and calls has proven to be very helpful on more than one
occasion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;SPC P f&lt;/code&gt; to very quickly find or create a person/event.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Link events and people to build a graph of relationships, which provide
context and help me remember our meetings vividly. It is valuable for me
because it save me from anxiety about forgetting people and things I discuss
with them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;SPC P i&lt;/code&gt; to insert link to a person/event in an org file (mostly my diary).
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have similar keybindings for taking (&lt;code&gt;SPC n f&lt;/code&gt;) and inserting notes (&lt;code&gt;SPC n
i&lt;/code&gt;), so it builds into a nice theme for easy-to-remember keybindings and
consistent UI.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org2292995&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org2292995&quot;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org2292995&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Elisp I use org-roam as a CRM, while keeping &quot;normal&quot; org-roam available for
taking notes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;defvar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #b6b635;&quot;&gt;spook--org-roam-crm-dir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;~/Documents/org/people&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #987654;&quot;&gt;&quot;Directory where org-roam notes related to people are kept.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)

(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;spook--with-org-roam-crm&lt;/span&gt; (func &lt;span style=&quot;color: #d65946;&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;rest&lt;/span&gt; args)
  &lt;span style=&quot;color: #987654;&quot;&gt;&quot;Evaluate FUNC with ARGS org-roam set for working as CRM.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;let*&lt;/span&gt; ((org-roam-directory spook--org-roam-crm-dir)
         (org-roam-db-location (concat org-roam-directory &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;/roam.db&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)))
    (apply func args)))

(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;spook-crm--db-sync&lt;/span&gt; ()
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;interactive&lt;/span&gt;)
  (spook--with-org-roam-crm #&apos;org-roam-db-sync))

(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;spook-crm--find-person&lt;/span&gt; ()
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;interactive&lt;/span&gt;)
  (spook--with-org-roam-crm #&apos;org-roam-node-find))

(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #1d9a79;&quot;&gt;spook-crm--insert-person&lt;/span&gt; ()
  (&lt;span style=&quot;color: #598bc1;&quot;&gt;interactive&lt;/span&gt;)
  (spook--with-org-roam-crm #&apos;org-roam-node-insert))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Setup keybindings for calling &lt;code&gt;spook-crm--find-person&lt;/code&gt; to quickly search for
(and/or add) a person or event, and &lt;code&gt;spook-crm--insert-person&lt;/code&gt; to add a link to
a person or event in any org-mode buffer. I frequently use it when adding
meeting notes and in my diary.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here&apos;s how I add the keybindings:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-elisp&quot;&gt;(spook-defkeymap
 &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;spook-people&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;C-c P&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
 &apos;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;f&quot;&lt;/span&gt; . spook-crm--find-person)
 &apos;(&lt;span style=&quot;color: #6aaf50;&quot;&gt;&quot;i&quot;&lt;/span&gt; . spook-crm--insert-person))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can find source of my very naive &lt;code&gt;spook-defkeymap&lt;/code&gt; macro in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/spookmax.d/blob/master/readme.org#helper-utilities&quot;&gt;Emacs
configuration&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to this, I assign the &lt;code&gt;spook-people&lt;/code&gt; keymap to my
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/meow-edit/meow/&quot;&gt;meow&lt;/a&gt; leader key, means I can press &lt;code&gt;SPC P f&lt;/code&gt; to find a person/event, and &lt;code&gt;SPC P
i&lt;/code&gt; to insert a link to a person/event.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org28b223d&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org28b223d&quot;&gt;Does it solve everything?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org28b223d&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No. But it is the quickest solution which achieves satisfactory result and free
me up to focus on other things. I feel org-roam itself to be over-engineered
sometimes, and there are a bunch of things I might like but don&apos;t need right
now. e.g
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More structured way of capturing specific kind of information. e.g contact
details. Structure of data kept in org files is upto me, which works for now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Searching by something which isn&apos;t title or tags. This is solved by doing grep
over&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visualize the people and events I participate in. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui&quot;&gt;org-roam-ui&lt;/a&gt; didn&apos;t work on
first shot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contacts/details on the go i.e a mobile app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Psychoanalyze people I meet; building, tracking and concluding experiments.
But it is perhaps too much to ask without making effort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org58dee24&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org58dee24&quot;&gt;Why am I sharing this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org58dee24&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To bounce ideas off of internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hoping someone will point me in a better direction if there is one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hoping someone will solve some problems with this snippet, build on it until I
come around to do it myself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To spread the cult of Emacs/org-mode (my precious-es)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To have some activity on my blog. It is too quiet here&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20220120T174152</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-01-22T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Find a functional programmer for your Javascript team</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/find-a-functional-programmer-for-your-javascript-team/</link>
            <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Written below are some opinions and rationalizations for them. I have come to
these opinions by interviewing and working with people for years. However
strongly I feel about them, they can still be wrong. If you have feedback for
these, please do contact me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/bitspook&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bitspook&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. All kind of feedback is
very much appreciated.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From &quot;Functional programmer&quot; I mean a programmer familiar with concepts of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Functional_programming&quot;&gt;functional programming&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A good teammate is someone:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Who takes care of themselves&lt;/b&gt;. They invest in themselves. They care
about their software as a craft, as something more than just cramming
a whole bunch of frameworks and libraries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Who take care of their teammates&lt;/b&gt;.

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They help their teammates grow, by mentoring and/or by serving as
an example&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are empathetic towards other developers. This is most visible
in kind of code a person writes. An empathetic developer writes
code for other people.

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They give preference to readability of code over
micro-optimizations that make them feel clever&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They write modular code with independent modules each of which do
one thing well. And are easily composed to build more complex
functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They write clean, predictable and intuitive APIs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
FP is steadily gaining popularity, but it is still not popular enough to
breach the talent pool I get to interview from. Familiarity with FP is a
very good indication that the person invest in themselves. And they do
that in a manner which goes beyond just increasing the number of
&quot;frameworks&quot; they have built a Todo App in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Developer empathy is surprisingly rare. In almost a decade of writing
code, I have met so few developers who really give a fuck that someone
else will also read their abomination. Most software is written in
vacuum. Familiarity with FP don&apos;t fix that magically.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However there is another factor at play here. Ironically, as a
side-effect of FP, code written in a functional manner is often a lot
more readable than its imperative and OOP equivalents (Impromptu quiz:
What&apos;s so ironic about this statement?). Not only is functional code
itself naturally declarative, an FP person is more likely to wtf when
they see unreadable code in PR reviews.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Basic principles of FP also make for great advice for inexperienced
developers. Good software architecture is hard to learn, it is a lot
harder to teach. You need a mind capable of holding large amounts of
complex code before the fancy design patterns even start making sense.
In comparison, &quot;pure functions + composition&quot; and you are good to go.
That is it. That is all you need to know to get started with writing
modular, testable, simple code; which is easy to write and easier to
maintain. As a mere side effect of avoiding side effects, you write
naturally &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SOLID&quot;&gt;SOLID&lt;/a&gt; (in spirit)
code.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
FP is not a silver bullet, but looking for functional programmers skew
the universe in your favor a little. You are a lot more likely to get
good people among functional programmers.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>find-a-functional-programmer-for-your-javascript-team</guid>
            <pubDate>2020-11-07T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Quick and Pretty Docs for Software Projects</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/quick-and-pretty-docs-for-software-projects/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I have practiced
&lt;a href=&quot;http://tom.preston-werner.com/2010/08/23/readme-driven-development.html&quot;&gt;Readme
Driven Development&lt;/a&gt; on a number of my projects with varying milage. I
have often found myself wishing for a few things:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;More structure&lt;/b&gt; When writing the documentation, and even more so
when reading it. A single markdown file starts getting out of hand
really quickly. On my presonal projects I go for org-mode, which keep
me satisfied. But when working on a professional gig, it don&apos;t feel
right to force other developers into org-mode/emacs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Prettiness&lt;/b&gt; Markdown is a quite reasonably readable format, but
there is always room for prettyness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Basically I wish for github-pages with more structure; so, a statically
generate site.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To minimize the added complexity to our dev setup, and since I am
already using docker to run dev-environments for almost all of my
projects, I chose to leverage it for building my readme as a local
&quot;service&quot;. i.e I chose to structure my documentation with filesystem,
and use docker to abstract the complexity of setting up the static site
generator.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have chosen hugo because of its simplicity. Its intuitive content
management means near-zero learning curve for my teammates to start
contributing documentation. I chose
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/matcornic/hugo-theme-learn&quot;&gt;hugo-theme-learn&lt;/a&gt;
because of its simplicity, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mermaidjs.github.io/&quot;&gt;mermaid.js&lt;/a&gt;
support for UML diagrams, and well, prettiness.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have a directory named &lt;code&gt;docs&lt;/code&gt; in our repository, with following
general structure:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;org22114f1&quot;&gt;
.
├── config.toml
├── content
└── Dockerfile
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Every markdown file in &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; directory adds to the generated
documentation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here is the Dockerfile I have used to create the docs container. It
downloads and sets up hugo with the theme in a single command without
anything other than docker installed on a developer&apos;s machine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;org1ca6211&quot;&gt;
FROM alpine:latest

WORKDIR /app

EXPOSE 80
ENV HOST=0.0.0.0

RUN apk update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; apk add hugo git

ENV HUGO_THEME_URL=&apos;https://github.com/matcornic/hugo-theme-learn&apos;
ENV HUGO_THEME_COMMIT=&apos;2.4.0&apos;

RUN mkdir -p /themes/current \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd /themes/current \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git init \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git remote add origin $HUGO_THEME_URL \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git fetch --depth 1 origin $HUGO_THEME_COMMIT \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git checkout FETCH_HEAD \
  &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd /app
RUN echo &quot;alias hugo=&apos;hugo --themesDir /themes --theme current&apos;&quot; &amp;gt; ~/.profile

COPY . /app

CMD hugo serve --port 3000 --bind=&apos;0.0.0.0&apos; --themesDir /themes --theme current
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When exposed on port &lt;code&gt;3000&lt;/code&gt;, it allows live-reloading of docs and search
in docs as well. It is possible to change the theme and theme version by
setting environment variables &lt;code&gt;HUGO_THEME_URL&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;HUGO_THEME_COMMIT&lt;/code&gt;
when building the docker image.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here is &lt;code&gt;config.toml&lt;/code&gt; file I&apos;ve used for my &lt;code&gt;docs&lt;/code&gt;, which allow me to
configure the hugo theme with above mentioned environment variable only:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;orgdebcf04&quot;&gt;
buildDrafts = true
title = &quot;My Project&quot;

# For search functionality
[outputs]
home = [ &quot;HTML&quot;, &quot;RSS&quot;, &quot;JSON&quot;]

[params]
  author = &quot;My team&quot;
  description = &quot;My project&apos;s cloud&quot;
&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>quick-and-pretty-docs-for-software-projects</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-08-28T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Helping others to help myself</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd-help-others-to-help-yourself/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
It is near impossible for me to get something done if I don&apos;t have 100%
peaked interest in it at &lt;b&gt;this&lt;/b&gt; very moment. Occasionally I can hyper
focus on things, but that hyper focus rarely finish things. Hyper focus
is like eating all the desert, leaving behind a plate full of broccoli.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have noticed however that most of the times when I have actually
finished something, I was, in my mind, helping someone else.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reviewing the judicious documentation of my life, that is my journal, I
can say it for near about 100% of the things that I actually finished.
The force behind crossing the finishing line was either accountability,
or my belief that someone else is relying on me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of my own &quot;side projects&quot; have ever seen a ray of light, but most
things I started for others were finished. Mostly that was
presentations, processes, and very personally tailored learning
materials.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reviewing my journal, I noticed a pattern developing over the course of
last year. Whenever I had an idea that I wanted to see done, I tried to
frame it in somebody else&apos; canvas. If I could do that, I shared the idea
with the person and got them involved as a partner. Chances of success
I&apos;ve observed were directly proportional to how much I care for the
person. Some of the things I started that I couldn&apos;t fit in to help
someone else are still in &quot;TODO&quot; state, despite the long and clear
road-maps I created for them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This discovery of transforming emotions that come easily to me, into
what I believe I severely lack has sown seeds of new hope. Perhaps I
will be able to replace my need of accountability to get things done
with this. I don&apos;t know if it is vain need of acknowledgment, or
goodness of heart, but it works.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have started taking actions to optimize this. I am as anti-social as
they come, and that, now I believe, is a problem to be solved if I want
to increase my happiness.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most of my activities with other people don&apos;t register to my brain as
something it should remember. My mind is often meeting people for first
time despite several previous encounters. That is the first thing I am
going to tackle. Concrete step I am taking for this, is to start using
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/monicahq/monica/&quot;&gt;Monica&lt;/a&gt; to keep track of my
social life. Next step would be to actually start making effort to
socialize. I suppose saying &quot;hello&quot; to my colleagues every morning could
be a good start.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>coming-to-terms-with-adhd-help-others-to-help-yourself</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-05-13T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Personal brands for software developers</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/personal-brands-for-software-developers/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/maximize-individual-growing-in-a-software-team-2-month-report/&quot;&gt;Reflecting on the progress&lt;/a&gt; we have made in our &lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/how-to-maximize-individual-growth-in-a-software-team/&quot;&gt;&quot;nurture a culture of individual
growth in a software team&quot; initiative&lt;/a&gt;, I realized there is much to gain from
candy wrapping our efforts. As per our plan, we&apos;ll be (and are) giving talks,
doing research, and writing itch-scratching code. Coming out of shadows and
presenting our efforts in a nice frame present many fold benefits.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My proposal is to invest energy in making our efforts more visible. To
focus this emotion on a more concrete goal, I have chosen
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-establishing-a-personal-brand&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;establishing-a-personal-brand&quot;&gt;Establishing a personal brand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-establishing-a-personal-brand&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I believe a person is a brand when (s)he is recognizable for the value
(s)he carry and can contribute, without fresh proof. Building a genuine
brand need genuine efforts. Efforts we are already making, and which can
gain a boost if we focus on this short term goal.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Doing so will also incentivize us to engage more in our chosen
activities. Our objective is personal growth of individuals involved in
our team(s), and I believe visibility of this growth is important for
its sustenance. The organization we work for, if it can see us growing
new skills, will be able to leverage them, hence contributing more to
our growth. Before I start fantasizing about all the good this can bring
to us, let&apos;s brainstorm on
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-how-can-we-establish-ourselves-as-brands&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-can-we-establish-ourselves-as-brands&quot;&gt;How can we establish ourselves as brands?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-how-can-we-establish-ourselves-as-brands&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Being a brand is a completely dependent value. Unlike our technical
skills, it is not something that can independently stand on its own. It
is almost entirely dependent on other people. People decide how valuable
you are as a brand. Thinking along these lines, I suppose the first
natural step turns out to be
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;b&gt;Building an online presence&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It boils down to having a home to showcase all the value we are
delivering right now. For starters, this can be a personal website which
can showcase the talks we are giving (since that is where we are
investing most of our time). Eventually, I imagine at least
incorporating all the steps we have chosen in our personal websites:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Talks/Presentations section&lt;/b&gt; for the talks we deliver. Perhaps we
can have &quot;Review&quot; section for the talks we attend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;A blog&lt;/b&gt; for sharing the discussions we have on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.trantorinc.com/&quot;&gt;Trantor forum&lt;/a&gt;, our research notes,
thoughts, opinions and just about anything. Blogs are great for
making noise and gather attention to yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;A Portfolio&lt;/b&gt; for showcasing the open source(?) work we do, as a
demonstration of our growing skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though there are platforms for creating and sharing content, I
firmly believe in having complete ownership of the content we generate.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once we have a platform where we are creating and sharing content, then
we can focus on
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Step 2&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;b&gt;Creating online visibility&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just creating content is not enough, there is too much noise all over
the internet to get noticed organically. Once we have the bare minimum
content creation pipeline, we can then focus on polishing things like
how it looks, SEO, automatic sharing across social media platforms,
analytic and data gathering, automatic updates for new content. I
wouldn&apos;t delve too deep into this right now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;b&gt;Building an offline presence&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another great first step along with aiming to build an online presence
is to build an offline presence. Local brands are very valuable,
probably more valuable than internet celebrities to local communities
and organizations employing us. Building offline presence require
engagement in local community, organizing and attending meetups,
hackathons etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We are in a unique position in this regard, the tech &quot;culture&quot; in our city
(Chandigarh) is yet barely blossoming. It used to be a &lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/dear-first-world-dev-have-a-look-at-your-nightmare/&quot;&gt;rather gloomy picture&lt;/a&gt;
around here, but I believe people have now started seeing the exploitation going
around in the tech scene of the city for what it is. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/find/events/?allMeetups=true&amp;amp;radius=10&amp;amp;userFreeform=Chandigarh%252C+India&amp;amp;mcId=z1018132&amp;amp;mcName=Chandigarh%252C+IN&amp;amp;eventFilter=mysugg&quot;&gt;More and more meetup groups&lt;/a&gt;
are blossoming for the good. Participating in these groups can be a great source
of content for our online presence. Before I start day-dreaming about how we can
hack for Chandigarh, I&apos;ll shut up about it : )
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For this, I suppose the next course of action is to open the sessions we
have been doing for public to attend. Trantor is one of the few
companies I have seen being quite open for organizing meetups in
Tricity, so this shouldn&apos;t be a problem from that front.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here is what I am imagining for our next goal is to attain our grand
objective of nurturing the culture of growth. Please do share your
ideas, opinions and thoughts. You are also always welcome to join us in
our endeavor.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>personal-brands-for-software-developers</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-04-01T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Maximize individual growing in a software team (2 month report)</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/maximize-individual-growing-in-a-software-team-2-month-report/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Couple months ago we started an &lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/how-to-maximize-individual-growth-in-a-software-team/&quot;&gt;initiative&lt;/a&gt; in our team here at &lt;a href=&quot;http://trantorinc.com/&quot;&gt;Trantor&lt;/a&gt; with the
focus on nurturing a culture which optimizes personal growth of an individual in
the team. I believe it is turning out to be quite successful. We decided we&apos;ll
focus on 4 things to achieve our goal:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-interactive-sessions-of-tools-technologies&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;interactive-sessions-of-tools-technologies&quot;&gt;Interactive sessions of tools/technologies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-interactive-sessions-of-tools-technologies&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is where we&apos;ve observed most success. We have had 4 sessions in
past 2 months (we do two-week sprints), with following primary topics:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up your ops game: Ansible and Vagrant &lt;i&gt;(delivered by &lt;b&gt;Charanjit Singh
(me)&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up your ops game: Docker and Docker Compose &lt;i&gt;(delivered by &lt;b&gt;Charanjit
Singh (me)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick and Dirty Kafka &lt;i&gt;(collaboratively delivered by &lt;b&gt;Charanjit Singh
(me), Rupinder Singh, Sheenam Narula, Krishan Saini&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting acquainted with Elasticsearch &lt;i&gt;(delivered by &lt;b&gt;Krishan Saini&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot;&gt;Collaboratively studying open source projects we use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We started off with &lt;code&gt;chai.js&lt;/code&gt;, but after probably spending only a few
minutes each, the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/13dko42FS9kcnpqnrjp9QCouQO0vZHDQ0tslID3BAQBs/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;google
doc&lt;/a&gt; we created for collaboratively creating notes didn&apos;t see much
action.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-being-active-in-trantor-forums&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;being-active-in-trantor-forums&quot;&gt;Being active in Trantor forums&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-being-active-in-trantor-forums&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Plan was to use Trantor Forums as a platform for proposing
(revolutionary) changes in our project. We started off with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.trantorinc.com/t/suggested-improvements-for-tdd-in-veriown-cloud-mutation-testing-and-running-tests-concurrently/74&quot;&gt;a
proposal to introduce mutation testing&lt;/a&gt; in our test-coverage reports,
but didn&apos;t move forward from that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I believe this is because we don&apos;t really spend as much time exploring
new/different things/subject-matters to be able to bring more of such
proposals. This problem is one of many that should fix itself if we are
successful in fostering a culture of self growth in the team.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-day-long-hackathons&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-long-hackathons&quot;&gt;Day long hackathons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-day-long-hackathons&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We are yet to realize this dream. Shiva proposed a neat little idea to
solve a problem faced by Trantor employees, but turned out an official
solution was already in the works and about to be released in couple
weeks (it didn&apos;t). I believe we should have just gone ahead and spend a
day to build what we wanted, just for the heck of it. That would have
been more fruitful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Above points are more than just steps to achieve our goal, I believe,
they are also metrics of our success. How much engagement each of these
get reflects on how much of a self-growth culture is prospering in the
team. I wonder if we can somehow quantize these per-person. If nothing
else, that&apos;ll create some cool graphs to gawk at.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>maximize-individual-growing-in-a-software-team-2-month-report</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-03-26T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>How to maximize individual growth in a software team?</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/how-to-maximize-individual-growth-in-a-software-team/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Working as a solo freelance developer, I used to have lofty ideas of how
a group of people can grow so much more together. I imagined how a mind
in the hive can grow at exponential rates. I made several attempts to
build communities striving for this, a few were successful to some
degree, most were not. Now working in a software development team at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://trantorinc.com/&quot;&gt;Trantor&lt;/a&gt;, I am revisiting these ideas.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I still believe that it&apos;s a worthwhile general direction to move in. In
this post, I am asking myself (and you) the question of &quot;how&quot;. How can
we maximize growth of an individual developer in a software team?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What do I mean by growth? Software is about so much more than just
writing code. It is also philosophy, psychology, mathematics, art and
policy making. Growth as a software developer encompass growth in all
these areas. Learning new tools and technologies is important, but so is
the conceptual knowledge of software development principles, foresight
about how decisions as trivial as naming a variable are going to impact
the future of our code, to perceiving the perception of reader of our
code, and also to make it elegant at many levels.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why focus on an individual&apos;s growth? I believe people are selfish by
design. We think first for ourselves, then for our family, then for our
closest community, and so on. Growing individuals help teams (and
companies) directly as well. A culture of growth attracts good
developers, more good developers are good for teams/companies than
mediocre/bad ones. Optimizing for an individual&apos;s growth seem like a
good idea to me. I think it adds significant positive value to everyone
involved in the process of writing software.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now then, how do we optimize for an individual&apos;s growth? I had a
discussion with the team here and we came up with some points that we
are going to try this
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlassian.com/agile/scrum/sprints&quot;&gt;sprint&lt;/a&gt;. Plan is to
buckle up and finish our committed work a day earlier than planned. Then
on the extra day we earn, we sit back together, analyze two weeks of our
code, share peer feedback, and dig into one or more of following
activities.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-interactive-sessions-of-new-tools-technologies&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;interactive-sessions-of-new-tools-technologies&quot;&gt;Interactive sessions of new tools/technologies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-interactive-sessions-of-new-tools-technologies&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Topmost and shiniest layer of a software developer&apos;s growth is knowledge
of new tools and technologies. Some of us explore more technologies than
others. It was proposed that team members present a tool or technology,
and give an interactive session of something they find cool. This can be
very helpful for knowledge sharing in a diverse team where different
people might have very different roles. For example, I am also handling
the dev-ops in our current project, using tools like
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ansible.com/&quot;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.terraform.io/&quot;&gt;Terraform&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/&quot;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://kubernetes.io/&quot;&gt;Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt;. But rest of the team has no
exposure to these tools. Me giving a session about these tools can be
very helpful for me, rest of the team, and the company. It is also very
much in alignment with my personal belief that every backend web
developer should be familiar with devops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I differ from the proposal by the team a bit though. I think it is cool
to just &quot;show and tell&quot; bi-weekly, giving an interactive session is a
good to have.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot;&gt;Collaboratively studying open source projects we use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-collaboratively-studying-open-source-projects-we-use&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another very good suggestion was reading the source code of an open
source project, and collaboratively make notes of the patterns that
codebase has used, things they did right, things they did wrong etc. At
the end of the sprint, we can all discuss the notes we took, if we can
take something and use in our projects etc. We have picked chai.js for
this sprint.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-put-forward-new-approaches-in-forums&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;put-forward-new-approaches-in-forums&quot;&gt;Put forward new approaches in forums&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-put-forward-new-approaches-in-forums&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Often times there are disagreements in team regarding approaches that
can be taken towards a problem. Or sometimes under the pressure of
delivery we pick one approach on another. If the taken approach is too
bad, a technical debt is created, but when it is &quot;good enough&quot;, we just
move on. We don&apos;t want to let this slide. We should reconsider these
small improvements, and keep incrementally improving and challenging our
current practices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We decided that we create posts on Trantor Forums for this, the team
should actively explore the alternative approaches, debate, reach a
consensus and implement the approach into our project. An example of
this is my proposal to bring &lt;a href=&quot;https://stryker-mutator.io/&quot;&gt;mutation
testing&lt;/a&gt; to our workflow. I raised it, and then higher priorities sent
it so deep into the ground that I myself forgot about it. A forum post
can be a healthy reminder in such cases, provide documented discussion
and bring activity in our forums as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-day-long-hackathons&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-long-hackathons&quot;&gt;Day long Hackathons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-day-long-hackathons&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another nice thing that came out of our discussion was that we can
utilize this extra day we earn ourselves as an internal team hackathon.
We can decide on any idea, regardless of its relevance for the
project/work, and the entire team spends a day hacking on it. Member
whose idea is selected can lead the team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think this can be a great way for team members to develop leadership
skills, learn new things, have some open-source portfolio, and most
importantly, feel that rush of starting a new project, and the bliss of
finishing one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Above are few things we are going to start doing starting this sprint.
Please put in comments below if you have opinions and/or suggestions!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>how-to-maximize-individual-growth-in-a-software-team</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-01-21T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Managing Chaos</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/managing-chaos-org-mode-as-a-todo-list/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I am thinking about doing a small series of posts on how I am managing
the chaos that I am trying to stop fighting. I hope the chaos of an ADHD
mind can be utilized rather than fought against. So far it has been
working out pretty great (for past ~8 months). This post is about how I
manage my ever exploding list of things I want to do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I believe one of the most important things is to externalize your
thoughts. Making it a habit to write them down is immensely helpful. So
many of my problems stopped being problems as I adopted writing things
down more and more. I have very small working memory. I forget often and
I forget most things. Mind is always thinking of new ideas, things to
do, things to tell people. The knowledge that I am going to forget the
thing I am thinking right now is a big source of anxiety. The burden of
remembering innumerable things and then failing to do so has a cognitive
toll of its own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I use org-mode as a lot of things; a TODO list is one of them. I am not
going to get into the details of using org-mode for a beginner, but I&apos;ll
share my flow of using org mode as a TODO list.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-capturing-things-to-do&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;capturing-things-to-do&quot;&gt;Capturing things to do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-capturing-things-to-do&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A very useful feature of org-mode is how easy it makes to &quot;capture&quot; TOOD
items. I use Emacs as my primary text editor; being a software
developer, most of my day time is spent in Emacs. Any time I think of
something I [want|have] to do, I capture it with 3 keystrokes and
usually immediately refile it under an appropriate heading. I keep 2
TODOs.org files, one for work and one for my personal life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my personal TODOs.org file, I keep headings categorizing the kind of
thing it is that I want to do; right now, they are =Study, Personal
Development, Habits, Projects, Reading List, In Basket&quot;.&quot;In Basket&quot;
heading keeps things that are quickly done in a day or few, and/or
cannot be categorized.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My work TODOs.org carries all my work related tasks, including Jira
issues, and general things I want/have to do when I am in the office. I
have a TODO item to integrate org-jira, but right now I am manually
copying Jira task IDs around like an imbecile.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is how my org-capture-templates variable looks like right now:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;example&quot; id=&quot;orgf815885&quot;&gt;
(setq
   org-capture-templates
   &apos;((&quot;d&quot; &quot;Diary Entry&quot; plain (file+datetree org-agenda-diary-file) &quot;\n&amp;lt;%&amp;lt;%I:%M %p&amp;gt;&amp;gt;\n%?\n&quot;)
     (&quot;f&quot; &quot;Feedback&quot; plain (file+datetree trantor-feedback-file) &quot;\n&amp;lt;%&amp;lt;%I:%M %p&amp;gt;&amp;gt;\n%?\n&quot;)
     (&quot;i&quot; &quot;Idea&quot; entry (file org-ideas-file) &quot;* %?\n%T&quot;)
     (&quot;t&quot; &quot;Todo&quot; entry (file+headline &quot;&quot; &quot;Todos&quot;) &quot;* TODO %?\n%U\n[[%F]]&quot;)
     (&quot;c&quot; &quot;Contact&quot; entry (file org-contacts-file) &quot;* %^{Name}\n:PROPERTIES:\n:COMPANY %^{Company}\n:PHONE: %^{Phone}\n:END:&quot;)))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-delegating-things-to-future&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;delegating-things-to-future&quot;&gt;Delegating things to future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-delegating-things-to-future&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode has a brilliant feature of scheduling tasks. It&apos;s rare for me
to schedule a task for &quot;today&quot;; I delegate stuff to future me. I can
capture and file things in any header, and then use org-mode&apos;s agenda
views to filter out things past-me assigned for today. I try to finish
the &quot;today&quot; tasks, and try to stay at peace when I fail to every day.
Org-mode also display a count of for how long I&apos;ve been missing to do a
certain task which is a handy reminder that I am falling short on my
commitments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-prioritizing-things&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;prioritizing-things&quot;&gt;Prioritizing things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-prioritizing-things&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not all tasks are made equal. Although I try my best to not let my
&quot;Today&quot; tasks list become too big, sometimes there is simply too much on
the plate. In that case, I define priorities for the most important
tasks, which are displayed at the top of the list in Day-agenda view.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-tagging-items&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tagging-items&quot;&gt;Tagging items&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-tagging-items&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I often tag my TODO items so I can easily filter them in the agenda view
when I want to find things I have to do in some particular context. I
often tag things by:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The person&apos;s name who I need to be with for doing something e.g when I
want to tell someone something&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Scrum sprint in which a task need to get done. For this I don&apos;t
tag each task but instead file my tasks in a &quot;Sprint X&quot; heading which
is tagged, and org-mode automatically inherit tags to all the
subheadings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place where I need to be at for doing something&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some other task specific metadata that I think can be helpful for
finding this task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-finding-things-to-do&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-things-to-do&quot;&gt;Finding things to do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-finding-things-to-do&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode allow me to write my todo items in any order in any manner; I
have several files where I write a lot of stuff, some of it is things to
do; most if it isn&apos;t. It&apos;s crucial to write things down for me, because
I know that I am going to forget it. Org-mode is immensely helpful in
finding things out when I need it. Org-files being just text files allow
me to just grep stuff; which is even more powerful with
helm-projectile-grep. But the killer feature for finding out what I am
supposed to be doing right now is org&apos;s agenda view. It allow me to
filter things by time and tags.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode require you to explicitly add files to a list of
&lt;code&gt;org-agenda-files&lt;/code&gt;. The agenda views only pick tasks from files in this
list. I have almost all my org files in my agenda list. It also provides
different views for the agenda; the one I am using most these days is
the &quot;Day-agenda&quot; view, and Week-agenda view when I want to plan things
ahead for the week.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On my mobile, I use orgzly android app. I am not too happy with it, but
it&apos;s the best I&apos;ve got for now. I&apos;ve it in my TODO list to create an app
focused on org-mode and TODO lists the way I want it to work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>managing-chaos-org-mode-as-a-todo-list</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-01-05T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Coming to terms with ADHD - Part 2</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd-part-2/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the important aspects of living with ADHD is getting overwhelmed
by thoughts. This is usually a major pain in the ass. When left
unchecked it usually leads to a lot of confusion very painfully visible
to people around you. This made most of my school life very tormenting.
Despite being an &quot;A&quot; student, I was always completely lost.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got better when I found computers. A book I found while sitting in
the wrong classroom turned things around for me. My thoughts got
channeled, things started becoming a lot more clearer when I wasn&apos;t
thinking of 10 random things at a time. I was still thinking of 10
things at a time, but it was now manageable; it was interesting. I
wasn&apos;t fighting the trains of thought anymore, I was enjoying the ride.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was alright while it was fun and games, but it became a problem
again when I entered software development as a profession. Now I had to
focus on things for extended duration of time; which usually was more
than my interest span. It was a struggle again. I got over that period
though; my current solution is to bring more accountability for my work,
for which right now, I am doing a day job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During my period of struggle, I did a lot of fight to stay focused. I
fought to not let distractions come in; I blocked sites, tried several
time-boxing techniques; most things worked, but for a small duration of
time. The fight did me more bad than good. Exploring things is what make
me happy, when I took that away from myself, the frustration that built
up as a result threw me in a pit of despair.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My recommendation to anyone finding [her|him]self in my shoes is to not
fight it all the time. Do whatever you feel like every once in a while.
It is very important to keep feeling happy. Trust yourself that you&apos;ll
manage to get important things done in time. However, you need to
build/earn this trust. Read my
&lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; for some tips on how I do it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When you find something you feel passionate about, the multiple trains
of thought kinda all go in the same direction. They&apos;re all interesting,
and you want to ride them all. If you fight to ride one (or few) of
them, you&apos;re gonna give yourself a hard time. Instinct to hop on each
one of them until another one is more interesting isn&apos;t all that evil.
I&apos;ll be writing more posts on how I do that (i.e tools and techniques I
use), I don&apos;t have time right now, and am losing interest in writing
this post. Try to trust yourself that you&apos;ll come back to what you&apos;re
pausing, have means that allow you to hop b/w different things, and try
to be at peace with the fact that this is simply how you operate. It
might look chaotic to others, you&apos;ll still not be &quot;normal&quot;, but you&apos;ll
be a whole lot happy, and hopefully satisfied.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my current setup I have tens of different things I am time-sharing
on, and am still delivering satisfactory value in my work. It is
certainly possible for you to not fight tooth and nail with your way of
thinking and have a satisfactory career (at least in Software
Development).
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>coming-to-terms-with-adhd-part-2</guid>
            <pubDate>2019-01-03T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Coming to terms with ADHD</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
After my recent subscription to &lt;a href=&quot;http://reddit.com/r/adhd&quot;&gt;/r/adhd&lt;/a&gt;, I
realized how important it can be to share experiences. Even when it is
something very personal and seem unlikely that anyone can relate to it,
it can be quite helpful for someone who thinks she&apos;s alone with her
struggles. A while back I deleted most of my old blog posts feeling
embarrassed of their suspected cringeworthiness. Now I think it was a
mistake. I am thinking about resurrecting them from archive.org.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this post I want to talk about how I came to the single instance of
my life when I am not completely lost in self-pity for being too lazy
and undisciplined. Perhaps it was this self-loathing that slowly turned
to depression, and a bad event finally pushed me into the hole that I
believe I am out of now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started my research on ADHD when my doctor pointed I might have it. At
that time I was in limbo of a special kind. I was quite used to the
struggle of making myself do work that wasn&apos;t interesting anymore. I was
also used to the periods of time when I was simply incapable of doing
any work. But what made me go to the doctor was a relatively longer
period of true nothingness. Nothing would excite me, no matter what I
tried. The chaos inside my head got so out of control I was often
talking to myself in an attempt to materialize the voices and solidify
the line of thought so I could deal with them one at a time. Nothing
worked. I would often contemplate suicide because my mind just wouldn&apos;t
shut up about how pathetic I was. It was then I decided to consult help
from a professional.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have not reached a solution, perhaps there is no solution that solves
everything. But here is a list of things that has made a huge impact in
helping me come to terms with my ADHD.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-keep-a-daily-journal&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-a-daily-journal&quot;&gt;Keep a daily journal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-keep-a-daily-journal&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Try to know yourself. Understanding why you are thinking what you are
thinking can be immensely helpful. It will help you figure out the flaws
in your thinking, and how to make up for them. For example, a pat
routine has saved me so many times once I started noticing that how
often in a single I would forget my wallet or my phone or keys. Small
things like this add up to make life miserable, and often go unnoticed
in the storms of thoughts we face every day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So much of the overwhelmingness can just be let gone by writing it down.
Try to be your own therapist, try to witness yourself. Not to
participate, or engage, just analyze. It can be quite an exhausting
thing to do, but I&apos;ve found it to be more helpful than meditation. When
I write in my diary, I find myself to be much more in control of life
the next day. It&apos;ll also help you figure out which of your ideas are
actually work-able and which are just fluff that need to go in trash
can.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-write-stuff-down&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;write-stuff-down&quot;&gt;Write stuff down&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-write-stuff-down&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You don&apos;t need to wait for the night to fall before you can write in
your diary. Writing often during the day is quite helpful too. Write
anything and everything down. Is it something you want to do but can&apos;t
right now? Create a todo entry. Just had a brilliant new idea? Capture
it. Invest in a tool that can help you capture your thoughts quickly.
Make this process a part of your life. I use Emacs&apos; Org mode which has a
brilliant capture system, and I am very happy with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-delegate-to-your-future-self&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;delegate-to-your-future-self&quot;&gt;Delegate to your future self&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-delegate-to-your-future-self&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You don&apos;t need to do all the hundred things you have thought of, today
itself. Delegate them to your future self. I don&apos;t remember where I
learned it, but it is very helpful to treat your future self as a
different person, and just assign tasks to him that you don&apos;t have time
to work on right now. You can schedule stuff you capture right away, or
you can have a weekly review when you sort everything you captured in
the week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-review-weekly&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;review-weekly&quot;&gt;Review weekly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-review-weekly&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is very important to review everything you capture on regular
intervals. It&apos;ll give you confidence regarding your system, you could
trust yourself more. When you can start trusting your future self,
things becomes a lot very easier. You also become better at estimating
stuff, so the commitments you give to other people bring you that much
less anxiety.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-respect-the-decisions-made-by-your-past-self&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;respect-the-decisions-made-by-your-past-self&quot;&gt;Respect the decisions made by your past self&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-respect-the-decisions-made-by-your-past-self&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Only way you can trust your future self to finish what&apos;s assigned to him
is if you respect the decisions made by your past self. You don&apos;t have
to beat yourself up too much about it either. Understand that it&apos;s not
easy to estimate things. If we could predict things very reliably, we
could open shops as psychics. Try to achieve &quot;eventual consistency&quot;. Not
everything is equally important. Make sure that if something has been
assigned to you, it eventually gets completed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-find-something-you-can-attach-meaning-to&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;find-something-you-can-attach-meaning-to&quot;&gt;Find something you can attach meaning to&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-find-something-you-can-attach-meaning-to&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&apos;s helpful to have something to call home. A principle that you
wouldn&apos;t compromise with. I have chosen to attach meaning to the quality
of the work I do. That&apos;s where I try to find solace. That&apos;s what I use
to bring myself to peace, when I can&apos;t control the mess in some parts of
my life. It might be one of the cardinal sins, but this kind of pride
helps build confidence to face life.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>coming-to-terms-with-adhd</guid>
            <pubDate>2018-12-15T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Relationships</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/relationships/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Romantic relationships are such amazing things. I have had moments in my
life when I considered myself to have a certain level of control on my
mind; in terms of that I can witness myself as an outsider. The
introspection, the self awareness that make me think that, very rarely
accompany me when I am in a relationship. It seem to have a liking to
solitude.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking at it from far really brings the picture of a &quot;family man&quot; home.
A lone man seem to have the ability to accomplish much more than a man
bound to another person. It takes a lot of energy just to be with
someone. It has been 220 days since I last wrote a diary entry; my
primary medium of introspection. I&apos;ve been so lost in the everyday
churn, I chose not to give time to my self. Not that I am complaining;
I&apos;ve been happily lost.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For however many gifts solitude brings, the pain of loneliness is not
something to fool around with. Perhaps it is the pain itself that make
great people do great things, but it did make me realize the meaning of
crippling in crippling depression. Perhaps this is one of the reasons
successful people credit half their success to their partners. It must
be possible to have partners that can assist each other unlock their
potentials. Can you be so alone with someone? I wonder if it is a matter
of finding someone right, or making yourself right for the one you are
with. I am going to put all my eggs in the latter basket. We&apos;ll see how
this gamble plays out.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>relationships</guid>
            <pubDate>2018-11-10T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>That sounds fun!</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/that-sounds-fun/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I got an opportunity to introspect in a conversation with a client when
he questioned my use of the word &quot;fun&quot;. What do I mean when I say
something is fun? I am not entirely sure. May be when I see something
that excites me a little. People have very different interpretations of
fun. For me it is usually applying creativity to build something.
Activities the involve combination of these two, make me feel most
satisfied. Balance is very important.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But what do I really mean when I say something is fun? I almost never
know if it is going to be fulfilling at the time of making this
declaration. So how do I reach the point where I can say that X is going
to be fun?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It might be an opportunity to learn something new. The unknown scares me. It&apos;s a
thrill and possibly vain feeling of growth. I have a long list of things I want
to learn/master. When my mind sees an opportunity to check a box off of that
list, it gets excited.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It might as well be pure vanity. Vanity plays important part in my mind. When my
subconscious thinks keeping appearances is important, seeing a geeky-sounding
statement just automatically make it blabber &quot;that sounds fun&quot;. Although I try
to keep my narcissism in check, occasional slips are a thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another thing that I think I consider fun is &quot;fixing&quot; something. It is quite
possible to mark me as a control freak; although I won&apos;t voluntarily accept the
label. I do however occasionally attain rather strong opinions about how certain
things shall be. When I see an opportunity to &quot;fix&quot; something to my definition
of right, that is a strong motivational force. However unreliable it might be,
working with motivation is fun.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>that-sounds-fun</guid>
            <pubDate>2018-09-11T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Some random thoughts</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/some-random-thoughts/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Life can be so overwhelming sometimes. Sometime I wonder how people go
on about living without asking questions. Or may be they do ask
questions but get satisfied by the answers world has to offer. So much
in the world goes around these questions after all. Religions and
nations for example. Who&apos;d believe in such farcicality if there were
proper answers. Purposelessness is painful. So is loneliness. I seem to
have plenty of both of them. And then there is paranoia and laziness.
Latter two are mostly the reasons for former two. Inability to trust
anyone and jumping to the worst keep me away from most people. Laziness
keep me from diving into anything engaging enough to forget that it&apos;s
all meaningless.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Laziness now, may be I can do something about it. I have been practicing
with rituals as of late. They work well 60% of the time, today however I
failed them drastically. May be tomorrow will be a stronger day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think there is another reason for laziness as well. The work. It gets
so stupid some times. Well, most of the times it is so damn fucking
stupid. It is no fun writing forms all day long. But I need money right
now, I need a lot more than this job provides, but to start generating
more money, I need more skills. Whether I go for a better paying job or
for my own business, both need time. We&apos;re building a house, so the need
for money is immediate. I have to stick with this job for long enough to
finish the house and have some savings to give myself some period to lay
back and learn new skills, and bootstrap a business.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to what business I&apos;ll do, I am thinking to have a take on content
publishing and app building combo. I&apos;ll build apps that do something,
and I&apos;ll start a blog for each app. Apps will have premium versions via
in-app purchases, and blogs will have ads. For this I plan to first
study the competition, for which I&apos;ll build an Intenet-wide crawler to
fetch and keep information about everything that goes on in public
Internet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another plan I have is to start an app and business for farming.
Bio-farming and whatnot. I like to farm and I like Punjab. I&apos;ll like to
do something for the land.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have to get on speed with studying Haskell. I intend to start building
the Internet scanner in Haskell after I finish the 2 Haskell courses I
plan to do. After that I&apos;ll do a series of blogs for algorithms, apps,
games and Mathematics. Perhaps on farming and immigration out of India
as well. Basically everything that I want to do, I&apos;ll turn it into a
blog.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sometime I want to just hit the road and live a traveler&apos;s life. I know
it sound obscene for I hate to travel, but constant change keep me from
falling into limbo, thinking how utterly meaningless everything is. I
guess that&apos;s how people go about their lives. There are so many problems
everyone have to deal with, there is no time or energy left to indulge
in this bullshit. Specially given that there is much more juicy bullshit
for most to indulge in; love, family, power, politics, nationality, and
the one bullshit to rule them all, religion.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>some-random-thoughts</guid>
            <pubDate>2016-09-30T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Losing to Nothingness</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/losing-to-nothingness/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Couple weeks back I executed my plan to return to Chandigarh. The plan
was to take a break from work and relax for a bit, teach myself some new
skills. The real life butted in and I haven&apos;t started the phase 2 yet,
but the change was big and I am feeling the affects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I strive to build bubbles of order in midst of chaos that is life, but
what&apos;s still a mystery to me is why change give me a high. Bigger the
change higher the crest. In my final days in Bangalore I was almost at
the deepest of the limbo; shifting almost brought me back on track. The
crest is usually temporary, I am certain same is the case this time as
well. Usually I meet equally deep troughs. Just thinking of it give me
the chills.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However, something is different this time. I am ought to be on a high,
yet I am feeling the pull of a trough. It feels even weirder than it
sounds. I feel very peaceful, yet there is this unanswerable
restlessness. I feel an insatiable hunger at all times, as if there is a
big void in middle my stomach which is pulling my abdomen inside. The
peace is such I could die right now and not have a single regret, not a
thing I want to do more or different. Same time there is this alarm that
just keep ringing for all the things I have left undone. All the
promises to be fulfilled.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Duality yet has some constants, some patterns are emerging. I am living
on 6th floor these days. It provide quite a demi-god view of the
neighborhood; looking at automated people, day in and day out. It raise
so many questions; so much of my own life is just acting on impulses. An
unclear realization is rendering so much of life to nothingness. It&apos;s
like I&apos;ve reached a conclusion, I don&apos;t know to what. I don&apos;t know what
it is. A cluster of thoughts I can&apos;t tell apart. Perhaps this is how it
feel like when entering the actual madness.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I fear most is that I might be concluding life. It is becoming
harder and harder to convince myself to live for gathering things. I&apos;ve
always had a loose grip on reality, now I am fighting to hang on to
however little I have left. Paranoia and delusions are coming back.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It feels like a storm is approaching, yet it&apos;s so calm. I am dreadfully
afraid, but something in me is welcoming it. May be this is the eye of
the storm I am in. It sure feel like somewhere there&apos;s a clock, ticking.
There is so much going on in my silly little head, and there is this
emptiness sucking me in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I fear I might be losing to this nothingness. I am scared the peace is
temporary, but the chaos is just getting started.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>losing-to-nothingness</guid>
            <pubDate>2016-08-23T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>My overplanning nature and how it help me</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/my-overplanning-nature-and-how-it-help-me/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Although I try my best to not fall in the conformist&apos;s trap, there is
always a force lurking right beneath the conscious which want me to fit
in. I remember my obsession for control and planning from quite early
childhood. It used to be a major source of frustration; not that I was
obsessive about planning things, but that everyone else was not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time I figured it was me who was the odd one; so I subconsciously
started suppressing this (over?)planning nature of mine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And supressed it was, until I started writing software. I found that
properly planning things out before writing the software was immensely
helpful. Writing every unique use case, all the nuances, things to do
and things not to do; all of them helped when writing actual code.
Proper planning would make writing software so much more smoother.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But it didn&apos;t put me on the path to undo the supression I had done for
years; it merely put a doubt. I was still in doubt if I was the odd one
here, may be I am just wasting time writing every detail down up front.
May be it helped me only because it would satisfy my over planning
nature which would then let me code in peace. So I wouldn&apos;t do it every
time. Even though the results were obvious as daylight, the doubt would
have me not write specs in so many cases. Laziness didn&apos;t help either;
it&apos;s far more fun to just start writing code then it is to write specs.
As a matter of fact, thinking and writing all the small details become
painful on times.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To my great surprise, all it took was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20161117174710/http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000036.html&quot;&gt;single blog post&lt;/a&gt; (well, actually 5 blog
posts from a single series) to pull this doubt out of me, to take away all the
confusion and bring the clarity that I knew the right thing to do all along.
There are still things to learn, &quot;where to draw the line?&quot; for instance. But
that is the fun part. Hard part will be to write specs for every software I
write, defeating the laziness; which unfortunatley has become a big part of me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wish more programmers would blog about thier learnings and experiences
and struggles. That blog post I linked about was written in 2000, and it
came to my attention following another post on the same blog which
someone linked in a chat group. May be I am the odd one here; I don&apos;t
exactly have a team of developers working together, learning together.
But I am certain I am not alone. I hope my posts help someone realise
they&apos;re not alone if they have struggles similar as mine.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>my-overplanning-nature-and-how-it-help-me</guid>
            <pubDate>2016-06-23T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Debt of my rebellion</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/debt-of-my-rebellion/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Most of my school life I was very confused, depressed perhaps. I was a &quot;good
boy&quot;, as they call those traumatized, obedient kids. Confusion started turning
into frustration by the end of my 10th standard. It was the &quot;board&quot; class.
Nonsensical pressure, corporal punishment and stupid as fuck rules had started
turning my depression into anger. So much pressure was put on by that &lt;a href=&quot;https://sasacademy.com&quot;&gt;shithole
of a school&lt;/a&gt; that one of my classmates had a mental breakdown. A guy went
complete nuts. That was the final nail in the coffin.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I felt like it was my turn next. So I rebelled. Against everything that
didn&apos;t make sense to me. Unfortunate for me, one of the foes in my
rebellion was Mathematics. The dull, complex subject whose applications
I couldn&apos;t understand. My teachers failed to convince me it was ever
going to have a practical application at all. All they could come up
with was &quot;competitive exams need it&quot;. But that won&apos;t make the cut.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a year of being a total brat, I finally pushed my parents to sell
a cow and buy me a computer. Computers always fascinated me, even though
I had used Computers only for a total of 10-12 hours max (occasional
15-20 minutes sittings in IT lab). I taught myself Python from the
ebooks I would download on my rare visits to cyber-cafe in nearest city.
It was a revelation. I didn&apos;t need those stupid teachers anymore; there
was no need to go through all the frustration, frowned looks and grudges
(which often lead to physical punishment) from the teachers. I could
teach myself better, faster. Unfortunate side effect of this
realization: I didn&apos;t need a shiny college.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Not going to college however was not an option. My parents were giving me enough
pain already for using computer too much (despite the fact that I was good at
school AND helped at home and farm as well). So I went for admission in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dgc.edu.in/&quot;&gt;one of
those piece of shit colleges which let anyone in for a big some of money&lt;/a&gt;.
Another story for another day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I could teach myself everything I needed. I was perhaps right about
that. But there was nobody to tell me what to learn. By the time I got
Internet I was making enough side money building software to pay for my
ever growing list of re-appears. I didn&apos;t see no math used anywhere.
When I got Internet, I started making websites. Again, no math to be
seen anywhere. The college was as shitty as they get. They never really
taught any of the syllabus (DS, algorithms etc). So I ignored them as
mumbo-jumbo schools put in their books to make money. I was making more
money than most lecturers in that college, I didn&apos;t care.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In 2014 I graduated, and went for full time freelancing. It took me some
time till I reached my limit; when I felt brute forcing my way through
problems wasn&apos;t really efficient. It was boring. It was becoming more
and more obvious that I was plateauing. I started realizing that there
are better ways to do things, and so many of them have already been
discovered.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But now the playtime was over. I was no longer in college, I had to
support myself; and my family (they&apos;re not very good financially). So I
continued freelancing. It was paying much more than most approaching
companies were offering, clients were happy, so what the hell, I
thought. I planned to save some amount in bank, and then I was to take
few months off to go back to square one and learn CS theory and
Mathemetics. I reached there 3 months ago. But then life did what it
always do. 2 big expenses came up and cleared most of my savings. So I
continued with freelancing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But I guess it&apos;s about time I put my original plan in action. I have
started getting the good ol&apos; limbo feeling again. I used to think it was
my indiscipline which make me feel like shit. But now I think it isn&apos;t.
Most of the time I have to discipline myself to get away from the
computer. When I start needing to force myself to code, it&apos;s because
something somewhere is wrong. I think I&apos;ve hit another plateau (this
realization (that it&apos;s not indiscipline that put me in limbo) itself was
a load off my chest, but a story for another time).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have savings to last for only a couple months without work, but I
guess that&apos;ll have to do. It&apos;s funny deja-vu situation actually. I was
in similar situation when I headed for Bangalore. Back to square one I
guess. I think it&apos;s time to put a pause on freelancing, and pay the debt
of my rebellion.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>debt-of-my-rebellion</guid>
            <pubDate>2016-06-11T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Reality</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/reality/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
It is one of those rare times I decide to write a blog post without life
taking a huge shit on me. Or am I just projecting success for attracting
success? Guess bitches. Hope you&apos;re all living in reality and not losing
yourself in your imaginary fantasy world. Guess what? You&apos;re not living
in reality. There is no reality to live in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reality like God can not be seen, observed, or proven. Even those
fucking scientists giving hardcore &quot;laws&quot; of physics say there can be
other realities where our laws of physics don&apos;t apply. Hell they don&apos;t
apply everywhere in our own dimension (hint: Quantum of Solace was a
douchie movie ).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even if there is a &lt;b&gt;reality&lt;/b&gt; (emphasis not mine, don&apos;t know who did it)
to observe and live in, human mind (and eyes) are certainly out of their
league to observe it for what it is. Fuck we can&apos;t even understand what
the person in front of us is saying, we only understand what we hear.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-personal-realities&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;personal-realities&quot;&gt;Personal Realities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-personal-realities&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We all live in our own versions of personal realities, sort of like
bubbles all our lives and thoughts and even imaginations are trapped in.
Reality is that we can&apos;t know the reality. We&apos;ll always live in one
bubble or other. Best you can do is choose your bubble, and switch from
time to time. More bubbles you observe, better your chances are to not
get locked in one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Everyone is living in a bubble. Some are aware of it, most are not.
People see through lenses they wear over time. With time the lenses get
different shades, get thicker and thicker. At the end of it, your whole
life is a fucking opinion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People in fact, live in more than one bubbles. Bubble of &quot;ethics&quot; given
by your parents, religion and society, the &quot;professional&quot; bubble most
get caught in when they taste the thing they think is success for first
time (this one is easiest to detect, look around, ask people why they&apos;re
doing what they&apos;re doing), the &quot;love&quot; bubble you get trapped in from
movies and fairy tales, and many more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-probabilities&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;probabilities&quot;&gt;Probabilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-probabilities&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You have no control over your life. Life is not yours to control, it is
not real. Everyone around you is carrying their own reality, overlapping
and interfering with yours. Best chance you&apos;ve got is a chance. If you
want to make something happen, you can only increase its probability of
happening. Doesn&apos;t mean you should lose hope and go home (if you thought
that, you probably should give up and go home), if you wanna make
something happen, you gotta keep increasing the probability of its
occurrence until the probability is 1. Or spend your 80 years of misery
trying to do so.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-people&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;people&quot;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-people&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I see people around, I try to think of them as different realities.
Every single one of them is living in their own reality. You&apos;d be
surprised to find out how easy it is to manipulate someone (read bend
people to your will) once you can empathise with their reality.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The only way to observe a (wo)man&apos;s reality is to observe it from the
outside. Like I said, it is not the reality, it is a bubble. Most people
are hardcoded in their bubbles. Bubbles are like games (or is it my
bubble kicking in?), bubbles have rules too. Like every game has its own
rules of physics, bubbles have their own rules. Even if you can&apos;t live
another person&apos;s bubble, you can read their rules. If you can do it well
enough, you can tell exactly what other person is thinking and what he&apos;s
going to do in next 5 minutes, or 5 years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You know the couples which live together (happily) can communicate
without talking, can tell what&apos;s up in other person&apos;s mind. My theory is
that by being close for long enough time, their bubbles start
overlapping. Like Van diagrams, there is that area in which they think
exactly same things. They don&apos;t need words anymore to communicate,
because they know what other person is feeling (and hence thinking,
wanting to say or do or whatever, old people creep me out).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-reading-the-bubbles&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;reading-the-bubbles&quot;&gt;Reading the bubbles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-reading-the-bubbles&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&apos;s not confined to couples, neither you need to live with someone for
a lifetime to be able to observe their bubbles. It is a skill, an art
perhaps. Some people are damn good at it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is easy to observe others&apos; bubbles. The basic and most difficult
requirement is already met. You are already outside the bubble, now all
you have to do is study it from inside without entering it. Easy, huh?
Look for the reflections. Make them talk, don&apos;t listen to what they say,
look for the patterns. Patterns tell you the rules of their worlds. Try
to imagine how it is to see through those eyes. That is a whole
different world that person is seeing, it is, fascinating to say the
least. (Fuck I just told you my mind reading trick, I think I should
stop blogging)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You need the right set of tools to think in. Like in software it&apos;s all
about the right abstractions. This whole &quot;bubbles&quot; thing is just that, a
tool to think in. Ultimate goal is to be able to look at the world
exactly as someone else, find out the patterns, and hence the rules. And
of course ultimately play the rules for fun and profit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Or you can take the script-kiddie way and jump to finding rules,
skipping the hardest first part. But that route involves lot of trial
and error, failure may result in bitter relations for life. Plus, you
lose all the scope for creativity and flexibility when you take the
latter way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-business&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;business&quot;&gt;Business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-business&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These &quot;personal realities&quot; can (and are) actually be used for
manipulating people to do what you want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People live in many bubbles; many people live in similar bubbles.
Bubbles have rules, similar bubbles have similar rules. The textbook
tricks salespeople do lie in that domain. The whole range of tricks an
Indian sales person use everyday, won&apos;t work if he move shop to US. The
whole mutual reality his customers live in just changed. (There are of
course certain universal rules which work with almost all humans. How
many years of evolution was it again?)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That&apos;s rudimentary though. &lt;b&gt;Personal realities&lt;/b&gt; can actually be created.
You are a sales guy, imagine if you could create a world where people
think they need your towels although they don&apos;t ever bath or wash their
hands (nasty people, I like &apos;em already). You can do that for one person
at a time, or N people at a time where N is the number of people who
watch the news you control, or (be less dramatic) people who watch your
advertisements. Again there are different levels of sophistication with
which this can be done. More you know about someone (that&apos;s why you make
&apos;em talk), their habits etc, easier it is to manipulate and fabricate
entirely new realities for them. Imagine how fun the life would be if
you were Facebook or Google. I&apos;ve heard Facebook knows even when and how
many times you go to poop everyday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You didn&apos;t think I was all evil trying to teach you how to manipulate
people as I do, did you? Well that&apos;s certainly a perk, but the goal is
to be able to identify the realities from induced realities, and
fabricated realities (there&apos;s a difference). See I was trying to save
you all this time, you silly! I am no evil! Come on now jump in my van
already, I have tinfoil hats too.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ll probably talk about this in depth later some time, about the
different tools I&apos;ve figured people using, some unused ones I&apos;ve
discovered through experimentation, and other delusional shit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I could write a book about it, but I gotta go watch that movie everyone
on Reddit has started talking about all of a sudden.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>reality</guid>
            <pubDate>2015-09-12T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Please Don’t Fuck Up the Hackathons</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/please-don-t-fuck-up-the-hackathons/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I came to Bangalore few months back attracted by its humming tech
culture, lots of meetups and even more so, hackathons. I work as a
freelancer, I have no other purpose here. And I was not disappointed
until recently. Honestly, I don&apos;t even know what definition of word
&quot;hackathon&quot; has for Bangalore. I&apos;d quote Paul Graham here, &quot;the city
sends you a message&quot;. Bangalore certainly doesn&apos;t give a message of
freedom or even innovation, the message I heard when I came here was
that of &quot;milk whatever you can&quot;. People running after money. End of
story. But it still has a (relatively) pretty healthy tech-culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I believe hackathons are meant for open innovation. An event where
people go and build something, anything that come to their mind. I don&apos;t
mind themes. But giving me a &quot;problem statement&quot; to work on is
ridiculous. It is no more a hackathon when you want everyone to climb
the same tree to &quot;win&quot;. I don&apos;t go to hackathons for &quot;winning&quot; them. I
don&apos;t know what kind of geek does that. Hackathons are for hackers, for
having fun, for our happiness, for teasing the brain muscles which we
can&apos;t utilise in our day jobs. The word &quot;hack&quot; in hackathon means
innovation. Anything useful that comes out of a hackathon is a
by-product, never the primary goal. It&apos;s sort of paradoxical.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Beauty of a hackathon is that there is no stressful competition. There
is nothing to compare against, which lead to a very healthy kind of
competition (which might not even be called competition). I&apos;d suggest to
read this if you&apos;d like to better understand the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20151124075842/https://medium.com/@pedramkeyani/hacking-company-culture-1daa3be1d769&quot;&gt;spirit
of a hackathon&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The one major piece of crap that I think is on the way to ruin
hackathons in Bangalore (at least) is this company called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20151124075842/http://www.venturesity.com/&quot;&gt;Venturesity&lt;/a&gt;.
Their main idea is to organize hackathons for companies so they can hire
the winners (or whomever, may be). But the way they organize the event
is what bothers me. They give 2-3 problem statements and ask people to
solve them. Recently they&apos;ve also made it compulsory to have a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20151124075842/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software%5Fdesign%5Fdocument&quot;&gt;&quot;design
document&quot;&lt;/a&gt; for the problem statement they send one day before the
event.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If some company actually want to hire some good hackers, then this
(venturesity) monkey-business is definitely not what they should be
doing. You kill the spirit of the hackathon, reduce it to a mere race
where everyone is climbing the same tree, and then you judge them to
&quot;hire&quot; them? Is this the best Bangalore&apos;s hackers could come up with?
There are so many things you could innovate, and you chose the same
retarded system of master race that&apos;s ruining education in our country.
I don&apos;t personally know the people behind venturesity, but I can bet
there is some academic from some big-shot school pulling the strings.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Interviews are not perfect, may be not even good, I agree with you
there. But this ventursity hackathon hiring shit is a step backward. It
is a night long exam which is anything but fun. When I look at this
situation, I don&apos;t see Venturesity solving a problem, they are milking
an opportunity which is not theirs to milk (you are not fucking hackers,
stay away from hackathons). They are in fact creating a problem of their
own. Soon people will follow the suit and in worst case Indian
hackathons will all be this bullshit Venturesity does. World is full of
monkeys you see. We all know how everything gets an Indian version, and
I don&apos;t want this to be Indian version of hackathons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the end, if there&apos;s someone from ventursity reading this or if
someone can take this message to them, I&apos;d like to personally say
something. My problem is not with companies using this strategy for
hiring, or with Venturesity doing business. My problem is with you
calling it a hackathon. Please stop calling your events hackathons.
Because they are fucking not. Call them hire-e-thons or
night-long-exams-because-we-couldnt-innovate or whatever, but please
don&apos;t call them hackathons. It gives a very wrong message to the
community about what a hackathon is.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;YOU ARE FUCKING RUINING HACKATHONS FOR EVERYONE.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once again with due respect, please don&apos;t ruin one good thing in
Bangalore I love, it&apos;s tech culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-update-1&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-1&quot;&gt;UPDATE 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-update-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So I got a response from Venturesity after a friend posted this post in
their private group. This is what they said and my reply:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Venturesity: The problem statements are well-defined practical problems
which our clients are trying to solve themselves. Though they may seem
rigid at times, they leave enough room for creativity and innovation.
Our asking for a design document ensures serious participation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There will be stress when anyone tries to program/debug anywhere. But we
try to make the event as less stressful as possible. There is always
good food/music/dance to take the edge off.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We appreciate the criticism, Charanjit :)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Me: Putting a theme on a hackathon is the restriction which encourages
innovation, giving a &quot;problem statement&quot; is not. I don&apos;t think it
matters how well defined the problem statement is, you simply change the
meaning of the word hackathon when you push a problem statement for
everyone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What do companies want to achieve with the venturesity hackathons? Good
hackers as employees. Is racing the only way to do that? Say Stayzilla
want employees who can work in hotels domain. They gave us problem
statements and looked for people who demonstrated the qualities required
to solve those specific problems, and who can race. If they had chosen
to just theme that hackathon saying “theme is stay in hotels (or
something more creative), and we&apos;ll judge projects by 1. data mining
fu 2. Our API fu 3. Whatever their third problem statement was
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Companies are putting a lot of money in there, they should be clear
about what they want and try not to damage the culture. If they want to
hire &quot;hackers&quot; with vision and creativity along with the ability to
code, they should innovate and change their approach here a bit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If all the companies want are code-monkeys who race all day to achieve
goals in cubicles, then that is fine too. Just don&apos;t call it a
hackathon. Because it is not. When you give a too restrictive (or even
open) &quot;problem statement&quot; you killed the hack of hackathon, it&apos;s just a
(mar)athon that is left behind.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I respect companies for putting the money and for showing openness for
hiring. May be they are expecting to see innovative solutions to some of
their problem statement (like you said) that they can use from the
hackathon. But won&apos;t it be better if they let people truly innovate in
aspects the company has not thought of yet? They might get something
they haven&apos;t even imagined/envisioned yet, and they will surely get the
most innovative minds which they can then use for solving the problem
statements they actually need solved.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don&apos;t want to be too mean, but I didn&apos;t really expect Venturesity to
see the problem here. If they could, they would&apos;ve seen it by now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Also design documents is not a solution to their problem of &quot;serious
participation&quot;. Have you never participated in some big hack before?
Just copy ‘em if you can&apos;t participate. Why don&apos;t you ask people to
submit ideas, and have their github/linkedin/resumes (you already
collect that info) and filter ‘em by hand. Design Document thing is more
bad than problem statements.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
PS Stress in a hackathon is a luxury. We love it. That is the prime
motivator in a hackathon for pushing to the limit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>please-don-t-fuck-up-the-hackathons</guid>
            <pubDate>2015-04-13T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Making a System for Making a System for Productivity</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/making-a-system-for-making-a-system-for-productivity/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I thought out hard last night and came up with a system that might (or
might not) work. But I have to keep trying till I get it right. Here are
some main points of my new system:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-commitment-1-commitment&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;commitment-1-commitment&quot;&gt;#1 Commitment {#1-commitment}&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-commitment-1-commitment&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Do 8+ hours on day&apos;s priority #1 before you can open any other
website/video on the web. On weekdays it should be work that pay my
bills, on weekends it can be 2 things, study/side-kick-projects to try
new things/or whatever. I am free to just troll around on weekends, i.e
do nothing and waste the day. This is the only commitment I make for a
day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-iterate-2-iterate&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;iterate-2-iterate&quot;&gt;#2 Iterate {#2-iterate}&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-iterate-2-iterate&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Iterate over 3 days. Do above for 3 days, then review it and come up
with a list of things that were tempting me to divert from my plan. Then
replace these things with something else, or if possible get rid of
them. Improvise and bring changes in my system to remove all the
falsities. Also make a list of all the things that were motivating, and
keep bringing them back in the system with #3.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-change-3-change&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;change-3-change&quot;&gt;#3 Change {#3-change}&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-change-3-change&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bring something new in my workflow every 3 days. Start using some new
tool, make some modifications in Emacs.d, anything. If can&apos;t find
anything, spin something from good things I got from #2 and bring it in
the system with a flavour, or find a creative solution to get rid of
something bad from #2
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#x2013;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It&apos;s not a perfect system, but aiming for perfection has brought nothing
but failure for me in past. I am trying to strike a balance b/w
practicality and flexibility in the system. i.e for a system that would
be flexible enough to improvise over time but strict enough that I won&apos;t
get lost in managing the system itself. Idea is that I am going to get
bored from this system in 15 days max. So before that happens, it should
become self-sustaining and would require minimum input, while giving
maximum satisfaction.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is a system that should create another system when it dies in next
15 days, and same should happen after than. Only constant is change.
Keep improving, and more importantly, keep changing. Even if it is a
step in wrong direction once in a while, just change for the sake of
changing. If my system doesn&apos;t change, I will abandon it; so no matter
how much good it was, it&apos;s gonna get wasted. If it doesn&apos;t change that
is. Change is life baby!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By the way, today was the first day of me using this system. I
introduced Trello as a change to my workflow. I used to plan things in
org-mode in my Emacs, it&apos;s awesome. I changed to Trello just for the
sake of changing, and it worked wonders for one day at least. I believe
it can keep doing so for two more days. After that, I&apos;ll change
something else. Not necessarily my thought/todo management system, but
anything. I&apos;ll come back to Emacs&apos; org-mode some time later. Constant
change doesn&apos;t mean things can&apos;t repeat. Future is what if not a
reincarnation of past.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I did more tasks than I planned for today. It feels good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>making-a-system-for-making-a-system-for-productivity</guid>
            <pubDate>2015-04-01T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>A Mind Full of Chaos</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/a-mind-full-of-chaos/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I need to reinvent a system for keeping myself in check. I can&apos;t think of a
single thing I haven&apos;t tried in past; pomodoros, gtd, time boxing, what not.
They all work for some time, and then stop working. We find flaws in systems
pretty quickly; we find cracks, make excused to let us do the easiest thing, the
laziest thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No matter what system I would adopt next, it all wears off soon. This is a wheel
that has been reinvented countless times. If only world was so simple that what
works for one would work for all. I need to build a system unique for myself;
considering factors that might not have existed for those who predate me. Things
that I didn&apos;t include earlier.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-change&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;change&quot;&gt;Change&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-change&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I never considered change to be a part of any of my systems. I should this time.
I believe most things work because of the new tools/techniques/whatever they
bring on plate. A new lifestyle, a new toy, or just a different way to do
something. As soon as the newness fades away, it becomes a chore to do. A
cognitive load that I finally throw away with a deep breath.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wonder how I&apos;ll integrate change. To make it an ultimate changing system, may
I should adopt the actual digital nomad lifestyle. Travel around all the time. A
month here, few weeks there, keep hopping from city to city. But then, I don&apos;t
think I am a traveler kind of person. I like it more when there is less chaos
outside my mind.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-hunger&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hunger&quot;&gt;Hunger&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-hunger&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another important thing is the hunger for growth. I have an unquenchable thirst
for growing bigger and bigger. Bigger in everything. I am not a competitive
person though, I don&apos;t like competing with others. With just myself. I believe
it is a good thing. Most satisfying is when I grow my skill set, learning
something new or getting deeper into what I am already familiar with. But I
wonder if it should be used as a carrot, or as a central piece of the system.
Using it as carrot would be like having a 2 hour slot to study something after
the day&apos;s work is done. For making it a central piece of the system will require
me to find either:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New things to learn from within what I am currently working. Or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find work for what I want to learn/strengthen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-race&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;race&quot;&gt;Race&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-race&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am seeing people leaving me behind, in the race I don&apos;t know I belong
or not. A friend just got a job in a startup with very smart people. I
envy him for the work environment and team he&apos;ll have there. May be I&apos;ll
start looking for a job in May. Or just enter the wilds of freelancing,
leaving the mothership of faceyspacey. I don&apos;t know. But that would be
an easy workaround, not a solution. I might get into a team of people
smarter than me, but not now. Not before I learn to orchestrate this
chaos in my head.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These problems have been with me from the very beginning. I thought I
solved them when we were in that pressure cooker with celebvidy. They
seemed to be a thing of past when we were doing 18 hour days a year ago.
But here I am facing them again, half dead. Or living dead may be (the
problems, not me). I know I have nailed them, it just need a final push,
the last piece of puzzle.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-specs&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;specs&quot;&gt;Specs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-specs&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&apos;t like it when I waste a day like I did today. I need to develop a
real good system for myself, a system that will consume least willpower
and provide maximum satisfaction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-consumes-willpower&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;consumes-willpower&quot;&gt;Consumes willpower&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-consumes-willpower&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Decision making
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What to eat lunch, which cold drink, which snack. Fuck.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The feeling of &quot;not enough freedom&quot; I have living in the hostel.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Forcing myself to do things

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;when I actually want to do something else. Oooh new shiny
language/framework, so cool. I wanna do that, and I am stuck with
Meteor. I can code this shit in dreams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-boosts-willpower&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;boosts-willpower&quot;&gt;Boosts willpower&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-boosts-willpower&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Change in my tools
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A new cool mode in Emacs, some new sexy modification I do in
settings, some new cool way I invent to do something that was
repeating
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Knowing my tools better
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reading something new/deeper about Emacs/git/javascript/meteor is
generally a happy/refreshing moment
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Talking to someone new in a friendly way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If this backfires, it keep me drained for days though.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-maximum-satisfaction&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;maximum-satisfaction&quot;&gt;Maximum satisfaction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-maximum-satisfaction&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Seeing 8:00+ in the hours worked today Knocking more tasks from my todo
list than I actually plan to Exercising
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is funny all these things that give most satisfaction at the end of
the day are most hard to do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am making this a blog post. Will be funny to read in future when I
have conquered all these problems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>a-mind-full-of-chaos</guid>
            <pubDate>2015-03-31T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Small Things</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/small-things/</link>
            <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this post I am talking about the significance of small things in
life, some lessons I&apos;ve learned over time, and some random stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Everyday I go to bed with bigger than life dreams, promising myself
tomorrow is the day when I&apos;ll take a giant step to drop all my bad
habits and be a better, more productive person forever. A life full of
satisfaction is just a night away. I&apos;ve been doing this for may be over
2 years. Nothing changed of course. What actually mattered over time
were the small things. All the new year resolutions, or stricter &quot;code
of conduct&quot;s caused exhaustion at best, and dragged me into depression
at their worst.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Small things keep accumulating over time, like the little bit of poison
we eat everyday with &quot;food&quot;. Many times I&apos;d realize after it&apos;s too late,
the little something has gotten so big that I have to cut it off
altogether, or smother under the weight of little mistakes. A little bit
of submission over time can make your employer feel like he own you. A
little bit of lies, can mark you a liar for life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But it&apos;s not all bad that come from little things. I have just made
myself such that I see negative first. It is supposed to be a positive
post, but a small step it is.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-small-wins&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-wins&quot;&gt;Small Wins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-small-wins&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Winning is a habit. There are many theories that&apos;ll nod in affirmation,
I won&apos;t mention in this post. You have to get into the habit of winning
to keep winning. No biggie, win small win frequently, and soon you&apos;ll be
on the track of tackling any challenge with an invincible attitude, and
you will actually score big wins.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-small-losses&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-losses&quot;&gt;Small Losses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-small-losses&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I first started out with Python, it was all too easy. I was so
super confident I can do anything with my dragon slayer. I of course
fell on face many times, again and again. They never felt like a battle
lost, they were small. Insignificant. But it did it&apos;s job in bringing
down my morale for a long time. No matter with how much enthusiasm I&apos;d
start something, something in me always kept mocking me, &quot;you&apos;ll fail&quot;,
and I did. It still haunts me sometime, but I&apos;ve got over it pretty
well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When you are just starting with something new, be little careful and
build a momentum with small wins, avoid losses howsoever small they
would be.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don&apos;t mean don&apos;t start something challenging. Do whatever you want, be
prepared, you will hit walls. And when you do, remember not to
accumulate small losses, your mind is too stupid, fool it. For every
loss you suffer, score 3 wins. It doesn&apos;t matter how small they are,
just win something small, minute I&apos;d say, it doesn&apos;t matter, just win.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-small-habits&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-habits&quot;&gt;Small Habits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-small-habits&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Habits are hard to build and leave. It&apos;s hard to get rid of bad ones,
it&apos;s even harder to build good ones.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I feel it to be very expensive to force myself out of (or into)
something new. It takes a huge chunk of my always limited will power,
leave me drained and exhausted. Leave me with too little energy to make
myself do anything else throughout the day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead of building a big habit of doing regular exercise, I made some
small ones. Like eating some of my favorite snack bars every morning,
but only if I do 20 some push ups. It&apos;s working better than my previous
approach so far. I have raised the bar to 50 push ups in couple of
weeks. Yes its slow, but I win every morning, get to eat my favorite
snacks, and am building a healthy habit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So the takeaway, instead of bringing a big change in your daily routine,
bring a small one, and if that too is too much for your puny self, bribe
yourself with a small reward.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-write-better-code&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;write-better-code&quot;&gt;Write better code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-write-better-code&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enough talk about stupid meaningless life, let&apos;s discus some real stuff
now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some small things can make you better at writing code.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Start with the smallest, most minimal version of your program, as
featureless as it can be without losing its meaning, and build it.
Software in some ways is like pottery, start small, iterate till you are
satisfied, and then bake it with intensive testing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That&apos;s about tackling a problem, but how can you make your code better.
Well, make the smallest unit of your code clean and tidy. Now that
smallest unit can be whatever for you, I think of a file as the smallest
unit of my code. Start small, keep classes in their own files, keep the
file small and beautiful. At the end of the day, when you are about to
call your software &quot;done&quot;, looking at each file of your app should fill
your eyes with tears of joy. It should be that beautiful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And I can&apos;t emphasize it enough, keep your files small.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-read-code-better&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;read-code-better&quot;&gt;Read code better&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-read-code-better&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I was just getting started with software, what would bother me a
lot was &quot;how to read software&quot;. I struggled a lot with it, mostly
because I always took software too big for my mind back then.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, first of all, don&apos;t bite more than you can chew. Start with small
software, start with software you think you can write yourself and
increase the bar from there. Again, make several small wins before you
raise the bar for yourself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If the software is written well enough, you&apos;ll find it very easy to
understand and pleasant to read. For example, I found meteor to be a
great read and very easy to understand. Just dive in, read the readmes,
big picture start revealing itself and soon you&apos;re reading a novel
written in Javascript.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-small-annoyances&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-annoyances&quot;&gt;Small annoyances&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-small-annoyances&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And finally, small annoyances caused by the person sitting beside you
can make you wish the flight will crash and you&apos;ll get a chance to smack
his head into the running engine fan (or may be his feet first) before
you can finally die in peace
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>small-things</guid>
            <pubDate>2015-01-19T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Stalemate</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/stalemate/</link>
            <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I write here mostly only when things aren&apos;t going well in my life.
Writing is a good exercise, it clear thoughts. It work better when
others give you their opinions. So please be my guest and share your
thoughts in comments. After a quite a roller-coaster ride for past 6-7
months, I am finding myself caught up in a stalemate like situation.
That&apos;s what I am writing about here.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the moment there&apos;s trouble going between me and my first and foremost
mentor/employer James Gillmore. He&apos;s been paying me for past 7 months,
and for past couple weeks, I am not working well. So what&apos;s apparent to
me is coming end of our relationship.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reasons for me not working are unknown to me. But here are my guesses:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-no-work-place&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-work-place&quot;&gt;No work place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-no-work-place&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am living in a hostel working from my bed. There is no suitable place
to sit and work. Not much space in room that I could buy a small office
setup (aka a chair and table; I actually bought them but had to return
‘cause I couldn&apos;t place them anywhere). Working from bed is a disaster,
but somehow it worked fine for 3 months or so.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-not-getting-enough-food&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;not-getting-enough-food&quot;&gt;Not getting enough food&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-not-getting-enough-food&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I live in my head. Food for mind is important for me. With James, I&apos;ve
mostly worked in Javascript and Meteor.js. When he first contacted me,
my JavaScript was same as my French. I don&apos;t know French. It was a fun
ride. I learned a hell lot of stuff. Besides learning JavaScript and
meteor, I got the opportunity to manage AWS instances, tweaking npm
modules, setting up Mongo replicas, fixing Mysql servers, RoR apps (at
one instance) and many more. It was all super cool. But for past couple
months, I am not getting any food. I&apos;ve been working on a very
interesting project (a collaborative development tool that aims to make
the web writeable). But I feel like I am not learning anything new. I am
feeling like I am not growing. For last 3 months (since I moved to
Bangalore) I&apos;ve been constantly working for 8 hours a day, sometimes
working on weekends too.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Although I managed to teach myself Objective-C (out of foolish fear that
it might extinct before I could learn it) and Angular.js (I learned this
when I was teaching it to my girlfriend who wanted to make a phonegap
app; she got a job at Intel with that), but I don&apos;t think it&apos;s worth
even mentioning them. They were easy and I haven&apos;t mastered any of
these. IMO mastering anything without investing substantial amount of
time actually working in it is not possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-loneliness&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;loneliness&quot;&gt;Loneliness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-loneliness&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am loner to be honest. I despise company. This is festival season in
India, my roommates are gone to their homes. I can&apos;t be happier. But
it&apos;s not true when I am coding. I like company there. For about a month
I worked along with James Gillmore. He&apos;s like 10X smarter than I am. I
loved every moment of it even though for about a week we were working
may be 18 hours a day. I didn&apos;t exactly logged any hours, but I remember
all I did for may be a week was eat, sleep and code. Literally. I loved
it and still cherish the memory.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But for last 4 or so months, I am working all alone. I&apos;ve brought
meteor-only version of nucleus to a level where we can start using it
(internally), but I haven&apos;t even launched it yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-caught-in-a-limbo&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;caught-in-a-limbo&quot;&gt;Caught in a Limbo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-caught-in-a-limbo&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I find myself caught in a Limbo. I don&apos;t know if that&apos;s the word to use
here, I learned it from a blog post I read couple days ago (about
Ubisoft doing funny things with its employees). I am not working for
reasons unknown to me, and I am not doing anything else because I have
unfinished work to do. I have spent days just staring at my computer&apos;s
screen, not moving a finger.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My gut feeling says I should stick. But probably I should quit and find
myself work elsewhere on the interwebs. I really don&apos;t want to work in a
shitty development shop. Big companies won&apos;t take me because I don&apos;t
have any experience on paper. A freelancer friend (yes I made a friend
in new place) warned me that it&apos;s not that easy for un-established
Indian freelancers to find work. Apparently the law of averages rule the
Internet. With the vast number of Indian developers lurking around the
Internet and the quality of most of them, averages are certainly not in
my favour. Personally I don&apos;t want to quit. Reasons being I want to
finish what I&apos;ve started, for the sake of it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And I don&apos;t really have any savings to survive without work for more
than a couple weeks. But if I can&apos;t produce results.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>stalemate</guid>
            <pubDate>2014-10-12T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Ghost Out of Shell</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/ghost-out-of-shell/</link>
            <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this post are the thoughts running through my head nowadays.
Dreams, hopes and fears. I am depicting myself to be the ghost getting
out of my shell created by years of social isolation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am going to Bangalore. Jobless and almost empty-handed. But full of
hopes, and fears. Hope that it will be the place I imagine. Silicon
Valley of India. Of course not as good as SF, may be more like a pirated
version of it. I am pretty scared. There are far too many &quot;if&quot;s and a
lot I&apos;ve put at risk, some pretty sexy opportunities I&apos;ve ditched to
keep the commitment I made with myself a while ago, and a pile of lies I
imagine would be too heavy to bear if any of the &quot;if&quot;s returned true.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-ghost-shell-wtf&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ghost-shell-wtf&quot;&gt;Ghost? Shell? Wtf?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-ghost-shell-wtf&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am living in a sort of social isolation for past 4-5 years. I live
with my family, 90% of my villagers don&apos;t know I am a resident of this
village. They know there are two &quot;kids&quot; in my home, but most of them
think I live in hostel or something. This is abnormal. My village is
pretty small. Everyone knows everyone else. I&apos;ve been living a ghost
like existence. Why? I don&apos;t know why. Standing in group of people
bragging, teasing and sharing (almost always wrong) political wisdom
never amused me. I rather prefer to sit in front of the light filled
rectangle and put something amusing in my head to churn.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-why-am-i-doing-this&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-am-i-doing-this&quot;&gt;Why am I doing this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-why-am-i-doing-this&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve been unfortunate to never had a mentor who could understand me and
could show me a path. A guide can mean a lot. Trust me. I consider
myself very lucky, and even I couldn&apos;t get much out of trial and error
methods of finding a path for myself. I am talking about guidance in
technical realm. All I could become by 2 years of relentless pursuit on
my computer was a lost techie.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am lucky. Things always fall in the right place for me. They do
eventually. That&apos;s why I don&apos;t usually panic when shit goes wrong. But
it doesn&apos;t mean there is no sense of fear or anxiety. There&apos;s a hell lot
of it. Stupid belief (and a history to back that belief) that everything
will fall in right place eventually allow me to do crazy things and stay
with them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why this babbling? I was to tell why I have decided to move to Bangalore
instead of staying in the city closest to my village (Chandigarh) and
get a job there. Or may be freelance but stay in Chandigarh. I won&apos;t get
a job because I don&apos;t want to let James go. I got into him from a
stupider blog post of mine which hit HN, and have worked for him for
past 5 months. I&apos;ve learned a lot from him. But it&apos;s not finished yet.
There is much more I have to learn from him. And he&apos;s got a vision for a
great product we are working on, and I want to be the one who
materializes his vision.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can stay in Chandigarh and do freelancing. I&apos;ve ditched 2-3 pretty
lucrative jobs in here. But I want to get out into a tech land. I would
have gone out of India if I could, but unfortunately my finances won&apos;t
allow me to. Bangalore will be good enough I think.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-go-through-hell-and-die&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;go-through-hell-and-die&quot;&gt;Go through hell and die&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-go-through-hell-and-die&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
James told this to me once. We were discussing about how near-death
experience change a person&apos;s perception of life, how it fades away, and
how James became what he is after going through hell multiple times;
having a ridiculous debt on his head and getting out of it working every
waking moment. James said my true potential will come to surface only
when I am working with my life on line. I am pretty much already feeling
like that; but this feeling might be temporary. Fear of change you say.
This is going to be the biggest change of my life so far. I suppose
being jobless in a (rather expensive) place so far from home will be
ideal life on line situation. Keeping the pile of lies I&apos;ve earned is an
added bonus. This is a drowning feeling (although I have yet to leave
for Bangalore), but I&apos;ll have to get over it, with shear brute-force if
nothing else.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-the-pile-of-lies&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pile-of-lies&quot;&gt;The pile of lies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-the-pile-of-lies&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Indian parents don&apos;t let go their children (I am 22) that easily.
(Financial) security is most important thing for middle-class. So I had
to create a whole plot to make my voyage to Bangalore resistance free.
In this plot, I&apos;ve got a job in a software development company who make
software for Australian government. They pay me Rs. 35,000 pm, and I can
save about Rs. 20,000 per month (send Rs. 10,000 home and Rs. 10,000 my
personal savings). My parents have a thing about getting me immigrated
to Australia (my cousins are Aus citizens), so it was extra sugar to
keep them from having second thoughts. I have a (verbal) deal with James
by which he pay me about $1250 per month and make me write whatever
software for him. But what &quot;if&quot; something go off track and this deal is
broken? I wonder what I could do to save RS. 20,000 a month unemployed.
I have almost no other connections to get freelance work, and I don&apos;t
know how hard it is to seek a well paying job in Bangalore. Given my
meager bank balance, if James decide to ditch me, I wonder if could keep
myself fed for a month.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-freelancing-as-a-junior-developer&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;freelancing-as-a-junior-developer&quot;&gt;Freelancing as a Junior Developer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-freelancing-as-a-junior-developer&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Freelancing I&apos;ve experienced is not as easy as it sounds for a new born
developer, especially if you seek perfection and aim to have long
lasting bonds with clients. There are some things which you learn only
with experience. Even if you&apos;re successfully making a living
freelancing, it comes with a price. Learning a craft is many times fast
and efficient if you learn under the shadow of a master. I am depicting
senior developers / product managers here. I am still doing this,
because James play those two roles for me. He teaches me a lot, more
like a personal trainer and pay me more than I think I can get on a job
given my portfolio. So it&apos;s a win-win for me. If I had time I would
create a place on interwebs where Senior level devs could find
apprentices (to do stuff for less pay and more interest?), and
(passionate?) people kickstarting their carrier could find
mentors/employers to polish them. I would call it Internstine.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-how-am-i-feeling&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-am-i-feeling&quot;&gt;How am I feeling?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-how-am-i-feeling&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Excited. Scared. More of latter. I&apos;ve never got out of Chandigarh and
given my utter lack of sense of direction, I get lost in almost every
place. In the title of this post, I am considering the &quot;shell&quot; I am
leaving to be of protective nature rather than limiting. I&apos;ll have to
worry about finding a place to live, food, clothes and all sort of stuff
I never had to think of when at home. I imagine me getting lost on
airport, then on taxi stand, on the place where I am supposed to get a
hostel to live in, everywhere. I am excited I&apos;ll hopefully be in a
community of like-minded people. I hope I&apos;ll get chances to get into
them, I imagine tech meetups and hackathons to be a thing of daily life.
That&apos;s one of few things I think of and not piss my pants.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>ghost-out-of-shell</guid>
            <pubDate>2014-07-21T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>3K Later</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/3k-later/</link>
            <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This post is follow up to my previous unintentional rant about the
situation I was in and the tech scene in my city in general. In this
post I am writing the things I went through in past 3 months, joys and
burns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-k-3-k&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;k-3-k&quot;&gt;3 K {#3-k}&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-k-3-k&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yes 3 K is 3000 USD. It might not be too much for 3 month time period
(for you), but it&apos;s a huge sum if you see from my eyes. Besides, what I
learned in past three months is worth way more than 3K. Although I spent
almost all of it (Macbook + iPhone), but past 3 months had been bestest
of my life so far.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-opportunities-missed&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;opportunities-missed&quot;&gt;Opportunities Missed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-opportunities-missed&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I missed a lot of what was offered to me in a plate. Offer from awesome guys at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20140813170756/http://boards.coffeestrap.com/&quot;&gt;coffeestrap&lt;/a&gt;, the test project from &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20140813170756/http://www.epiphanyeyewear.com/&quot;&gt;Epiphany Eyewear&lt;/a&gt;, the awesome team we built
for learning ML and many more. All the sudden attention I got drove me nuts. It
was too much chaos in the days when my last post hit HN. I made many mistakes in
that time. Not that I regret it. I didn&apos;t let it all go away (it didn&apos;t let me
all go away). I held on to the most probably best of them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-the-mentor&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mentor&quot;&gt;The Mentor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-the-mentor&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I met a really awesome person. &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20140813170756/https://twitter.com/faceyspacey&quot;&gt;James Gillmore&lt;/a&gt;. I call him master. He was the
first person to offer me to teach code and I couldn&apos;t stop the adrenaline rush.
He offered to teach me Meteor.js and promised to give me real work once I know
enough of it. I denied. I wanted to do more of Django and Python and Machine
Learning, to get done with all I started. But I have a serious issues saying no
to people, especially when they ask for second time. On the email he&apos;d go in
detail explaining how Javascript is future of web and how Django and bros gonna
be a thing of past. So James convinced me to learn Meteor. Initially I was doing
it just to avoid saying no to him. I would do the coursera Machine learning
course all day, and would give about 2 hours a day to little fun project he gave
me. After about 13 hours (about a week), he said I was ready for a real project.
I was stunned. I was new to Javascript itself. But he has a way to boost you up.
When he want you to do something, he pumps you up with energy and you simply
can&apos;t say no. And I am happy that happened.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-the-early-wearout&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-early-wearout&quot;&gt;The early wearout&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-the-early-wearout&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I started out with full power on my first project. I was feeling a lot of
pressure from inside. There were people saying &quot;I won&apos;t let such person stand in
my office&quot; (a relative of mine who owns same kind of sweatshop as I mentioned in
other post said that, behind my back; if you&apos;re reading this Mr, you were being
a real bitch getting that post printed and showing it to my uncle). For the
first week, I coded for 16 hours a day for 7-8 consecutive days. Truth to be
told, all the progress in that project was made during that week. If I could
keep on going for just 2-3 more days, I could save me next 3 weeks. But at a
point it became too much for me. This was the first time I was doing real work,
first time I was getting instructions from someone to code, first time I was
getting paid significant money, and I wanted to nail it. I couldn&apos;t. In those 8
days, I was literally glued to my chair. When I&apos;d get up for dinner at night,
there I had a feeling as doped. A light spin in head and little dark in front of
eyes. On the 8th day that spin stayed when I woke up. The dark went all around
me I almost fell on floor. That day I opened Hacker News for first time in 8
days. It looked like it was &quot;burn-out&quot; themed that day. Every third post was
about burn-outs, devs going mad, and stuff. It scared the shit out of me. I
didn&apos;t want to go mad. I talked to James. I emailed him that I gonna take a day
off. He was cool with it. He was always cool with it. It was my stupid ass who
was pushing me harder and harder. It took me whole next week just to recover to
the point where I could think straight. It was a funny feeling. It was not a
burn-out. I didn&apos;t lose my will to code. I still wanted to and was still coding.
But I couldn&apos;t. It was a wall got built around my head and I was unable to think
deeper. Holding just few things in mind became difficult. I realised the
significance of thinking with holding detail in head. Something I always took
for granted. And a strange fear followed the week next.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-on-shoulders-of-the-giant&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-shoulders-of-the-giant&quot;&gt;On shoulders of the giant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-on-shoulders-of-the-giant&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I gave up on the first project more than one times. That has been the
pattern of my life for long. My fight or flight hormone almost always
choose flight. I could finish it only because of James. He&apos;d send me
emails to motivate me, and they worked. I would be on steroids the day
he sent me his motivational emails. I can&apos;t express my gratitude towards
him for picking me from the Internet, and for all the time and energy
(and money) he invested in me. I&apos;ve been sitting on a rollercoaster
under his mentorship.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-bad-habits-from-past&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bad-habits-from-past&quot;&gt;Bad habits from past&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-bad-habits-from-past&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-drag-it-to-the-end&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;drag-it-to-the-end&quot;&gt;Drag it to the end&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-drag-it-to-the-end&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Education system here is clunky. We have a whole year of study and exams in the
end (there are six months exams too, and of course stupid tests anytime in b/w).
The point is, most kids in schools find tricks to live through the schooling
without getting much of what they call education. One is to drag it to the end.
No need to touch the book the whole year, you can just study for a day and get
passed. I topped my class for 10 consecutive years with half day studies. Nobody
cares if you are learning anything or not, scores on your card is the only thing
that matter. This is a dangerous mentality to attain. I didn&apos;t realise the
consequences until I went through them. You naturally tend to drag tasks until
it is absolute necessary to do them. This leads to frustration and stress. Trust
me, once you do it enough times, the stress make a home in your head and won&apos;t
leave you alone. Not even during coitus. I won over most part of this though.
Trick I used is broadly known and followed by many. Just do it. Whenever James
would add a row to the todo sheet, I would just rush for it.This takes lot of
mental energy, but it works. I couldn&apos;t keep it on forever though, but I kept it
for long enough to break the habit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-hop-hop-hop&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;hop-hop-hop&quot;&gt;Hop hop hop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-hop-hop-hop&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One bad habit you acquire when you teach yourself stuff from internet
all by yourself is hopping. You hop, from here to there to somewhere.
There&apos;s nothing to stop you. When the primary goal is just &quot;learning&quot;,
you don&apos;t bother about sticking with a single technology. Mind simply
make excuses and you hop. Learning new things become analogous to
chewing a chewing-gum. You chew until it&apos;s sweet, and when you start
hitting the sour parts, you throw it away and put a new one in mouth. It
would be different for different people, but it worked this way for me.
I think thing that makes a difference is the direction. Some guys get
motivation when they start a project of their own, some guys (like me)
just never get the direcion. It takes real hard effort to get over the
plateaus and taste the bitter parts of technology. Nothing is all sweet.
You can&apos;t pass on a technology learning just the good parts, bad parts
are where you get real lessons. You don&apos;t know a technology well enough
if you don&apos;t know where it fails. Knowledge of failure is the real test
of your knowledge of something.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-the-most-important-lesson-give-up-or-fight-on&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-most-important-lesson-give-up-or-fight-on&quot;&gt;The most important lesson: Give up, or fight on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-the-most-important-lesson-give-up-or-fight-on&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is most important lesson only experience can teach. Experience
doesn&apos;t necessarily means failures (although failures count for more
valuable experience). James have been through what I am going right now.
He can perceive a dead end, he can also see when success is just beyond
the next wall. Me on the other hand give up when I am most close to
success, and keep ramming the steal wall until my head opens up. That&apos;s
where having a mentor makes a difference. Some mistakes help you grow
up, some take you down temporarily. If you make the second kind of
mistakes often enough, the temporary phase can get longer and longer.
Hitting the wrong walls was the reason of my fickleness. When you keep
hitting the wrong walls, your mind catch an (obviously wrong) pattern.
When you start doing something, the first hurdle raise an alarm that
&quot;this is like last time, remember how you wasted whole week trying to do
X but failed? This is same&quot;. Even when it&apos;s not. That alarm make you
give up early. Online courses, self-guided projects and all can do only
so much. Having a real mentor/sensai/guru with you takes the learning
process to another level. This is the traditional eastern way of
learning. Accept a master, make him accept you, and learn. Online
learning is great, but wherever I see, they are missing the most
important ingredient of all-round education: a real teacher/guide, who
could actively participate in student&apos;s growth. Where teacher is
genuinly interested in student&apos;s growth. If you are making another
Codeacademy, I&apos;d suggest aiming for Internstine instead.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-procrastination&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;procrastination&quot;&gt;Procrastination&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-procrastination&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I miss it. No really. When I was working on the work all the time, I
missed procrastinating. It&apos;s weird but I think procrastinating can be
recreational to some level. Or may be it&apos;s just being and not doing
anything that I am misinterpretting as procrastination. I don&apos;t have
words to say this thought, it&apos;s kinda rough in my mind at the moment,
but I believe it is recreational. Not just good procrastination, what I
mean is the type A of procrastination Paul Graham talks about in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20140813170756/http://paulgraham.com/procrastination.html&quot;&gt;his
essay&lt;/a&gt;. He talks about 3 kind of procrastination: A) Doing nothing B)
doing something less important C) doing something more important.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-changing-places&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;changing-places&quot;&gt;Changing places&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-changing-places&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve noticed a weird thing about productivity I haven&apos;t read much about.
I found myself more productive during first few days of working from a
new place. Like first week in my uncle&apos;s home, first few days at my
friend&apos;s place etc. After first few days, things become less
interesting, more boring. I&apos;ve noticed that same work stays interesting
if I keep switching places. Another reason I am considering staying a
contract worker instead of doing a day job.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-smartass-jackass&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;smartass-jackass&quot;&gt;Smartass Jackass&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-smartass-jackass&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve been proved wrong a lot lately. By many people. I was never proved
wrong ever by anyone until before 3 months. That could simply mean that
I&apos;ve been living with people most of whom are total idiots (I&apos;d have
said all, but lets stay safe in case someone confront me). World is a
big place. People are lot more smarter than I am. And I like that. That
means the game is not over yet. I have many levels more to play. Many
worlds to explore. I wanna explore. Want to see what this world has to
offer. I have a long way to go. I have to get over this anti-social
thing of mine, and be better at my craft. I really love programming; I
have to take myself to place where it&apos;ll love me back.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This post is getting little too long. I wanted to write about the
techniques and tricks I learned during this period, and also about my
thoughts and future plans to make my city better in terms of tech, but I
think I should write a separate post for it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;I wanna apologize to Sunny, Jayant, Martin and Lido. We started a team
to start learning Machine Learning, I was the one super determined, and
I was the one who quit first. I took more than one endeavors at a time
and gave the other more priority. I also wanna apologize to all those
whom I couldn&apos;t respond.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>3k-later</guid>
            <pubDate>2014-06-02T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Dear First World Dev, Have a Look at Your Nightmare. I Am Going to Live It</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/dear-first-world-dev-have-a-look-at-your-nightmare/</link>
            <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tech scene in my city (Chandigarh) is daunting. There is super heavy
exploitation of new developers and nobody seem to have any problem
with it. In this post I am plotting the situation from my view, and
sharing the reasons behind my decision of accepting a job where I&apos;ll
obviously get exploited.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For a long time, I&apos;ve been very afraid of doing a job in my locality.
First of my concerns have been that it will hinder my growth. From
people working in local companies, I&apos;ve heard things like &quot;they will
suck all plasma out of your blood; you&apos;ll hate to even look at a
computer&quot;. I don&apos;t want this to happen with me. I love computers, and I
want to keep loving computers. I don&apos;t want to get stuck either. On job,
I&apos;ll most likely be doing PHP projects. I don&apos;t want to do PHP for rest
of my life. It was the second language I learned, and I hate it. Looking
back at it after a year of Python, most of it look like mumble-jumble of
hoola-boo.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I will be working 48 hours a week (excluding break; mon-sat 10 am to 7
pm) for less than $100 per month. Pick that jaw up, I know it&apos;s
exploitation. What they are going to do is get projects from oDesk and
similar sites, and make developers do them, and pay like 0.01% to the
devs. I can do it myself sitting at home, I&apos;ve done a couple projects,
but it was not fun. I got bored and left my third project halfway. I am
so fucking undisciplined that it frustrates even me. Here&apos;s the list of
my reasons for diving into the situation which at the moment looks like
a whirlpool to hell.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-my-reasons-for-doing-this-job&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-reasons-for-doing-this-job&quot;&gt;My reasons for doing this job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-my-reasons-for-doing-this-job&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-indiscipline&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;indiscipline&quot;&gt;Indiscipline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-indiscipline&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am sick of my fickleness. I get bored like after 20 minutes of playing
with anything. I&apos;ve tried as many techniques as I could in 2 years to
discipline myself. I am expecting my new job to discipline me more. I am
expecting it to be one of the most suffocating environments I can
imagine as a developer. I know the culture of most companies in my city.
I&apos;ll have to keep my phone outside the office before I enter, only the
time I spend in my cube will be counted as my &apos;in office&apos; time and
similar. If nothing else, it will at least make me realize the
significance of all the freedom I have in my room.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-team&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;team&quot;&gt;Team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-team&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I want a team of coders to work with. I&apos;ve always done coding alone, and
I am sick of it. It&apos;s no fun. I want to work in a team. I want to show
off my work. And most importantly I want smart people around me to look
upto and learn from. There will probably be senior developers on job
from whom I can learn many things.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-network&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;network&quot;&gt;Network&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-network&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve been living in the place I am staying at present for about 8
months, and my neighbor doesn&apos;t know I live in this house. Actually I
met my neighbor in the new company I joined when I went there for
interview. He work there. He accidentally read the address on my resume
and asked me. I wasn&apos;t least bit surprised when he said &quot;I didn&apos;t know
you live there, I thought there&apos;s only an old couple in that house&quot;. I
have made literally 0 friends in the period of 8 months, and I hardly
know more than 5 people in whole city (that old couple included). I am
expecting to get to know more people from programming community. And may
be I&apos;ll make some friends.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-i-want-these-9-months-to-change-my-life&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-want-these-9-months-to-change-my-life&quot;&gt;I want these 9 months to change my life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-i-want-these-9-months-to-change-my-life&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I will be doing a bond of 9 months with them. If I leave them before 9
months, I will be paying them my 2 month salary before leaving. I want
these 9 months to change my life. I don&apos;t mind working heavily underpaid
if I can grow myself in same proportions as the exploitation. I will be
working in a technology I&apos;ve always hated, more because of other&apos;s
opinions than my own experience. From this I am expecting to learn
something I haven&apos;t realized yet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I want them to stand with a machine gun and shoot whatever they can at
me. I am expecting to gain a lot of mental strength and sharpen my
ability to quickly learn new things further. I&apos;ve always felt proud of
my quick-learning ability, I want to put it through the most intense
test.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-confidence&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;confidence&quot;&gt;Confidence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-confidence&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know many things. I&apos;ve developed things in Django, Flask, PyQt,
CodeIgniter, SlimPHP, Wordpress, Angularjs, ReactJs, Backbone and
similar tools. But still I could never collect enough nerve to bid for
any such projects on freelancing sites. I know I can do them, I do them
for my friends or for my experiments, but I get scared when it comes to
work for someone I don&apos;t know. On the job I&apos;ll be forced to do things.
May be by doing things this way I&apos;ll get some confidence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-i-want-to-study-the-environment&quot; class=&quot;outline-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-want-to-study-the-environment&quot;&gt;I want to study the environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-3&quot; id=&quot;text-i-want-to-study-the-environment&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the last thing on my mind, actually at the moment it is not even
on my mind. I am too scared thinking of what is about to come. But
earlier it was one my reasons for my decision of jumping in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Things are very bad in my city. There is no any kind of active community
of computer enthusiasts; be it some Linux Users Group or something
similar. For me thinking Hackathons in my city is similar to thinking a
Lamborghini in my garage. Developers are heavily underpaid and
over-exploited. I want to study the environment. I have ideas for a
self-sustaining software company that would follow an open business
model (another idea in my ideas.org). I want to foresee if it is
practical.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-thing-that-triggered-this-decision&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;thing-that-triggered-this-decision&quot;&gt;Thing that triggered this decision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-thing-that-triggered-this-decision&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have been at home for about 2 months, self-learning stuff. I thought
of continuing like this for next 4 months. Couple days back I met Jayant
on /r/machinelearning. (We&apos;ve decided to pursue learning ml the way I
discussed in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20140814135355/http://www.reddit.com/r/datascience/comments/1y9t11/is%5Fit%5Fa%5Fgood%5Fapproach%5Fto%5Fget%5Fstarted%5Fwith%5Fmachine/&quot;&gt;this
thread&lt;/a&gt;. If you are interested in joining the team pm me.) I talked to
him and he turned out to be in a situation very similar to mine. He even
called us identical twins. But he&apos;s a year ahead of me. He spent a whole
year self-learning without doing any job. He said the experience was
good and he learned a lot. I had a different feeling from his words
though. Assuming that we are identical, I want to know what would have
happened if he made the other choice. So I have decided to go for
&quot;learning on the shitty job&quot; approach, just to make a twist in the
timeline. It&apos;s looking like a risky decision to me, so I was postponing
it for some time. But the thrill of doing this experiment is what
triggered me doing it. Life is an experiment after all, and I like doing
crazy things with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>dear-first-world-dev-have-a-look-at-your-nightmare</guid>
            <pubDate>2014-02-26T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>One Reason Every Geek Should Blog For</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/one-reason-every-geek-should-blog-for/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Right answer is the most obvious one. Learning. Blogging helps a lot
when you are obsessed with learning and creating new things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You learn a lot if you blog responsibly
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started my first blog in 2011 (I run two now). It was first time I got an
Internet connection of my own. I was excited and I did some posts about few
things I was trying those days. Some people read it, few praised it, it felt
nice. Then I got bored. And I stopped writing slowly. There were people thanking
me for putting my time in writing and encouraging me to write more. But I
couldn&apos;t.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was not doing it right. I am a geek, not a blogger or writer or poet (although
I blog and &lt;a href=&quot;file:///poems/poem-pathr/&quot;&gt;write&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;file:///poems/poem-kaynat&quot;&gt;poems&lt;/a&gt;). Actually I recently discovered it. Writing and blogging
become all so much fun when you stop writing what you already know. Sharing
experience is cool. Actually it is only the experience that is worth writing
about. But for me it was very boring to sit down and write about what I already
knew. Then I tried writing posts as notes. Notes to remind me how to do stuff I
know I will forget in some time. But it didn&apos;t work either.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And then I started blogging with a different objective. Earlier I was writing my
experience to help people. But (un?)fortunately I am not that good a person who
would do things for helping others and enjoy it. I am little more on the devil&apos;s
side.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For about few weeks now, I am blogging for learning. Instead of writing a post I
already know, I write about things I want to know. I choose a topic (say git),
and think of a post I want to read about it (say, how internals of .git
directory work?). Then I start preparing to write it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No I don&apos;t Google it. It might be already written. There might be 10
posts already crawling through reddit on the same topic. I don&apos;t give a
fuck. What you read in blog posts is the summary. It&apos;s the juice drawn
from sugarcane. But the real thing a geek want is knowledge. True
knowledge can only be acquired by experience. You have to live through
the process of putting a piece down in soil, and grow your experience
into the sugarcane from which you can draw the juice and put in your
post. Of course how much you learn depends all on how much work you can
put when writing a post. I found it particularly beneficial to write
about topics I have some experience in but want to go deeper. Like git.
I use it everyday, but digging deeper is not a requirement.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my opinion, the secret sauce which make this work is responsibility.
When you write a post and you know people gonna read it, you can&apos;t write
carelessly. I can&apos;t say about others, but I feel a sense of
responsibility when I am writing about something I haven&apos;t personally
experienced long enough. It make me work extra hard.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&quot;Great power brings great responsibility&quot;, right? The inverse is also
true (in this case at least). Great responsibility can bring great power
as well (provided you can feel it). This worked with me. It might work
with you as well (unless you have already surpassed me in terms of
slacking and procrastination).
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>one-reason-every-geek-should-blog-for</guid>
            <pubDate>2014-02-24T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>My notes to help learning Javascript</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/my-notes-to-help-learning-javascript/</link>
            <description>

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-patience&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;patience&quot;&gt;Patience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-patience&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You need to keep it. Don&apos;t rush, it&apos;s alright if you are not getting it.
Specially if you are from Python world. Javascript is to Python like
India is to New Zeland, things are not actually as complicated as they
appear, you just need to keep little patience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-coffeescript-is-your-friend&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;coffeescript-is-your-friend&quot;&gt;Coffeescript is your friend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-coffeescript-is-your-friend&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Coffeescript helped me learn to think in javascript more than any book.
I am not saying that you should use coffeescript, but use it for
learning more about javascript. If you are unable to think something in
javascript, do a version of it in Coffeescript, generate javascript and
try to learn. I don&apos;t know how good is the generated javascript, but it
was good enough for me to not get stuck. Emacs helped me a lot in this.
I created a buffer with coffee-mode which was not visiting any file, and
compiled coffee to see javascript in a split window for comparison. It
really helped to avoid creating temporary files.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-don-t-rely-too-much-on-books-try-something-real&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;don-t-rely-too-much-on-books-try-something-real&quot;&gt;Don&apos;t rely too much on books, try something real&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-don-t-rely-too-much-on-books-try-something-real&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Books can do only so much to help you. Elequent Javascript is great (or
so they call it, actually I never got why it&apos;s called great), but what a
real project can teach you is on another level. Go out in wild and try
to do some real project, for fun of course.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-avoid-dom-and-ui&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;avoid-dom-and-ui&quot;&gt;Avoid DOM and UI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-avoid-dom-and-ui&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
DOM manipulation and Javascript have their own concepts which are most
times confusing to foreigners, specially if you are already infected by
JQuery. Make your aim to learn Javascript, as a programming language and
do something you do when learning a new language. Make self-contained
scripts which don&apos;t need browser to work. Of course browser help when
you are getting started and with &apos;console.log&apos; you can avoid all sort of
DOM manipulation, but that&apos;s not what I mean. On the next step to
getting started, when you &apos;think&apos; you know some javascript, try to make
something that involve as little DOM manipulation as possible. Try
making some simple nodeJs module, or some sort of browser extension.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-focus-on-getting-it-done-learning-is-a-bonus&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;focus-on-getting-it-done-learning-is-a-bonus&quot;&gt;Focus on getting it done, learning is a bonus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-focus-on-getting-it-done-learning-is-a-bonus&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&apos;s better if you choose to do something you want to use, or at least
something you find really interesting. And focus on getting it done. All
ninja skills you want to learn come as a bonus. Remember those old
Jackie Chan movies in which kung-fu master make him do his household
chores? Just focus on washing clothes, you&apos;ll learn iron-fist style
without knowing it, as a bonus.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>my-notes-to-help-learning-javascript</guid>
            <pubDate>2014-02-12T01:00:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>I Eventually Managed to Leverage My Wave</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/i-eventually-managed-to-leverage-my-wave/</link>
            <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The wave I am talking about here is the period of crests and troughs
which I have been experiencing for like always. It has always been a
very commoving pull-back experience. Lately I have been through a
series of change and started looking at things with a different eye.
Here&apos;s a list of things helping me the most.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My life is like riding a wave. When I am on the crest everything is
easy, I am super-curious, confident and over-flowing with energy. After
some time the energy of the crest goes away. And starts very depressing,
negative period. I feel myself to be a weight on Earth. People call them
`burn-outs&apos;. I have read they burn-out after doing something reckless.
But I burn-out periodically. This very negative time come in circles in
my life no matter what I do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But now I think I&apos;ve eventually managed to leverage my wave. I am not
just living with it, I am using it. I started looking at the world with
a different view after I read the Theory of Positive Disintegration. I
learned it&apos;s not bad to be super-sensitive. The sadness, the pain, they
can be used for good.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are some of the things helping me to make something out of all the
mess my life have become, and utilize the wave.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-abandoned-commitments-and-my-gtd-dot-org&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;abandoned-commitments-and-my-gtd-dot-org&quot;&gt;Abandoned commitments and my gtd.org&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-abandoned-commitments-and-my-gtd-dot-org&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I once tried to utilize the `Getting Things Done&apos; system. It didn&apos;t work
very well for me. Although it did not fail 100% either. Thanks to it now
I am in a habit of writing down most of my thoughts (I do it in an org
file I&apos;ve named gtd.org). I have made a list of all the commitments I
have made to myself, things I wanted to do but didn&apos;t, and things I want
to do in future. All the fallen dreams/commitments which have been a
psychological weight on me. One of the problems I face in troughs is
that I find nothing interesting. Like I don&apos;t want anything. Reading
through my gtd.org always give me something in which some part of me is
interested. I haven&apos;t recognized any pattern in this yet, but it
significantly decreases the trough period. Last time I found learning
e-lisp quite fascinating and that brought me out of the trough fast, and
my crest now is not that chaotic.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org5a866ba&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org5a866ba&quot;&gt;Inspiration from the&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org5a866ba&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
`&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.42floors.com/100-day-goals/&quot;&gt;100 day goals&lt;/a&gt;&apos;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I read a blog post in which an entrepreneur is talking about his system
of applying &apos;100 day limits&apos; to do some hard projects. He also warned
that he and his team get burnt out and need rest after that. I thought
to myself that I am going to burn out anyways, there is no stopping to
it, so why not give it a shot. May be it will do some good. And it is
working. I set a limit to finish `The Emacs-lisp intro&apos; in seven days,
and did it. It felt good. The sense of achievement was much needed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-self-introspection&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;self-introspection&quot;&gt;Self introspection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-self-introspection&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me self introspection appear to be a wastage of time on crests. But
it has been a great help in darkest depths of my troughs. Would it be
studying psychology, trying to diagnose myself for some mental disorder,
or just digging through my zodiac and stuff, it help me not get lost.
It&apos;s like the last line of defense for my focus, and has always worked
till now. It give me a feel that all the chaos can be sorted out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-video-games&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-games&quot;&gt;Video games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-video-games&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They have always been a source of despair actually. I waste all my time
in them when I am going through troughs. But I actually found a way to
utilize them. It came from another blog post I read. What I was doing
was that I used to play a lot of video games in troughs, and none at all
in crests. May be it created a pulling force towards troughs. Inspired
by above mentioned blog post, I now give a little time playing some
games everyday. And I am riding on my longest crest ever.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-a-pinch-of-success&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-pinch-of-success&quot;&gt;A pinch of success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-a-pinch-of-success&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I used to love my computer more than I love my girlfriend (note: my
culture has molded my mind to make me a serious one woman man, don&apos;t
interpret the word &apos;girlfriend&apos; as used in western-culture
relationships). I still feel fascinated about computers and programming,
but looking at my computer I have a feeling like a lost battle-ground.
There are so many things I thought I could do with it, so many I started
on it, and no one I ever finished. The wave is the one I blame.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;file:///blog/the-most-beautiful-tutorial/&quot;&gt;My previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; was a wild success (when seen from my eyes). It earned me
many hn and reddit points, and is still bringing traffic. It was a blow to my
thought that I can&apos;t achieve anything. Many of the self-doubting thoughts that
started raising heads in my head got chopped.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I took a lesson from it. Instead of trying to pursue my half-baked
world-changing ideas, I will spend more time doing small things. It
certainly doesn&apos;t mean I am not thinking big. I still have ideas that
will turn the world around ;-) But a pinch of success is necessary.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>i-eventually-managed-to-leverage-my-wave</guid>
            <pubDate>2013-10-20T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>The most beautiful tutorial</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/the-most-beautiful-tutorial/</link>
            <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The most beautiful tutorial I&apos;ve ever read, &quot;The Emacs-lisp Intro&quot;.
Run your Emacs and press &apos;C-h-i&apos;, and select &quot; Emacs Lisp Intro&quot; to
read it. I am a reader, and learner, I read a lot. I used to prefer
learning from books, and have a huge collection 70% of which I haven&apos;t
even ever opened (and 95% I have never completed). Most of my reads
are related to programming, new languages, techniques and frameworks.
Over time my preference for learning programming shifted from learning
from books to learning from tutorials, documentation and by reading
the code itself. I found myself too fickle to stick with one long book
and keep myself interested in it. There is so much to explore in the
world, whenever I start reading a book, half way through I find
something more interesting. Something from the book, or hacker news,
or reddit, or prismatic. Mind is always successful in finding some
sort of diversion. For a week ago, I had not find any book or tutorial
that could keep me with it till the end. And then I met &apos;the
Emacs-lisp intro&apos;. It&apos;s the most beautiful book (or tutorial, I don&apos;t
know what to call it) I have ever laid my eyes on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-perfect-flow&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;perfect-flow&quot;&gt;Perfect flow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-perfect-flow&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&apos;s more like a compilation of tutorials than a book, but it is so
beautifully organized. While reading it, it feels like it is
orchestrated in the most perfect way possible, to get the concepts
settle in your mind, and not letting you get bored at the same time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-i-never-felt-like-lost-somewhere&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-never-felt-like-lost-somewhere&quot;&gt;I never felt like lost somewhere&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-i-never-felt-like-lost-somewhere&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Being a mere mortal, many times when reading programming stuff I get
lost in between. Some topics that just don&apos;t enter my head, some things
I can&apos;t grasp sometime. Most tuts just get over with it leaving me in
half despair. But this one was very well laid out. I never had a feeling
like missing something or getting behind the author.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-it-held-my-hand-but-never-spoon-fed&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-held-my-hand-but-never-spoon-fed&quot;&gt;It held my hand but never spoon fed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-it-held-my-hand-but-never-spoon-fed&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another beautiful thing. Easy tutorials most times are just too easy,
their easiness make them boring. I was working myself when reading this
tutorial. It was (little) challenging and very easy flow. Perfect for
me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-i-learned-to-praise-lisp-and-the-beauty-of-parenthesis&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-learned-to-praise-lisp-and-the-beauty-of-parenthesis&quot;&gt;I learned to praise lisp and the beauty of parenthesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-i-learned-to-praise-lisp-and-the-beauty-of-parenthesis&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The perfect speed with which the things are put forward, and the clarity
with which it&apos;s done made me respect lisp much more. I learned so much
about how lisp works and how things are done in lisp world without even
knowing I was learning them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-if-you-tried-learning-a-lisp--clojure--and-found-it-too-difficult-try-reading-this-tutorial&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-tried-learning-a-lisp--clojure--and-found-it-too-difficult-try-reading-this-tutorial&quot;&gt;If you tried learning a lisp (Clojure?) and found it too difficult, try reading this tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-if-you-tried-learning-a-lisp--clojure--and-found-it-too-difficult-try-reading-this-tutorial&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I tried learning Clojure few months back. I got a book and tried to
study it. I failed. There were so many things quite foreign to me, and I
decided to put on the shelf for future. That was the right decision.
Reading this tutorial made many things clear, and weird things
respectable. I think now I am ready to give Clojure another shot.
Reading first few chapters of the same book (Programming Clojure) was so
much easier than before.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-using-anki-alongside-perfect-combination-for-producing-some-emacs-love&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-anki-alongside-perfect-combination-for-producing-some-emacs-love&quot;&gt;Using Anki alongside: perfect combination for producing some Emacs love&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-using-anki-alongside-perfect-combination-for-producing-some-emacs-love&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve been using Anki for spaced learning for a while now. I use it every
time I am reading something, it help me a lot to avoid re-reading books
I left half way (and then pick up later). Still it was a different
experience using it while reading this tutorial. So many ideas of doing
stuff with Emacs were popping up in my head while reading this tutorial,
and thanks to Anki I reminded every e-lisp function I encountered on the
way, and this made me feel comfortable as I knew their possible
implementations, I knew what to use, and where to take inspiration from.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-it-made-emacs-appear-so-simple-and-easy-and-powerful&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-made-emacs-appear-so-simple-and-easy-and-powerful&quot;&gt;It made Emacs appear so simple and easy, and powerful&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-it-made-emacs-appear-so-simple-and-easy-and-powerful&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have been using emacs for few months now (3 or 4 may be). I thought I
knew it just fine and that it&apos;s awesome but over-glorified. I was wrong.
Emacs is awesome indeed, but I didn&apos;t knew shit about it. And no one can
tell you the real glory of Emacs. It&apos;s a path one need to travel to know
the feel. It has changed many things in me as a programmer. For one
thing, I now feel much more controlled (and like secure in some way
(&apos;cause of my psychotic issues may be)) when doing anything in Emacs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-fill-your-mind-with-tons-of-ideas-things-you-want-your-editor-to-do-and-they-are-all-possible&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fill-your-mind-with-tons-of-ideas-things-you-want-your-editor-to-do-and-they-are-all-possible&quot;&gt;Fill your mind with tons of ideas, things you want your editor to do, and they are all possible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-fill-your-mind-with-tons-of-ideas-things-you-want-your-editor-to-do-and-they-are-all-possible&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Emacs is known for its ability to customize, everyone know that. So did
I. But no, now I feel I really didn&apos;t know that. There is a whole world
of possibilities. There is so much one might desire from their editor
and not even know it. Now I realize so many things are wrong with my
current setup, so many new things I want Emacs to do. It&apos;s a very good
feeling to have.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-it-was-a-bliss-reading-it-inside-the-emacs&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-was-a-bliss-reading-it-inside-the-emacs&quot;&gt;It was a bliss reading it inside the Emacs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-it-was-a-bliss-reading-it-inside-the-emacs&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think it is the most important thing that made me feel so great about
this tutorial. Emacs dwarfs any awesome e-book reader I have ever tried.
Not because of navigation or any other fancy,but because I suddenly
realized that right way to read about programming is from inside my
editor. Even a simple &apos;alt-tab&apos; is too much. Almost all the cases where
I would normally copy-paste the code to check out something (I know
copy-paste is a bad thing, but lazy me) were replaced with a &apos;ctrl-e&apos;. I
could execute the code right there inside the tutorial, even parts of
it. There are browser embedded consoles and stuff which do the similar,
but they can never match the experience Emacs gave.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>the-most-beautiful-tutorial</guid>
            <pubDate>2013-10-11T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Directionless Wandering</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/directionless-wandering-cursed-by-dreams/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
It has been about five years since I first got my computer. Endless
hours I have spent in front of the two dimensional rectangle, the third
world. Before I got the machine, most of my time was spent in the world
inside my head. My thoughts, feelings, sensations and so many things. I
was never at rest. Then I got the machine. I had dreamed of it for like
years before I got one. I was excited, fascinated. There were so many
things in my mind to do with the computer, so many plans of changing the
world. I couldn&apos;t harness any of them. Now it feels like every dream I
had back then has become a burden on my shoulders, depressing me, making
my feet heavy. Keeping me from moving forward. I am feeling powerless,
like I am losing a bit of life with every failed dream. I&apos;m getting
frightened from dreaming. What have it brought to me other than burden?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Clarity of thoughts was never my strength, but nowadays I am feeling
much more puzzled. Lost. Like I am stuck. World is leaving me behind.
I&apos;ve always seen the world like a witness. The third person standing on
the shore looking at the fishes racing, the canaries flying. Something
has happened. Making me feel as I am in the middle of the race I always
witnessed. Just witnessed. Never participated. Not even as audience. I
blame dreams. The fallen ones.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday on reddit I found a name for my madness. Existential
Depression they call it. It made me believe I am not the only one
feeling this. There are others. There might be others who have gone
through the path I am on now. May be they could give me a tip or two.
Here I am outside my diary, writing in public.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have been into computers for so long. And yet I found myself no where.
So much time I have put into programming, operating systems, security,
psychology and so many other things. All seem wasted. It is depressing
to just look at all the mess I have made of me. I see people so less
talented than me, with no knowledge of what they are doing, even doing
it wrong, crossing me in terms of success. They are richer, happier, and
better than me. I know I can do what they are doing 10 times better, but
I don&apos;t. Instead of motivating me, it is drowning me even deeper. I feel
no motivation to finish any project I start. And when the unfinished
gets piled up, they haunt me. They make me angry and depressed. I can&apos;t
remember how many times I swiped my hard disk to get rid of the
unfinished &apos;awesome&apos; projects I thought will change the world. So many
half written poems whose traces can&apos;t be found now in the burnt
notebooks. It sucks. I feel like every single thought I had, every new
idea I ever failed has cursed me. I have a trembling feeling just
thinking about thinking something new.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So many techniques I tried. So many psychology papers, books I read.
Still I am here. Another trough. I&apos;ve tried the GTD (Getting Things
Done) and the concept of &apos;limited willpower&apos;. Wrote all my mess down.
Tried to minimize the decision making. And so much more. This fucking
wave is just not leaving me. I find myself stuck in the crests and
troughs all the time. I am on the top of sky when on a crest. Have so
many new ideas, start new projects. Start reading new books. New
programming languages. New frameworks. New poets. And then it all start
fading. Then come the phase when I try to balance things. And just when
I feel I can do it, I find myself in middle of a trough. The disgust and
depression of it is just killing. I do many stupid things in troughs.
All failures. May be writing this blog post is one of them. May be after
some hours I will start feeling ashamed of writing such a thing, and
delete it. It just sucks to be here. I know it will pass. It always do.
But it leave behind scars. Scars that will keep scaring me from thinking
new ideas, from dreaming. And I think this might be the lesson. Dreams
suck.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>directionless-wandering-cursed-by-dreams</guid>
            <pubDate>2013-09-30T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>