<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts tagged `life&apos;</title>
        <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        <generator>cl-ownpress</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <image>
            <title>Posts tagged `life&apos;</title>
            <url>/images/spooky-avatar.png</url>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>I am moving to Berlin</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/i-am-moving-to-berlin/</link>
            <description>
&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org0a739fe&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org0a739fe&quot;&gt;Why&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org0a739fe&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are several reasons I stated in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitspook.in/blog/after-6-months-of-voluntary-unemployment/&quot;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Other than those,
here are a few more:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Peer pressure
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At this point it is customary for Punjabis to immigrate to a foreign country.
Since I was little I was conditioned to want to go to a developed country, so
it had become a deep rooted desire. My choice was of &lt;b&gt;which&lt;/b&gt; country, and
going against the advice of almost everyone in my family, I chose to not go
to Canada or Australia. I was promised more money and easier life in those
countries, but I see more of my personal goals in alignment in Germany.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Cold weather
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Punjab has colder weather than most parts of India, and they&apos;re my favorite
part of the year. I absolutely abhor Punjab&apos;s summers. Germany&apos;s cold weather
was appealing.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Europe
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The fact that I get access to more than one country was also a factor. If I
still have the appetite, I can move to a different culture relatively easily.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Rules
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am a sucker for rules. If they are sensible and sensibly implemented, they
can free you up in so many ways. Many lines-of-thought can be short-circuited
and mental resources invested in more interesting things. Germany as far as I
have researched online have more sensible rules, and a culture of mostly
following them.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orge38a1b3&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orge38a1b3&quot;&gt;How I am feeling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orge38a1b3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am scared shitless. I am full of stress and anxiety, I can barely sleep and
can&apos;t focus on anything. I have stopped drinking coffee because I no longer need
caffeine for the jitters.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is way more scarier than what I imagined. When I decided to move to Berlin I
was excited, a little scared too but also looking forward to it. Now I am
fighting myself to not just drop the whole thing every second of the day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am not an adventurous person, I find all forms of traveling tiresome. I stay
at home to recharge. Fear I am feeling right now however is more than the
ambiguity of going somewhere new. Me burning through my savings during past few
months is also a major contributor. I have made this huge decision, and spent
almost all my remaining funds to book housing, tickets and stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgfb3f383&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgfb3f383&quot;&gt;What lies ahead&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgfb3f383&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I intend to come back to India after at most 2 years and at least 1 year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
1 year minimum because 1 year is the limit I am putting for myself to buckle up
and stay in Berlin, experience stuff even if I don&apos;t want to. I am hoping it&apos;ll
be enough to reveal whether my feeling that being outside my comfort zone will
make me do more fulfilling things is true or not. 2 year maximum because I think
2 years should be enough for personal growth by being in a foreign country.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I find the ideas of e-governance and using technology in public administration
most exciting. I think India is the right place to make most impact with these.
I want to establish a parallel social administration system, which can help the
State&apos;s system, or fight it to make a positive impact. This is also one of the
reasons I have decided to go work outside India. Because it is a significant
commitment and I don&apos;t want to find myself taking breaks from it for other
things I wanted to do which might significantly disrupt this commitment.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Or all this could just be fantasies. In almost every phase of life, whenever I
felt like things need to be improved I have fantasized about how things could
have been made better. At my home, in school, in college, in software companies,
in my village, in my city, in the companies I worked in; pretty much everywhere.
I have not always taken action, and often moved to the newer set of problems
forgetting the old ones as they became irrelevant to me. I won&apos;t fight it if it
happens this time as well. I can&apos;t fight every battle, I prefer letting the
fights pick themselves for me. But so far I am fully intent on returning to
India and participate somehow in public administration.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20221122T151233</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-11-22T16:12:00.000000+01:00</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>After 6 months of voluntary unemployment</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/after-6-months-of-voluntary-unemployment/</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
For the last six months, I have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitspook.in/blog/i-have-quit-my-job&quot;&gt;voluntarily unemployed&lt;/a&gt;. Here&apos;s a brief
summary of how the last six months shaped my thoughts, and an abstract plan of
what I intend to do next.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgaaffce2&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgaaffce2&quot;&gt;Mental health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgaaffce2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I needed this break a lot more than I thought I did. Being perpetually restless
had been my state of being for too long. It felt good, to breath out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When writing software, you reach a certain point where things start falling into
place, the uncertainties are answered for and you can feel that the decisions
you made were right. Those few seconds of invincibility spanned over several
(not always consequent) days, because I felt it was me in control. Them I
remember most cherishingly. It was a kind of high I intend to chase again in
life.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Primary reason for which I quit my job was the curiosity about whether I can
manage my ADHD now; or if I still need the crutches of accountability. On job, I
could effortlessly perform well, in contrast to solo freelancing. My therapist
had suggested it will get better with age.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had more good days than bad, which is a win. Unfortunately I still don&apos;t have
a definite answer to consider the matter resolved. More on this later (below).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgb5756fc&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgb5756fc&quot;&gt;Social work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgb5756fc&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When busy with material responsibilities, I used to fantasize that if I had more
free time I could do so much more for people around me. When I had it, I tried
to start with the place closest to my heart.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tried to &quot;help&quot; my village by contributing to its small primary school, least
politically charged of situations there. Well, not so much as tried to help as
probed with a long stick to assess the willingness to be helped. I quickly found
out that a significant involvement there is a luxury I can&apos;t afford just yet.
Established power structures see everything new as threat, and eagerly sabotage
what they can get away with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So I chose a different avenue. One just as dear to me, but where I have more
experience and room to maneuver. I decided to make &lt;a href=&quot;https://entropyhacker.space/&quot;&gt;another attempt&lt;/a&gt; to nurture a
healthy tech culture in my city. It produced mixed results because I was not
able to put in as much energy as it demanded.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org400a956&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org400a956&quot;&gt;Mistake of learning Common Lisp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org400a956&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was running full speed building &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/press.el&quot;&gt;foolish&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/spookfox&quot;&gt;things&lt;/a&gt;. Then lisp came calling.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video autoplay loop alt=&quot;Wile E Coyote hitting the tunnel. Tunnel hits back.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;/videos/hit-it.webm&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was working on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitspook/entropy&quot;&gt;Entropy&lt;/a&gt;, to build a software to help me do the leg work of
building a tech community. Thought came that it is for hackers, so it should be
hackable. Lisp is praised for how hackable it is. It is also praised for its
expressiveness. Momentum is something I was finding hard to achieve with Rust,
because of my inexperience and perhaps the nature of the language and problem I
was trying to solve with it. At least checking lisp out seemed reasonable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After 30 years of living with them, I have come to recognize desires of pivotal
nature. In the face of these sublimely consuming whims, I can either do what
they say, or not do anything at all (I am told it is common with ADHD, so not to
beat myself too much about it).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve learned that it is possible to suppress these urges by feigning blindness.
My mistake was that of indecision. It is not possible to take a sip and not
gulp. I chose to look at it, but took too long to engage. I got thrown off the
build-mode.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have observed that I operate in two distinct modes: build-mode and study-mode.
Although building something is always a learning experience, and to learn
something I gotta build something; it is efficient to treat them as separate. It
is also easier on my mental peace.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This time, the transition between the two modes was not smooth. Getting
involuntarily thrown out of the workshop left me with (mental) bruises. This
incident is the reason I still consider the matter of my self-discipline
unresolved. Although the fact that there were only 2 such incidents over 6
months is a win by itself (another was when I fell in love with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://practicalguidetoevil.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;, and
spent weeks doing nothing else).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I filled the downtime during transition with another thing I wanted to do, and
probably would not have done otherwise. I traveled.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org4b515ea&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org4b515ea&quot;&gt;Travel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org4b515ea&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am not much of a site-seeing kind of guy. I find traveling exhausting,
regardless of how beautiful the views or how fun the activities. Being a tourist
is not for me. I like to stay and experience. I enjoy exploring/observing people
(people watching?). Witnessing people go by their lives is soothing. There is a
warm fuzzy feeling behind every smile, however mundane.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So I traveled the way I truly like, perhaps for the first time. For about 3
months trotting around the mountains of Uttrakhand, visiting people in their
homes (home stays). Observing a way of life familiar yet strange.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It came as a surprise how eye-opening the experience turned out to be, despite
being quite event-less. It was like learning a new language or studying math. I
could almost feel my brain building new connections. This is one of the few
feelings which still stays exciting even when the rat-race and hoarding have
stopped being as stimulating. I did not expect to find an entirely new source of
it in an experience like this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is also the easiest methods in terms of active participation, compared to all
the other sources (most are a variations of intellectual exercises; solving a
challenging problem, crafting an elegant solution etc). It does have its costs,
but I believe they do not overlap with those of other methods; so they can be
employed at the same time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I take it to mean I can have twice of what makes me feel most alive, just by
putting myself in a place 🤯
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-org458387f&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;org458387f&quot;&gt;What comes next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-org458387f&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can perhaps spend a few more months before I run out of savings, but the
dimming safety net has already started making me anxious. I miss the tribe-like
feeling of working in a team, so I am actually looking forward to join work for
that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most freeing would be to start a business of my own; not because it will leave
me with more free time, but because I can feel more like myself when working on
something I find meaningful. But that won&apos;t be profitable right out of the door,
so perhaps after a bit more grinding I can save up to give myself a chance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The grind is decided, but I will not choose misery along with. I intend to chase
the feeling of growth and fulfillment. With these constraints, some more
decisions make themselves:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can&apos;t stay at home. Being home is extremely comfortable, but with
comfort comes stagnation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need a job which leaves me with enough time I can invest in something
demanding like math&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to put myself in a foreign culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Putting these into practice, I have decided I&apos;ll move to Berlin for a few years.
The city makes itself a good place to be for me for a few reasons:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practically, it is perhaps the easiest to immigrate to for an individual
Indian citizen, with a job in hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has a good hacker culture, something I&apos;ve always wanted to experience but
have only ever read about&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;German culture seem like a great fit for my personal tastes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get to learn a new language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;German work culture is praised (on the Internet) for respecting boundaries and
giving a priority to life over money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I ever decide to seek higher education (which is likely), German education
policies are good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now that that is decided, what&apos;s left to figure out is how to go about it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-orgee5fc11&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orgee5fc11&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-orgee5fc11&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After 6 months of voluntary unemployment, I am the same man I was before it.
Things I experienced and burdens I unburdened could be achieved by other means
as well. Perhaps I&apos;ve sown seeds to make me a different person in future, but
they will take time to bloom. It is a guessing game, same as what might have
happened had I done it differently.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As for the journey to be where I already was, I&apos;ll do it again if I can.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>20220921T194836</guid>
            <pubDate>2022-10-03T02:00:00.000000+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>