<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts tagged `introspection&apos;</title>
        <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        <generator>cl-ownpress</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <image>
            <title>Posts tagged `introspection&apos;</title>
            <url>/images/avatar.png</url>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>Coming to terms with ADHD</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/coming-to-terms-with-adhd</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
After my recent subscription to &lt;a href=&quot;http://reddit.com/r/adhd&quot;&gt;/r/adhd&lt;/a&gt;, I
realized how important it can be to share experiences. Even when it is
something very personal and seem unlikely that anyone can relate to it,
it can be quite helpful for someone who thinks she&apos;s alone with her
struggles. A while back I deleted most of my old blog posts feeling
embarrassed of their suspected cringeworthiness. Now I think it was a
mistake. I am thinking about resurrecting them from archive.org.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this post I want to talk about how I came to the single instance of
my life when I am not completely lost in self-pity for being too lazy
and undisciplined. Perhaps it was this self-loathing that slowly turned
to depression, and a bad event finally pushed me into the hole that I
believe I am out of now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started my research on ADHD when my doctor pointed I might have it. At
that time I was in limbo of a special kind. I was quite used to the
struggle of making myself do work that wasn&apos;t interesting anymore. I was
also used to the periods of time when I was simply incapable of doing
any work. But what made me go to the doctor was a relatively longer
period of true nothingness. Nothing would excite me, no matter what I
tried. The chaos inside my head got so out of control I was often
talking to myself in an attempt to materialize the voices and solidify
the line of thought so I could deal with them one at a time. Nothing
worked. I would often contemplate suicide because my mind just wouldn&apos;t
shut up about how pathetic I was. It was then I decided to consult help
from a professional.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have not reached a solution, perhaps there is no solution that solves
everything. But here is a list of things that has made a huge impact in
helping me come to terms with my ADHD.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-keep-a-daily-journal&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-a-daily-journal&quot;&gt;Keep a daily journal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-keep-a-daily-journal&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Try to know yourself. Understanding why you are thinking what you are
thinking can be immensely helpful. It will help you figure out the flaws
in your thinking, and how to make up for them. For example, a pat
routine has saved me so many times once I started noticing that how
often in a single I would forget my wallet or my phone or keys. Small
things like this add up to make life miserable, and often go unnoticed
in the storms of thoughts we face every day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So much of the overwhelmingness can just be let gone by writing it down.
Try to be your own therapist, try to witness yourself. Not to
participate, or engage, just analyze. It can be quite an exhausting
thing to do, but I&apos;ve found it to be more helpful than meditation. When
I write in my diary, I find myself to be much more in control of life
the next day. It&apos;ll also help you figure out which of your ideas are
actually work-able and which are just fluff that need to go in trash
can.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-write-stuff-down&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;write-stuff-down&quot;&gt;Write stuff down&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-write-stuff-down&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You don&apos;t need to wait for the night to fall before you can write in
your diary. Writing often during the day is quite helpful too. Write
anything and everything down. Is it something you want to do but can&apos;t
right now? Create a todo entry. Just had a brilliant new idea? Capture
it. Invest in a tool that can help you capture your thoughts quickly.
Make this process a part of your life. I use Emacs&apos; Org mode which has a
brilliant capture system, and I am very happy with it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-delegate-to-your-future-self&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;delegate-to-your-future-self&quot;&gt;Delegate to your future self&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-delegate-to-your-future-self&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You don&apos;t need to do all the hundred things you have thought of, today
itself. Delegate them to your future self. I don&apos;t remember where I
learned it, but it is very helpful to treat your future self as a
different person, and just assign tasks to him that you don&apos;t have time
to work on right now. You can schedule stuff you capture right away, or
you can have a weekly review when you sort everything you captured in
the week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-review-weekly&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;review-weekly&quot;&gt;Review weekly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-review-weekly&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is very important to review everything you capture on regular
intervals. It&apos;ll give you confidence regarding your system, you could
trust yourself more. When you can start trusting your future self,
things becomes a lot very easier. You also become better at estimating
stuff, so the commitments you give to other people bring you that much
less anxiety.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-respect-the-decisions-made-by-your-past-self&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;respect-the-decisions-made-by-your-past-self&quot;&gt;Respect the decisions made by your past self&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-respect-the-decisions-made-by-your-past-self&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Only way you can trust your future self to finish what&apos;s assigned to him
is if you respect the decisions made by your past self. You don&apos;t have
to beat yourself up too much about it either. Understand that it&apos;s not
easy to estimate things. If we could predict things very reliably, we
could open shops as psychics. Try to achieve &quot;eventual consistency&quot;. Not
everything is equally important. Make sure that if something has been
assigned to you, it eventually gets completed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;outline-container-find-something-you-can-attach-meaning-to&quot; class=&quot;outline-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;find-something-you-can-attach-meaning-to&quot;&gt;Find something you can attach meaning to&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;outline-text-2&quot; id=&quot;text-find-something-you-can-attach-meaning-to&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&apos;s helpful to have something to call home. A principle that you
wouldn&apos;t compromise with. I have chosen to attach meaning to the quality
of the work I do. That&apos;s where I try to find solace. That&apos;s what I use
to bring myself to peace, when I can&apos;t control the mess in some parts of
my life. It might be one of the cardinal sins, but this kind of pride
helps build confidence to face life.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>coming-to-terms-with-adhd</guid>
            <pubDate>2018-12-15T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Relationships</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/relationships</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Romantic relationships are such amazing things. I have had moments in my
life when I considered myself to have a certain level of control on my
mind; in terms of that I can witness myself as an outsider. The
introspection, the self awareness that make me think that, very rarely
accompany me when I am in a relationship. It seem to have a liking to
solitude.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking at it from far really brings the picture of a &quot;family man&quot; home.
A lone man seem to have the ability to accomplish much more than a man
bound to another person. It takes a lot of energy just to be with
someone. It has been 220 days since I last wrote a diary entry; my
primary medium of introspection. I&apos;ve been so lost in the everyday
churn, I chose not to give time to my self. Not that I am complaining;
I&apos;ve been happily lost.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For however many gifts solitude brings, the pain of loneliness is not
something to fool around with. Perhaps it is the pain itself that make
great people do great things, but it did make me realize the meaning of
crippling in crippling depression. Perhaps this is one of the reasons
successful people credit half their success to their partners. It must
be possible to have partners that can assist each other unlock their
potentials. Can you be so alone with someone? I wonder if it is a matter
of finding someone right, or making yourself right for the one you are
with. I am going to put all my eggs in the latter basket. We&apos;ll see how
this gamble plays out.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>relationships</guid>
            <pubDate>2018-11-10T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>That sounds fun!</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/that-sounds-fun</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
I got an opportunity to introspect in a conversation with a client when
he questioned my use of the word &quot;fun&quot;. What do I mean when I say
something is fun? I am not entirely sure. May be when I see something
that excites me a little. People have very different interpretations of
fun. For me it is usually applying creativity to build something.
Activities the involve combination of these two, make me feel most
satisfied. Balance is very important.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But what do I really mean when I say something is fun? I almost never
know if it is going to be fulfilling at the time of making this
declaration. So how do I reach the point where I can say that X is going
to be fun?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It might be is the opportunity to learn something new. The unknown
scares me. It&apos;s a thrill and possibly vain feeling of growth. I have a
long list of things I want to learn/master. When my mind sees an
opportunity to check a box off of that list it gets excited.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It might as well be pure vanity. Vanity plays important part in my mind.
When my subconscious thinks keeping appearances is important, seeing a
geeky-sounding statement just automatically make it blabber &quot;that sounds
fun&quot;. Although I try to keep my narcissism in check, occasional slips
are a thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another thing that I think I consider fun is &quot;fixing&quot; something. It is
quite possible to mark me as a control freak; although I won&apos;t
voluntarily accept in a normal setting. I do however occasionally attain
rather strong opinions about how certain things shall be. When I see an
opportunity to &quot;fix&quot; something to my definition of right, that is a
strong motivational force. However unreliable it might be, working with
motivation is fun.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>that-sounds-fun</guid>
            <pubDate>2018-09-11T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Some random thoughts</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/some-random-thoughts</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Life can be so overwhelming sometimes. Sometime I wonder how people go
on about living without asking questions. Or may be they do ask
questions but get satisfied by the answers world has to offer. So much
in the world goes around these questions after all. Religions and
nations for example. Who&apos;d believe in such farcicality if there were
proper answers. Purposelessness is painful. So is loneliness. I seem to
have plenty of both of them. And then there is paranoia and laziness.
Latter two are mostly the reasons for former two. Inability to trust
anyone and jumping to the worst keep me away from most people. Laziness
keep me from diving into anything engaging enough to forget that it&apos;s
all meaningless.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Laziness now, may be I can do something about it. I have been practicing
with rituals as of late. They work well 60% of the time, today however I
failed them drastically. May be tomorrow will be a stronger day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think there is another reason for laziness as well. The work. It gets
so stupid some times. Well, most of the times it is so damn fucking
stupid. It is no fun writing forms all day long. But I need money right
now, I need a lot more than this job provides, but to start generating
more money, I need more skills. Whether I go for a better paying job or
for my own business, both need time. We&apos;re building a house, so the need
for money is immediate. I have to stick with this job for long enough to
finish the house and have some savings to give myself some period to lay
back and learn new skills, and bootstrap a business.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to what business I&apos;ll do, I am thinking to have a take on content
publishing and app building combo. I&apos;ll build apps that do something,
and I&apos;ll start a blog for each app. Apps will have premium versions via
in-app purchases, and blogs will have ads. For this I plan to first
study the competition, for which I&apos;ll build an Intenet-wide crawler to
fetch and keep information about everything that goes on in public
Internet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another plan I have is to start an app and business for farming.
Bio-farming and whatnot. I like to farm and I like Punjab. I&apos;ll like to
do something for the land.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have to get on speed with studying Haskell. I intend to start building
the Internet scanner in Haskell after I finish the 2 Haskell courses I
plan to do. After that I&apos;ll do a series of blogs for algorithms, apps,
games and Mathematics. Perhaps on farming and immigration out of India
as well. Basically everything that I want to do, I&apos;ll turn it into a
blog.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sometime I want to just hit the road and live a traveler&apos;s life. I know
it sound obscene for I hate to travel, but constant change keep me from
falling into limbo, thinking how utterly meaningless everything is. I
guess that&apos;s how people go about their lives. There are so many problems
everyone have to deal with, there is no time or energy left to indulge
in this bullshit. Specially given that there is much more juicy bullshit
for most to indulge in; love, family, power, politics, nationality, and
the one bullshit to rule them all, religion.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>some-random-thoughts</guid>
            <pubDate>2016-09-30T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Losing to Nothingness</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/losing-to-nothingness</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Couple weeks back I executed my plan to return to Chandigarh. The plan
was to take a break from work and relax for a bit, teach myself some new
skills. The real life butted in and I haven&apos;t started the phase 2 yet,
but the change was big and I am feeling the affects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I strive to build bubbles of order in midst of chaos that is life, but
what&apos;s still a mystery to me is why change give me a high. Bigger the
change higher the crest. In my final days in Bangalore I was almost at
the deepest of the limbo; shifting almost brought me back on track. The
crest is usually temporary, I am certain same is the case this time as
well. Usually I meet equally deep troughs. Just thinking of it give me
the chills.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However, something is different this time. I am ought to be on a high,
yet I am feeling the pull of a trough. It feels even weirder than it
sounds. I feel very peaceful, yet there is this unanswerable
restlessness. I feel an insatiable hunger at all times, as if there is a
big void in middle my stomach which is pulling my abdomen inside. The
peace is such I could die right now and not have a single regret, not a
thing I want to do more or different. Same time there is this alarm that
just keep ringing for all the things I have left undone. All the
promises to be fulfilled.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Duality yet has some constants, some patterns are emerging. I am living
on 6th floor these days. It provide quite a demi-god view of the
neighborhood; looking at automated people, day in and day out. It raise
so many questions; so much of my own life is just acting on impulses. An
unclear realization is rendering so much of life to nothingness. It&apos;s
like I&apos;ve reached a conclusion, I don&apos;t know to what. I don&apos;t know what
it is. A cluster of thoughts I can&apos;t tell apart. Perhaps this is how it
feel like when entering the actual madness.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I fear most is that I might be concluding life. It is becoming
harder and harder to convince myself to live for gathering things. I&apos;ve
always had a loose grip on reality, now I am fighting to hang on to
however little I have left. Paranoia and delusions are coming back.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It feels like a storm is approaching, yet it&apos;s so calm. I am dreadfully
afraid, but something in me is welcoming it. May be this is the eye of
the storm I am in. It sure feel like somewhere there&apos;s a clock, ticking.
There is so much going on in my silly little head, and there is this
emptiness sucking me in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I fear I might be losing to this nothingness. I am scared the peace is
temporary, but the chaos is just getting started.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>losing-to-nothingness</guid>
            <pubDate>2016-08-23T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>My overplanning nature and how it help me</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/my-overplanning-nature-and-how-it-help-me</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Although I try my best to not fall in the conformist&apos;s trap, there is
always a force lurking right beneath the conscious which want me to fit
in. I remember my obsession for control and planning from quite early
childhood. It used to be a major source of frustration; not that I was
obsessive about planning things, but that everyone else was not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time I figured it was me who was the odd one; so I subconsciously
started suppressing this (over?)planning nature of mine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And supressed it was, until I started writing software. I found that
properly planning things out before writing the software was immensely
helpful. Writing every unique use case, all the nuances, things to do
and things not to do; all of them helped when writing actual code.
Proper planning would make writing software so much more smoother.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But it didn&apos;t put me on the path to undo the supression I had done for
years; it merely put a doubt. I was still in doubt if I was the odd one
here, may be I am just wasting time writing every detail down up front.
May be it helped me only because it would satisfy my over planning
nature which would then let me code in peace. So I wouldn&apos;t do it every
time. Even though the results were obvious as daylight, the doubt would
have me not write specs in so many cases. Laziness didn&apos;t help either;
it&apos;s far more fun to just start writing code then it is to write specs.
As a matter of fact, thinking and writing all the small details become
painful on times.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To my great surprise, all it took was a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20161117174710/http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000036.html&quot;&gt;single
blog post&lt;/a&gt; (well, actually 5 blog posts from a single series) to pull
this doubt out of me, to take away all the confusion and bring the
clarity that I knew the right thing to do all along. There are still
things to learn, &quot;where to draw the line?&quot; for instance. But that is the
fun part. Hard part will be to write specs for every software I write,
defeating the laziness; which unfortunatley has become a big part of me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wish more programmers would blog about thier learnings and experiences
and struggles. That blog post I linked about was written in 2000, and it
came to my attention following another post on the same blog which
someone linked in a chat group. May be I am the odd one here; I don&apos;t
exactly have a team of developers working together, learning together.
But I am certain I am not alone. I hope my posts help someone realise
they&apos;re not alone if they have struggles similar as mine.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>my-overplanning-nature-and-how-it-help-me</guid>
            <pubDate>2016-06-23T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Debt of my rebellion</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/debt-of-my-rebellion</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
Most of my school life I was very confused, depressed perhaps. I was a &quot;good
boy&quot;, as they call those traumatized, obedient kids. Confusion started turning
into frustration by the end of my 10th standard. It was the &quot;board&quot; class.
Nonsensical pressure, corporal punishment and stupid as fuck rules had started
turning my depression into anger. So much pressure was put on by that &lt;a href=&quot;https://sasacademy.com&quot;&gt;shithole
of a school&lt;/a&gt; that one of my classmates had a mental breakdown. A guy went
complete nuts. That was the final nail in the coffin.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I felt like it was my turn next. So I rebelled. Against everything that
didn&apos;t make sense to me. Unfortunate for me, one of the foes in my
rebellion was Mathematics. The dull, complex subject whose applications
I couldn&apos;t understand. My teachers failed to convince me it was ever
going to have a practical application at all. All they could come up
with was &quot;competitive exams need it&quot;. But that won&apos;t make the cut.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a year of being a total brat, I finally pushed my parents to sell
a cow and buy me a computer. Computers always fascinated me, even though
I had used Computers only for a total of 10-12 hours max (occasional
15-20 minutes sittings in IT lab). I taught myself Python from the
ebooks I would download on my rare visits to cyber-cafe in nearest city.
It was a revelation. I didn&apos;t need those stupid teachers anymore; there
was no need to go through all the frustration, frowned looks and grudges
(which often lead to physical punishment) from the teachers. I could
teach myself better, faster. Unfortunate side effect of this
realization: I didn&apos;t need a shiny college.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Not going to college however was not an option. My parents were giving me enough
pain already for using computer too much (despite the fact that I was good at
school AND helped at home and farm as well). So I went for admission in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dgc.edu.in/&quot;&gt;one of
those piece of shit colleges which let anyone in for a big some of money&lt;/a&gt;.
Another story for another day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I could teach myself everything I needed. I was perhaps right about
that. But there was nobody to tell me what to learn. By the time I got
Internet I was making enough side money building software to pay for my
ever growing list of re-appears. I didn&apos;t see no math used anywhere.
When I got Internet, I started making websites. Again, no math to be
seen anywhere. The college was as shitty as they get. They never really
taught any of the syllabus (DS, algorithms etc). So I ignored them as
mumbo-jumbo schools put in their books to make money. I was making more
money than most lecturers in that college, I didn&apos;t care.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In 2014 I graduated, and went for full time freelancing. It took me some
time till I reached my limit; when I felt brute forcing my way through
problems wasn&apos;t really efficient. It was boring. It was becoming more
and more obvious that I was plateauing. I started realizing that there
are better ways to do things, and so many of them have already been
discovered.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But now the playtime was over. I was no longer in college, I had to
support myself; and my family (they&apos;re not very good financially). So I
continued freelancing. It was paying much more than most approaching
companies were offering, clients were happy, so what the hell, I
thought. I planned to save some amount in bank, and then I was to take
few months off to go back to square one and learn CS theory and
Mathemetics. I reached there 3 months ago. But then life did what it
always do. 2 big expenses came up and cleared most of my savings. So I
continued with freelancing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But I guess it&apos;s about time I put my original plan in action. I have
started getting the good ol&apos; limbo feeling again. I used to think it was
my indiscipline which make me feel like shit. But now I think it isn&apos;t.
Most of the time I have to discipline myself to get away from the
computer. When I start needing to force myself to code, it&apos;s because
something somewhere is wrong. I think I&apos;ve hit another plateau (this
realization (that it&apos;s not indiscipline that put me in limbo) itself was
a load off my chest, but a story for another time).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have savings to last for only a couple months without work, but I
guess that&apos;ll have to do. It&apos;s funny deja-vu situation actually. I was
in similar situation when I headed for Bangalore. Back to square one I
guess. I think it&apos;s time to put a pause on freelancing, and pay the debt
of my rebellion.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>debt-of-my-rebellion</guid>
            <pubDate>2016-06-11T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Directionless Wandering</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/directionless-wandering-cursed-by-dreams</link>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;
It has been about five years since I first got my computer. Endless
hours I have spent in front of the two dimensional rectangle, the third
world. Before I got the machine, most of my time was spent in the world
inside my head. My thoughts, feelings, sensations and so many things. I
was never at rest. Then I got the machine. I had dreamed of it for like
years before I got one. I was excited, fascinated. There were so many
things in my mind to do with the computer, so many plans of changing the
world. I couldn&apos;t harness any of them. Now it feels like every dream I
had back then has become a burden on my shoulders, depressing me, making
my feet heavy. Keeping me from moving forward. I am feeling powerless,
like I am losing a bit of life with every failed dream. I&apos;m getting
frightened from dreaming. What have it brought to me other than burden?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Clarity of thoughts was never my strength, but nowadays I am feeling
much more puzzled. Lost. Like I am stuck. World is leaving me behind.
I&apos;ve always seen the world like a witness. The third person standing on
the shore looking at the fishes racing, the canaries flying. Something
has happened. Making me feel as I am in the middle of the race I always
witnessed. Just witnessed. Never participated. Not even as audience. I
blame dreams. The fallen ones.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday on reddit I found a name for my madness. Existential
Depression they call it. It made me believe I am not the only one
feeling this. There are others. There might be others who have gone
through the path I am on now. May be they could give me a tip or two.
Here I am outside my diary, writing in public.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have been into computers for so long. And yet I found myself no where.
So much time I have put into programming, operating systems, security,
psychology and so many other things. All seem wasted. It is depressing
to just look at all the mess I have made of me. I see people so less
talented than me, with no knowledge of what they are doing, even doing
it wrong, crossing me in terms of success. They are richer, happier, and
better than me. I know I can do what they are doing 10 times better, but
I don&apos;t. Instead of motivating me, it is drowning me even deeper. I feel
no motivation to finish any project I start. And when the unfinished
gets piled up, they haunt me. They make me angry and depressed. I can&apos;t
remember how many times I swiped my hard disk to get rid of the
unfinished &apos;awesome&apos; projects I thought will change the world. So many
half written poems whose traces can&apos;t be found now in the burnt
notebooks. It sucks. I feel like every single thought I had, every new
idea I ever failed has cursed me. I have a trembling feeling just
thinking about thinking something new.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So many techniques I tried. So many psychology papers, books I read.
Still I am here. Another trough. I&apos;ve tried the GTD (Getting Things
Done) and the concept of &apos;limited willpower&apos;. Wrote all my mess down.
Tried to minimize the decision making. And so much more. This fucking
wave is just not leaving me. I find myself stuck in the crests and
troughs all the time. I am on the top of sky when on a crest. Have so
many new ideas, start new projects. Start reading new books. New
programming languages. New frameworks. New poets. And then it all start
fading. Then come the phase when I try to balance things. And just when
I feel I can do it, I find myself in middle of a trough. The disgust and
depression of it is just killing. I do many stupid things in troughs.
All failures. May be writing this blog post is one of them. May be after
some hours I will start feeling ashamed of writing such a thing, and
delete it. It just sucks to be here. I know it will pass. It always do.
But it leave behind scars. Scars that will keep scaring me from thinking
new ideas, from dreaming. And I think this might be the lesson. Dreams
suck.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>directionless-wandering-cursed-by-dreams</guid>
            <pubDate>2013-09-30T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>