<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts tagged `functional-programming&apos;</title>
        <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        <generator>cl-ownpress</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <image>
            <title>Posts tagged `functional-programming&apos;</title>
            <url>/images/avatar.png</url>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/</link>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>Find a functional programmer for your Javascript team</title>
            <link>https://bitspook.in/blog/find-a-functional-programmer-for-your-javascript-team/</link>
            <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Written below are some opinions and rationalizations for them. I have come to
these opinions by interviewing and working with people for years. However
strongly I feel about them, they can still be wrong. If you have feedback for
these, please do contact me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/bitspook&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bitspook&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. All kind of feedback is
very much appreciated.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From &quot;Functional programmer&quot; I mean a programmer familiar with concepts of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Functional_programming&quot;&gt;functional programming&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A good teammate is someone:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Who takes care of themselves&lt;/b&gt;. They invest in themselves. They care
about their software as a craft, as something more than just cramming
a whole bunch of frameworks and libraries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Who take care of their teammates&lt;/b&gt;.

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They help their teammates grow, by mentoring and/or by serving as
an example&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are empathetic towards other developers. This is most visible
in kind of code a person writes. An empathetic developer writes
code for other people.

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They give preference to readability of code over
micro-optimizations that make them feel clever&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They write modular code with independent modules each of which do
one thing well. And are easily composed to build more complex
functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They write clean, predictable and intuitive APIs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
FP is steadily gaining popularity, but it is still not popular enough to
breach the talent pool I get to interview from. Familiarity with FP is a
very good indication that the person invest in themselves. And they do
that in a manner which goes beyond just increasing the number of
&quot;frameworks&quot; they have built a Todo App in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Developer empathy is surprisingly rare. In almost a decade of writing
code, I have met so few developers who really give a fuck that someone
else will also read their abomination. Most software is written in
vacuum. Familiarity with FP don&apos;t fix that magically.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However there is another factor at play here. Ironically, as a
side-effect of FP, code written in a functional manner is often a lot
more readable than its imperative and OOP equivalents (Impromptu quiz:
What&apos;s so ironic about this statement?). Not only is functional code
itself naturally declarative, an FP person is more likely to wtf when
they see unreadable code in PR reviews.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Basic principles of FP also make for great advice for inexperienced
developers. Good software architecture is hard to learn, it is a lot
harder to teach. You need a mind capable of holding large amounts of
complex code before the fancy design patterns even start making sense.
In comparison, &quot;pure functions + composition&quot; and you are good to go.
That is it. That is all you need to know to get started with writing
modular, testable, simple code; which is easy to write and easier to
maintain. As a mere side effect of avoiding side effects, you write
naturally &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SOLID&quot;&gt;SOLID&lt;/a&gt; (in spirit)
code.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
FP is not a silver bullet, but looking for functional programmers skew
the universe in your favor a little. You are a lot more likely to get
good people among functional programmers.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <author>Charanjit Singh</author>
            <category>blog</category>
            <guid>find-a-functional-programmer-for-your-javascript-team</guid>
            <pubDate>2020-11-07T05:30:00.000000+05:30</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>